<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.745399</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Magnetostratigraphy and biostratigraphy of ODP Leg 105 sites and DSDP Hole 12-112</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Magnetostratigraphic and biostratigraphic synthesis of Ocean Drilling Program Leg 105: Labrador Sea and Baffin Bay</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>During Ocean Drilling Program (ODP) Leg 105, three sites (Sites 645 through 647) were drilled in Baffin Bay and the Labrador Sea to examine the tectonic evolution and the climatic and oceanic histories of this region. Biostratigraphic and magnetostratigraphic results vary at each site, while stratigraphic resolution depends on the limited abundance of marker species and the completeness of the paleomagnetic record. Because of the paucity of planktonic microfossils and the poor paleomagnetic record signatures, stratigraphic determinations at Site 645 often rely on defining minimum temporal constraints on specific samples or stratigraphic intervals. The completed stratigraphy indicates that the sedimentary sequence recovered at Site 645 is early Miocene to Holocene in age.The magnetostratigraphy and biostratigraphies are better defined at Sites 646 and 647 in the Labrador Sea. Site 646 generally contains a well-developed magnetostratigraphy and calcareous microfossil biostratigraphy. This biostratigraphy is based on calcareous nannofossils and planktonic foraminifers typical of the North Atlantic Ocean. Siliceous microfossils are also present at Site 646, but they are restricted to upper Pliocene through Holocene sediments. The stratigraphic sequence recovered at Site 646 is late Miocene to Holocene in age. Based primarily on the calcareous nannofossil stratigraphy, the sequence recovered at Site 647 consists of lower Eocene to lower Oligocene, lower Miocene, upper Miocene, and upper Pliocene through Holocene sediments. Three hiatuses are present in this sequence: the older hiatus separates lower Oligocene sediments from lower Miocene sediments, another hiatus separates lower Miocene sediments from upper Miocene sediments, and the youngest one separates upper Miocene from upper Pliocene sediments. A magnetostratigraphy is defined for the interval from the Gauss/Matuyama boundary through the Brunhes (Clement et al., this volume). Both planktonic foraminifers and siliceous microfossils have restricted occurrences. Planktonic foraminifers occur in Pliocene and younger sediments, and siliceous microfossils are present in lower Miocene and lower Oligocene sediments.The near-continuous Eocene through lower Oligocene sequence recovered at Site 647 allows the calcareous nannofossils and diatom stratigraphies at this site to act as a Paleogene stratigraphic framework. This framework can be compared with the stratigraphy previously completed for DSDP Site 112.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>DSDP</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>105-646</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment>91 cores, 869.7 m cored, 0 m drilled, 57.1% recovery</md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Sample code/label | Sample label | ODP sample designation | Sample code/label 2 | Sample label 2 | Depth, top/min | Depth top | Depth, bottom/max | Depth bot | FO = first occurrence, LO = last occurrence, LCO = last common occurrence, D-S = dextral-sinistral, occ. = occurrence | Ageprofile Datum Description | Ageprof dat des</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>1989-09-21T10:30:19</date></data>