<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.905428</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Curie Depth and geothermal heat flux of the Scotia Sea</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title /><md:MetaData/md:abstract>The sinking of the ocean sea bottom is produced by thermal cooling of the lithosphere. This evolution is determined by the underlying asthenospheric mantle. Estimation of the Curie Depth variations in the Scotia Sea by using a spectral approach and applied on magnetic anomaly data led us to determine a thermal model and derive a heat flux map. Using multichannel seismic and bathymetry data, we show that the West Scotia Sea reaches thermal equilibrium more quickly than other oceans do and thermally behaves like old oceanic crust in large oceans, following a different empirical age (t, in Ma) - depth (d, in m) relationship, d(t)=4480-19380exp(-t&#8260;4). For oceanic crusts of the same age, underlain by different shallow mantle controlling the heat supply, low heat flux values imply older ages than those predicted for large oceans based on the empirical relationships of the standard plate model. These circumstances, together with the new heat flux map, shed light on the anomalous evolution of the Scotia Sea, a consequence of the present Pacific mantle outflow through the Drake Passage. Two branches of elevated heat flux surround the Shackleton Fracture Zone and extend to the northern and southern boundaries of the Scotia Plate. Most of the heat sources are located in the flanks, whereas the colder parts are centrally located. This signature supports the Drake Passage's role as a main mantle gateway for Pacific outflow towards the Atlantic reservoir favoring the oceanic spreading activity of this ocean.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>Scotia_Sea_area</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-4.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Curie point depth | CPD | Heat flow | HF</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>2019-09-02T08:46:47</date></data>