<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.856585</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Stable carbon and oxygen isotope record of IODP Site 306-U1313, MIS 23-19</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>The Marine Isotope Stage 19 in the mid-latitude North Atlantic Ocean: astronomical signature and intra-interglacial variability</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Since the seminal work by Hays et al. (1976), a plethora of studies has demonstrated a correlation between orbital variations and climatic change. However, information on how changes in orbital boundary conditions affected the frequency and amplitude of millennial-scale climate variability is still fragmentary. The Marine Isotope Stage (MIS) 19, an interglacial centred at around 785 ka, provides an opportunity to pursue this question and test the hypothesis that the long-term processes set up the boundary conditions within which the short-term processes operate. Similarly to the current interglacial, MIS 19 is characterised by a minimum of the 400-kyr eccentricity cycle, subdued amplitude of precessional changes, and small amplitude variations in insolation. Here we examine the record of climatic conditions during MIS 19 using high-resolution stable isotope records from benthic and planktonic foraminifera from a sedimentary sequence in the North Atlantic (Integrated Ocean Drilling Program Expedition 306, Site U1313) in order to assess the stability and duration of this interglacial, and evaluate the climate system's response in the millennial band to known orbitally induced insolation changes. Benthic and planktonic foraminiferal d18O values indicate relatively stable conditions during the peak warmth of MIS 19, but sea-surface and deep-water reconstructions start diverging during the transition towards the glacial MIS 18, when large, cold excursions disrupt the surface waters whereas low amplitude millennial scale fluctuations persist in the deep waters as recorded by the oxygen isotope signal. The glacial inception occurred at ~779 ka, in agreement with an increased abundance of tetra-unsaturated alkenones, reflecting the influence of icebergs and associated meltwater pulses and high-latitude waters at the study site. After having combined the new results with previous data from the same site, and using a variety of time series analysis techniques, we evaluate the evolution of millennial climate variability in response to changing orbital boundary conditions during the Early-Middle Pleistocene. Suborbital variability in both surface- and deep-water records is mainly concentrated at a period of ~11 kyr and, additionally, at ~5.8 and ~3.9 kyr in the deep ocean, these periods are equal to harmonics of precession band oscillations. The fact that the response at the 11 kyr period increased over the same interval during which the amplitude of the response to the precessional cycle increased supports the notion that most of the variance in the 11 kyr band in the sedimentary record is nonlinearly transferred from precession band oscillations. Considering that these periodicities are important features in the equatorial and intertropical insolation, these observations are in line with the view that the low-latitude regions play an important role in the response of the climate system to the astronomical forcing. We conclude that the effect of the orbitally induced insolation is of fundamental importance in regulating the timing and amplitude of millennial scale climate variability.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>IODP</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Naafs et al. (2012) | Depth, composite revised | Depth cr | Intercore correlation | Expedition 306 Scientistst (2006) | Depth, composite | Depth comp | Sample code/label | Sample label | ODP sample designation | with respect to VPDB, size fraction &gt;212 &#181;m | Cibicidoides wuellerstorfi, &#948;18O | C. wuellerstorfi &#948;18O | Mass spectrometer Finnigan MAT 252 | Cibicidoides wuellerstorfi, &#948;13C | C. wuellerstorfi &#948;13C | Cibicidoides spp., &#948;18O | Cibicidoides spp. &#948;18O | Cibicidoides spp., &#948;13C | Cibicidoides spp. &#948;13C | Uvigerina spp., &#948;18O | Uvigerina spp. &#948;18O | Uvigerina spp., &#948;13C | Uvigerina spp. &#948;13C | C. wuellerstorfi + 0.64 per mil | &#948;18O, adjusted/corrected | &#948;18O | Calculated | Uvigerina spp. + 0.9 per mil | &#948;13C, adjusted/corrected | &#948;13C | with respect to VPDB, size fraction 315-355 &#181;m | Globigerina bulloides, &#948;18O | G. bulloides &#948;18O</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>2015-01-04T13:12:30</date></data>