<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.807552</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Phytoplankton abundance during L'Atalante cruise EBENE</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Picophytoplankton abundance and biomass in the western tropical Pacific Ocean during the 1992 El Ni&#241;o year: results from flow cytometry</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Natural populations of phytoplankton from the western tropical Pacific Ocean were analyzed by flow cytometry from a transect along 165&#176;E between 20&#176;S and 7&#176;N. The abnormal hydrological situation corresponded to a weak El Ni&#241;o event, with no equatorial upwelling and a marked nutrient ridge centered on 10&#176;S. Prochlorophytes dominated numerically everywhere along the vertical, whatever the depth, in the 0-160-m layer (96% of cell abundance). Paradoxically, the highest concentrations, up to 4.4 x 10**5 cells/ml, were found in oligotrophic waters (&lt; 0.1 &#181;M NO3). In contrast, the highest concentrations of orange cyanobacteria and redfluorescing picoeukaryotes were observed when nitrate was present in the photic layer, i.e. around 10&#176;S (up to 6.4 x 10**4 cells/ml and 1.3 x 10**4 cells/ml), and, to a lesser extent in the vicinity of the deep nitracline north of 8&#176;S. Along the transect we encountered two hydrological situations, characterized by different community structures. The first one, found from 15&#176;S to 7&#176;N, except at 10&#176;S, was a two-layer structure (Typical Tropical Structure, TTS) defined by a strong pycnocline in the upper 180 m and a well-marked nitracline. In this region, Prochlorococcus and picoeukaryotes co-dominated the 180-m integrated fluorescence and carbon biomass, but Prochlorococcus were the major component in the upper nitrate-depleted layer, while picoeukaryotes dominated the underlying rich layer. Inversely, Synechococcus were a relatively minor contributor to fluorescence (~4%) and phytoplankton biomass (&lt; 1%) in comparison to the other cell types. The second structure observed in the southernmost part of the transect (20&#176;S-16&#176;S) was defined by the absence of a density gradient, and therefore by deep vertical mixing. In this case, the concentration of Prochlorococcus in the upper nitrate-depleted layer was reduced, whereas Synechococcus percentage contribution in the upper 180 m was significantly higher than in the TTS ( &gt; 30% of total fluorescence and ~4% of carbon biomass). According to our results, we discuss the expected role of each phytoplankton group in the regenerated and new production. Finally, we discuss the importance of cell size as a factor in the expected roles of the different phytoplankton groups in the carbon sink.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>JGOFS</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>EBENE_001</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent /><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>1996-02-19T11:12:16</date></data>