<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.883742</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Congo River particulate and dissolved organic carbon concentrations, isotope compositions (&#948;&#185;&#179;C, d15N, D14C), and particulate GDGT distributions</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Hydrologic controls on seasonal and inter-annual variability of Congo River particulate organic matter source and reservoir age</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>We present dissolved organic carbon (DOC) concentrations, particulate organic matter (POM) composition (d13C, d15N, D14C, N/C), and particulate glycerol dialkyl glycerol tetraether (GDGT) distributions from a 34-month time-series near the mouth of the Congo River. An end-member mixing model using d13C and N/C indicates that exported POM is consistently dominated by C3 rainforest soil sources, with increasing contribution from C3 vegetation and decreasing contribution from phytoplankton at high discharge. Large C4 inputs are never observed despite covering ~ 13% of the catchment. Low and variable D14C values during 2011 [annual mean = (-148 &#177; 82) per mil], when discharge from left-bank tributaries located in the southern hemisphere reached record lows, likely reflect a bias toward pre-aged POM derived from the Cuvette Congolaise swamp forest. In contrast, D14C values were stable near -50 per mil between January and June 2013, when left-bank discharge was highest. We suggest that headwater POM is replaced and/or diluted by C3 vegetation and pre-aged soils during transit through the Cuvette Congolaise, whereas left-bank tributaries export significantly less pre-aged material. GDGT distributions provide further evidence for seasonal and inter-annual variability in soil provenance. The cyclization of branched tetraethers and the GDGT-0 to crenarchaeol ratio are positively correlated with discharge (r &gt;=0.70, p-value &lt;= 4.3 &#215; 10**-5) due to the incorporation of swamp-forest soils when discharge from right-bank tributaries located in the northern hemisphere is high. Both metrics reach record lows during 2013, supporting our interpretation of increased left-bank contribution at this time. We conclude that hydrologic variability is a major control of POM provenance in the Congo River Basin and that tropical wetlands can be a significant POM source despite their small geographic coverage.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>River discharge | Q | MATBraz | Temperature, air, calculated | T air calc | Surface water temperatures (Triv) | Temperature, water | Temp | riv + | pH | Carbon, organic, dissolved | DOC | * | Carbon, organic, particulate | POC | OC mean | Carbon, organic, total | TOC | Standard deviation | Std dev | mean | Nitrogen, organic | N org | mean, vs. VPDB | &#948;13C | &#948;13C, standard deviation | &#948;13C std dev | mean, vs. per mil air | &#948;15N | &#948;15N, standard deviation | &#948;15N std dev | molar | Nitrogen/Carbon ratio | N/C | &#916;14C | &#916;14C, standard deviation | &#916;14C std dev | Crenarchaeol isomer, fractional abundance | GDGT-5 iso | Caldarchaeol isomer, fractional abundance | GDGT I iso | Branched Glycerol dialkyl glycerol tetraethers, fractional abundance Ia | brGDGT f(Ia) | Branched Glycerol dialkyl glycerol tetraethers, fractional abundance Ib | brGDGT f(Ib) | Branched Glycerol dialkyl glycerol tetraethers, fractional abundance Ic | brGDGT f(Ic) | Branched Glycerol dialkyl glycerol tetraethers, fractional abundance IIa | brGDGT f(IIa) | Branched Glycerol dialkyl glycerol tetraethers, fractional abundance IIb | brGDGT f(IIb) | Branched Glycerol dialkyl glycerol tetraethers, fractional abundance IIc | brGDGT f(IIc) | Branched Glycerol dialkyl glycerol tetraethers, fractional abundance IIIa | brGDGT f(IIIa) | Branched Glycerol dialkyl glycerol tetraethers, fractional abundance IIIb | brGDGT f(IIIb) | Methylation index of dominant branched tetraethers | MBT' | Cyclization ratio of branched tetraethers | CBT | GDGT-0/cren, mean | Ratio | C3 soils, fractional contribution | C3 soil fr | C3 vegetation, fractional contribution | C3 veg fr | Phytoplankton, fractional contribution | Phytopl fr | Reference/source | Reference</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title>Extras to: Hydrologic controls on seasonal and inter-annual variability of Congo River particulate organic matter source and reservoir age</md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title><date>2017-12-04T12:43:06</date></data>