<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.816252</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>(Table 1) Mineralogical composition of sediments from DSDP Sites 69-504 and 69-505</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Mineralogy of sediments encountered during Deep Sea Drilling Project Leg 69 (Costa Rica Rift, Panama Basin), as determined by x-ray diffraction</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>We discuss the provenance of minerals detected by X-ray-diffraction analyses of sediments of Sites 504 and 505 of Deep Sea Drilling Project Leg 69. These are X-ray-amorphous material, opal-CT, calcite, quartz, feldspar, apatite, smectite, illite, kaolinite, magnetite, maghemite, pyrite, marcasite, barite, sepiolite, and clinoptilolite. Authigenic marcasite and clinoptilolite together with opal-CT are restricted to Site 504, indicating the special diagenetic conditions related to relatively high sediment temperatures at this site. Marcasite formation is likely dependent on the relatively low pH values of &lt;7.1 found in interstitial waters of Site 504 sediments below 50 meters sub-bottom. Clinoptilolite evidently was formed by diagenetic alteration of rhyolitic volcanic glass or smectite plus biogenic silica within the chalk-limestone-chert sequence of Site 504, where opal-CT also reflects a high degree of silica dissolution and reprecipitation. This was a consequence of high temperatures (50-55 &#176;C) at the base of the sediment column.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>DSDP</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>69-504</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment>26 cores, 223 m cored, 0 m drilled, 83.9 % recovery</md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent /><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>1983-07-01T22:06:35</date></data>