<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.785096</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Texture analyses of ODP Site 131-808 sediments</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Textures and microfabrics in fine-grained muds and mudstones from Site 808, Nankai accretionary prism</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>The microfabric of 11 mudrock specimens from ODP Site 808 (Nankai accretionary prism) was quantitatively analyzed using X-ray texture goniometry and optical petrography. The objectives of the study were to learn about rock strain and to detect a component of bulk lateral shortening in the deformation of the mudstones. Strain evaluation is based on the predictions of March theory, and on distortions of initially homogeneous marker particle distributions (the Fry technique). The main results are as follows. The specimens underwent a strain path of progressive flattening, which is closely related to loss of pore space by vertical loading. A component of bulk lateral shortening is detectable in the top 550 mbsf at Site 808, but compared with the amount of uniaxial vertical shortening, its relative magnitude is probably small. Moreover, it cannot be said with confidence whether this is caused by toe contraction of the accretionary wedge or by gravitationally induced downslope movement of the sediment pile. The mudstones examined were deposited in a marine environment with an oxic bottom water column.Micropore collapse is an important fabric building mechanism, but below 400 mbsf its effects are at least partly overridden by recrystallization of smectite. We conclude that mud microfabrics are not very precise deformation gauges, but can be used for rough estimations of strain.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>ODP</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>131-808A</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment>13 cores, 111.4 m cored, 0 m drilled, 79.6 % recovery</md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Sample code/label | Sample label | ODP sample designation | Method comment | Method comm | #1, maximum intensity of diffracted x-ray beam parallel to core axis | Intensity | #2, maximum intensity of diffracted x-ray beam parallel to core axis | Ratio | Fry-technique (Fry 1979) | PODI-technique (Unzog 1990) | Uniaxial shortening | e(z) | Type | f(max)( = maximum occurrence of illite (001) traces | Illite | Ill | March (1932) model | f(uniform) = uniform occurrence of illite (001) traces | #1, f(max)/f(uniform)e(z) | #2, f(max)/f(uniform) e(z)</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>1993-06-27T10:22:28</date></data>