<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.754885</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Absolute abundances of dinoflagellate cysts in surface sediment samples from four sites: Lycopodium marker-grain method</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Determining the absolute abundance of dinoflagellate cysts in recent marine sediments: The Lycopodium marker-grain method put to the test</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Absolute abundances (concentrations) of dinoflagellate cysts are often determined through the addition of Lycopodium clavatum marker-grains as a spike to a sample before palynological processing. An inter-laboratory calibration exercise was set up in order to test the comparability of results obtained in different laboratories, each using its own preparation method. Each of the 23 laboratories received the same amount of homogenized splits of four Quaternary sediment samples. The samples originate from different localities and consisted of a variety of lithologies. Dinoflagellate cysts were extracted and counted, and relative and absolute abundances were calculated. The relative abundances proved to be fairly reproducible, notwithstanding a need for taxonomic calibration. By contrast, excessive loss of Lycopodium spores during sample preparation resulted in non-reproducibility of absolute abundances. Use of oxidation, KOH, warm acids, acetolysis, mesh sizes larger than 15 &#181;m and long ultrasonication (&gt; 1 min) must be avoided to determine reproducible absolute abundances. The results of this work therefore indicate that the dinoflagellate cyst worker should make a choice between using the proposed standard method which circumvents critical steps, adding Lycopodium tablets at the end of the preparation and using an alternative method.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>GeoB</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>Benguela</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment>The Benguela sample consists of a mixture of sediment samples collected offshore Walvis Bay, at a water depth of about 200 m during Meteor cruise M63/2.</md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Species | see reference(s) | 1a/First 300 dinocysts | Laboratory | Lab | Lycopodium marker-grain method | 1a/Extra 100 | 16/First 300 dinocysts | 16/Extra 100 | 12/First 300 dinocysts | 12/Extra 100 | 13/First 300 dinocysts | 13/Extra 100 | 19/First 300 dinocysts | 19/Extra 100 | 9/First 300 dinocysts | 9/Extra 101 | 5/First 300 dinocysts | 5/Extra 100 | 11/First 300 dinocysts | 11/Extra 100 | 22a/First 300 dinocysts | 22a/Extra 100 | 22b/First 300 dinocysts | 22b/Extra 100 | 18a/First 300 dinocysts | 18a/Extra 100 | 10b/First 300 dinocysts | 10b/Extra 100 | 10a/First 300 dinocysts | 10a/Extra 100 | 2/First 300 dinocysts | 15b/First 300 dinocysts | 23/First 300 dinocysts | 4/First 300 dinocysts | 17/First 300 dinocysts | 20a/First 300 dinocysts | 20b/First 300 dinocysts | 18b/First 300 dinocysts | 1b/First 300 dinocysts | 21a/First 300 dinocysts | 21b/First 300 dinocysts | 3/First 300 dinocysts | 4/Extra 100 | 6/First 300 dinocysts | 6/Extra 100 | 17/Extra 100 | 1c/First 300 dinocysts | 1c/Extra 100 | 18b/Extra 100 | 7/First 300 dinocysts | 7/Extra 100 | 1b/Extra 100 | 8/First 300 dinocysts | 8/Extra 100 | 21a/Extra 100 | 21b/Extra 100 | 3/Extra 100 | 15a/First 300 dinocysts | 14/First 300 dinocysts | 23/Extra 100 | 17 | 21/First 300 dinocysts | 21/Extra 100</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>2009-12-09T10:09:06</date></data>