<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.862541</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Multi-year weather data in the remote semi-arid to arid mountain region of the Saharan flank of the Atlas Mountains</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title /><md:MetaData/md:abstract>In 2001, a weather and climate monitoring network was established along the temperature and aridity gradient between the sub-humid Moroccan High Atlas Mountains and the former end lake of the Middle Dr&#226;a in a pre-Saharan environment. The highest Automated Weather Stations (AWS) was installed just below the M'Goun summit at 3850 m, the lowest station Lac Iriki was at 450 m. This network of 13 AWS stations was funded and maintained by the German IMPETUS (BMBF Grant 01LW06001A, North Rhine-Westphalia Grant 313-21200200) project and since 2011 five stations were further maintained by the GERMAN DFG Fennec project (FI 786/3-1), this way some stations of the AWS network provided data for almost 12 years from 2001-2012. Standard meteorological variables such as temperature, humidity, and wind were measured at an altitude of 2 m above ground. Other meteorological variables comprise precipitation, station pressure, solar irradiance, soil temperature at different depths and for high mountain station snow water equivalent. The stations produced data summaries for 5-minute-precipitation-data, 10- or 15-minute-data and a daily summary of all other variables.This network is a unique resource of multi-year weather data in the remote semi-arid to arid mountain region of the Saharan flank of the Atlas Mountains. The network is described in Schulz et al. (2010) and its further continuation until 2012 is briefly discussed in Redl et al. (2015, doi:10.1175/MWR-D-15-0223.1) and Redl et al. (2016, doi:10.1002/2015JD024443).</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-NC-SA-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Mean relative humidity (2 m above ground) for mentioned period | Humidity, relative | RH | Mean air temperature (2 m above ground) for mentioned period | Temperature, air | TTT | shortwave and longwave (2.5 m above ground) | Net radiation | NET | 2.5 m above ground | Radiation, photosynthetically active | PAR | at 5 cm depth | Soil heat flux | Mean wind speed (3 m above ground) in the mentioned period | Wind speed | ff | rain and/or melted snow | Precipitation | Precip | Maximum net radiation (2.5 m above ground) in the mentioned period | Net radiation, maximum | NET max | Time for maximum net radiation (2.5 m above ground) in the mentioned period | Time of day | Radiation, photosynthetically active, maximum | PAR max | Time for maximum photosynthetic active radiation (2.5 m above ground) in the mentioned period | Mean relative humidity (1 m above ground) for mentioned period | Mean air temperature (1 m above ground) for mentioned period | Short-wave downward (GLOBAL) radiation | SWD | Short-wave upward (REFLEX) radiation | SWU | at 15 cm depth | Mean soil temperature (5 cm depth) for mentioned period | Temperature, soil | T soil | Mean soil temperature (15 cm depth) for mentioned period | Mean soil temperature (30 cm depth) for mentioned period | at 5 cm depth (only rain event pointer) | Soil moisture | at 15 cm depth (only rain event pointer) | at 30 cm depth (only rain event pointer) | Mean wind direction in degrees (of 360 degrees) for the mentioned period (3 m above ground) | Wind direction | dd | Standard deviation of wind direction in degrees (of 360 degrees) for the mentioned period (3 m above ground) | Wind direction, standard deviation | dd std dev | Mean wind speed (1 m above ground) in the mentioned period | Station pressure | PoPoPoPo | Mean dew point (2m above ground) for the mentioned period | Dew/frost point | TdTdTd | 2.5 m above ground (corrected) | Time of maximum short-wave radiation (2.5 m above ground) in the mentioned period | 10 cm above ground | Temperature, ice/snow | t | 20 cm above ground | 30 cm above ground | 50 cm above ground | 70 cm above ground | Reference temperature inside logger box | Temperature, technical | T tech | Surface temperature corrected with apt, set and ret | Apparent target temperature (raw surface temperature) | Temperature of set sensor | on snow pillow (uncorrected) | Snow water equivalent | SWE | Minimum air temperature (2 m above ground) reported during the mentioned period | Temperature, air, minimum | TnTnTn | Time for minimum air temperature (2 m above ground) in the mentioned period | Maximum air temperature (2 m above ground) reported during the mentioned period | Temperature, air, maximum | TxTxTx | Time for maximum air temperature (2 m above ground) in the mentioned period | Minimum air temperature (1 m above ground) reported during the mentioned period | Time for minimum air temperature (1 m above ground) in the mentioned period | Maximum air temperature (1 m above ground) reported during the mentioned period | Time for maximum air temperature (1 m above ground) in the mentioned period | Maximum wind speed (1 m above ground) in the mentioned period | Wind speed, maximum | ff max | Time for maximum wind speed (1 m above ground) in the mentioned period | Maximum wind speed (3 m above ground) in the mentioned period | Time for maximum wind speed (3 m above ground) in the mentioned period | Maximum short-wave radiation (2.5 m above ground) in the mentioned period | Short-wave downward (GLOBAL) radiation, maximum | SWD max | Minimum of logger battery voltage in V in the mentioned period | Battery terminal voltage | Vbat | Minimum relative humidity (2 m above ground) for mentioned period | Humidity, relative, minimum | RH min | Time of minimum relative humidity (2 m above ground) for mentioned period | Maximum relative humidity (2 m above ground) for mentioned period | Humidity, relative, maximum | RH max | Time of maximum relative humidity (2 m above ground) for mentioned period | on snow pillow (corrected) | Snow water equivalent, maximum | SWE max | Snow water equivalent, minimum | SWE min | rain | snow</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title>An extreme precipitation event in southern Morocco in spring 2002 and some hydrological implications</md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title><date>2016-07-04T20:25:03</date></data>