<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.808038</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Organic facies of Cenozoic and Cretaceous sediments at DSDP Leg 80 Holes</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Organic facies of Cenozoic and Cretaceous sediments from Deep Sea Drilling Project Sites 548 to 551, northern North Atlantic</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>The organic facies of Cenozoic sediments cored at DSDP Sites 548-551 along the Celtic Sea margin of the northern North Atlantic (Goban Spur) is dominated by terrestrially derived plant remains and charcoal. Similar organic facies also occur in the Lower and Upper Cretaceous sections at these sites. Mid-Cretaceous (uppermost Albian-Turonian) sediments at Sites 549-551, however, record two different periods of enrichment in organic material, wherein marine organic matter was mixed with terrestrial components. The earlier period is represented only in the uppermost Albianmiddle Cenomanian section at the most seaward site, 550. Here, dark laminated marly chalks rich in organic matter occur rhythmically interbedded with light-colored, bioturbated marly chalks poor in organic matter, suggesting that bottom waters alternated between oxidizing and reducing conditions. A later period of enrichment in organic material is recorded in the upper Cenomanian-Turonian sections at Sites 549 and 551 as a single, laminated black mudstone interval containing biogenic siliceous debris. It was deposited along the margin during a time of oxygen deficiency associated with upwelling-induced intensification and expansion of the mid-water oxygen-minimum layer. In both the earlier and later events, variations in productivity appear to have been the immediate cause of oxygen depletion in the bottom waters.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>DSDP</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Sample code/label | Sample label | ODP sample designation | Lithologic unit/sequence | Unit | Stage | Calculated assuming that all inorganic carbon occurs as CaCO3 | Calcium carbonate | CaCO3 | Calculated | Carbon, organic, total | TOC | Element analyser CHN, LECO | Organic matter, amorphous | AOM | Transmission electron microscope (TEM) | Algae | Pollen and spores | Pollen+spores | Wood remains | Wood | Coal clasts or fragments | Coal clasts | Components indeterminata | Comp indet | Other | Organic remains | Org rem | Organic matter | OM | Thermal alteration index | TAI | Rock eval pyrolysis (Espitali&#233; et al. 1977) | Hydrogen index, mass HC per unit mass total organic carbon | HI, HC/TOC | Oxygen index, mass CO2 per unit mass total organic carbon | OI, CO2/TOC | Pyrolysis temperature maximum | Tmax | Soluble | Bitumen | Bitum | Hydrocarbons | HC | Unit is % | Hydrocarbons/organic carbon ratio | HC/TOC | Soluble organic matter | Saturated hydrocarbon fraction | Sat HC | Aromatic hydrocarbon fraction | Arom HC | Soluble organic matter N, S, O compounds | Asphaltenes</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>1985-02-26T11:24:09</date></data>