<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.681805</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Mid-Pliocene diatom and palynological assemblages north-northeast of Cape Adare, Antarctica</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Evidence of Pliocene Abthofagus in Antarctica from Pliocene marine sedimentary deposits (DSDP Site 274)</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Microfossil assemblages in Pliocene sediments from DSDP Site 274 (68&#176;59.81'S, 173&#176;2564'E) provide data on the age of the sediments and suggest the presence of Nothofagus (southern beach) in Antarctica during the Pliocene. A suite of 17 samples was collected in an interval from Samples 28-274-6R-1, 83-87 cm to 28-274-11R-4, 73-77 cm (48.33-100.29 mbsf). Biostratigraphic study of the abundant diatom assemblages combined with published radiolarian data indicates that the sample interval ranges in age from 5.0 to 2.2 Ma, with an apparent unconformity between about 3.8 and 3.2 Ma. Nothofagidites (the genus for fossil pollen referable to Nothofagus) occurs throughout the interval, as well as pollen and spores with known stratigraphic ranges that unequivocally indicate reworking from older rocks. Species of Nothofagidites recovered include N. asperus, N. brachyspinulosus, N. flemingii, N. senectus, and N. sp. cf. N. lachlaniae, the latter form is previously known from the Sirius Group in the Transantarctic Mountains.Abundant palynomorphs were recovered in only three of the samples from Site 274 (Samples 28-274-9R-2,15-19 cm, 28-274-9R-2,48-52 cm, and 28-274-9R-2,65-69 cm). Based on the diatom and radiolarian biostratigraphic data, the ages of these samples range from 3.00 to 3.01 Ma. The relative abundance of N. sp. cf. N. lachlaniae in the three samples is an order of magnitude higher than relative abundances for the other species of Nothofagidites in the same samples. The signiticantly higher relative abundance of N. sp. cf. N. luchlaniae suggests that this pollen was derived from trees of Nothofugus that were living in Antarctica during the mid Pliocene. Diatom assemblages from these three samples indicate that sediments in this interval were rapidly deposited as biogenic oozes in an open-ocean setting relatively free of sea ice, thus decreasing the possibility of reworking from a single source bed rich in N. sp. cf. N. lachlaniae. Clearly, more detailed work in additional well-dated cores from around Antarctica is needed before a clear picture of the Neogene history of Antarctic terrestrial vegetation emerges.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>DSDP</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>28-274</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment>43 cores, 402 m cored, 9.5 m drilled, 67 % recovery</md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Sample code/label | Sample label | ODP sample designation | U.S. Geological Survey Palynology Sample Number | Sample code/label 2 | Sample label 2 | barren = no palynomorphs recovered, spares = palynomorphs present but slide too sparse for counting, good = palynomorph assemblage recovered that is adequate for counting | Abundance | Abund | Actinocyclus actinochilus | A. actinochilus | Actinocyclus dimorphus | A. dimorphus | Actinocyclus ingens | A. ingens | Asteromphalus sp. | Chaetoceros spores | Chaet spores | Eucampia antarctica | E. antarctica | cf. N. arcula | Nitzschia sp. | Nitzschia barronii | N. barronii | N. curta - N. cylindrica | Nitzschia curta | N. curta | Nitzschia interfrigidaria | N. interfrigidaria | Nitzschia ritscheri | N. ritscheri | Nitzschia spp. | Paralia sulcata | P. sulcata | Rhizosolenia spp. | Rouxia spp. | Stephanopyxis spp. | Stellarima spp. | Thalassionema nitzschioides | T. nitzschioides | cf. T. antarctica | Thalassiosira sp. | Thalassiosira insigna | Z. insigna | Thalassiosira inura | T. inura | Thalassiosira kolbei | T. kolbei | Thalassiosira oestrupii | T. oestrupii | Thalassiosira oliverana | T. oliverana | Thalassiosira torokina | T. torokina | Thalassiosira vulnifica | T. vulnifica | Thalassiosira spp. | Thalassiothrix longissima | T. longissima | Diatoms, reworked | Diatom rew | Diatoms | Nothofagidites asperus | N. asperus | Nothofagidites brachispinulosa | N. brachispinulosa | Nothofagidites flemingii | N. flemingii | Nothofagidites lachlaniae | N. lachlaniae | Nothofagidites senectus | N. senectus | var. 1 of Truswell (1983) | Nothofagidites sp. | Nothofagidites spp. | Coptospora sp. | Leptolepidites verrucatus | L. verrucatus | cf. R. micraulaxus | Rugulatisporites sp. | Araucariacites australis | A. australis | Microcachryidites antarcticus | M. antarcticus | Phyllocladidites mawsonii | P. mawsonii | Asteropollis asteroides | A. asteroides | Dilwynites tuberculatus | D. tuberculatus | Proteacidites parvus | P. parvus | Tricolpites asperimarginatus | T. asperimarginatus | var. 4 of Truswell (1983) | Tricolpites sp. | Pollen indeterminata | Pollen indet | Spores indeterminata | Spores indet | Pollen total | Pollen tot</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>1996-02-11T13:15:19</date></data>