<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.707911</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Petrological and geochemical characteristics of DSDP Hole 37-334 gabbroic cumulates (Table 1)</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Genesis of andesitic-boninitic magmas at mid-ocean ridges by melting of hydrated peridotites: Geochemical evidence from DSDP Site 334 gabbronorites</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>The gabbronoritic cumulates drilled at DSDP Site 334 (Mid-Atlantic Ridge off the FAMOUS area) are neither crystallization products of the associated basalts, nor from any MORB composition documented along ocean ridges. Their parent melts are richer in SiO2 than MORB at a given MgO content, as attested by the crystallization sequence starting with an olivine+calcic and sub-calcic pyroxene assemblages. These melts are issued from a source highly depleted in incompatible elements, likely residual peridotite left after MORB extraction. To understand the role of water in the genesis of these lithologies whose occurrence in a mid-ocean ridge setting is rather puzzling, we performed a geochemical study on clinopyroxene separates following an analytical protocol able to remove the effects of water rock interactions post-dating their crystallization. Accordingly, the measured isotopic signatures can be used to trace magma sources. We find that Site 334 clinopyroxenes depart from the global mantle correlation: normal MORB values for the 143Nd/ 144Nd ratio (0.51307-0.51315) are associated to highly radiogenic 87Sr / 86Sr (0.7034-0.7067) ratios. This indicates that the parent melts of Site 334 cumulates are issued from a MORB source but that seawater contamination occurred at some stage of their genesis. The extent of contamination, traced by the Sr isotopic signature, is variable within all cumulates but more developed for gabbronorites sensus stricto, suggesting that seawater introduction was a continuous process during all the magmatic evolution of the system, from partial melting to fractional crystallization. Simple masse balance calculations are consistent with a contaminating agent having the characters of a highly hydrated (possibly water saturated) silica-rich melt depleted in almost all incompatible major, minor and trace elements relative to MORB. Mixing in various proportions of contaminated melts similar to the parent melts of Site 334 cumulates with MORB can account for part of the variability in the Sr isotopic signature of oceanic basalts, among other to the short wavelength isotopic ,,noise" superimposed on regional trends. We conclude that seawater introduction into residual peridotite at shallow depth beneath mid-ocean ridges can lead mantle rocks and their melts to follow complex P-T-fH2O paths that mimic petrogenetic contexts classically attributed to subduction zone environments, like the production of boninitic-andesitic magmas.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>DSDP</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent /><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>2005-11-24T14:10:43</date></data>