<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.771356</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Highly stereoselective decarboxylation of (+)-1-Bromo-1-chloro-2,2,2-trifluoropropanoic acid gives (+)-1-Bromo-1-chloro-2,2,2-trifluoroethane ((+)-Halothane) with retention of configuration</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Highly stereoselective decarboxylation of (+)-1-Bromo-1-chloro-2,2,2-trifluoropropanoic acid gives (+)-1-Bromo-1-chloro-2,2,2-trifluoroethane ((+)-Halothane) with retention of configuration</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>The absolute configuration of the title acid (2) has been determined to be S by X-ray crystallography. Thus, decarboxylation of 2 produces (S)-(+)-halothane with 99% retention of configuration. This behavior is compared to other stereoselective decarboxylation reactions of ?-haloacids from the literature that also give high degrees of retention of configuration when in the form of their quaternary ammonium salts, which contain one proton. The proton of the ammonium salt is necessary to protonate the anionic intermediate formed from decarboxylation. In the absence of this relatively acidic proton, we had previously found that using triethylene glycol (TEG) as both solvent and proton source for the decarboxylation reaction of acid 2 caused poor stereoselectivity. This was in contrast to 1,2,2,2-tetrafluoro-1-methoxypropionic acid (6), which showed a high degree of retention of configuration in TEG. To rationalize this differing behavior we report DFT studies at PCM-B3LYP/6-31++G** level of theory (the results were additionally confirmed with 6-311++G** and aug-cc-pVDZ basis sets). The energy barrier to inversion of configuration of the anionic reaction intermediate of acid 2 (11) is 10.23 kcal/mol. However, we find that the anionic intermediate from acid 6 (10) would rather undergo ?-elimination instead of inversion of configuration. Thus the planar transition state required for inversion of configuration is never reached, regardless of the rate of proton transfer to the anion.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent /><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>2011-11-12T21:00:24</date></data>