<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.548471</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Age determination of sediment cores from the continental shelf and slope off North-West Africa</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Factors contributing to Late Glacial and Holocene sedimentation on the continental shelf and slope off NW Africa, Banc d`Arguin, 19&#176; N</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Three sediment cores from the continental shelf and slope off NW Africa (Banc d'Arguin, 52 m, 665 m and 973 m water depth) have been investigated by means of a coarse fraction analysis.The two shallower cores have been deposited during less than 10,000 years, the deeper one during the last 36,000 years. The Holocene sedimentation ( 4000 years) in the deeper part of core 79 the edge of the Banc d'Arguin is strongly influenced by reworking of Late Glacial dune sands and biogenic particles from shallower ware (&lt;40 m), as well as eroding current influence. A decrease in grain size of silicate material and a decrease in lateral supply, correlated to a doubling of accumulation rates in the upper part of the core, indicates a more autochthonous sedimentation with less sorting influence in the youngest Holocene. The depth of provenance of the allochttonous material can be assumed in 100-300 m water depth as indicated by various biogenous particles. Small amounts of shallow water particles in the autochthonous layers indicate a supplay from shallow water, which probably occured b ythe mechanism of &#8222;particle by particle supply&#8220;. None of the three cores indicates upwelling influence, although occanographers found intense upwelling in the area of the Banc d'Arguin.The Holocene climate in that area probably has been arid, small variations in terrigenous matter composition and grain size in the Early Holocene might be due to decreased wind strength or to an increase in rain fall.The Peak Glacial section (14,000-22,000 y. B.P.) of the deepest core 88 indicates a very much intensified eolian silt supply and an additional bottom supply of quartz sand In the interval 22,000-36,000 y. B.P. wind strength decreased, but probably no increase in humidity occurred. So this area in about 19&#176; 40' N had an arid climate in the Late Holocene and in the Peak Glacial.The fragmentation of planktonic foraminifers and the abundance of aragonitic tests of pteropods in core 88 indicate an Early Holocene (8330 y. B.P.) preservation spike. Two minima in fragmentation correlated to maxima in pteropod content at about 15,700 and 21,000 y. B.P. are correlated to maxima in shallow water supply and thus do not reflect preservation conditions, but only lateral supply from the carbonate dissolution minimum zone in about 300 m water depth.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>GIK13579-1</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Depth, top/min | Depth top | Depth, bottom/max | Depth bot | Sample code/label | Sample label | Age, dated | Age dated | Age, 14C conventional | Age, dated standard deviation | Age dated std dev | carbonate fraction | Age, dated material | Dated material</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>1981-11-15T13:06:00</date></data>