<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.548492</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Age models and sea-surface paleotemperature reconstruction of sediment cores from the eastern equatorial Atlantic</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Sea-surface temperatures during the last 750,000 years in the eastern equatorial Atlantic: Planktonic foraminiferal record of Meteor - cores 13519, 13521, and 16415</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Based on the faunal record of planktonic foraminifers in three long gravity sediment cores from the eastern equatorial Atlantic, the sea-surface temperature history ove the last 750,000 years was studied at a resolution of 3,000 to 10,000 years. Detailed oxygen-isotope and paleomagnetic stratigraphy helped to identify the following major faunal events: Globorotaloides hexagonus and Globorotalia tumida flexuosa became extinct in the eastern tropical Atlantic at the isotope stage 4/5 boundary, now dated at 68,000 years B.P. The persistent occurrence of the pink variety of Globigerinoides ruber started during the late stage 12 at 410,000 years B.P. CARTUNE-age. This datum may provide an easily detectible faunal stratigraphic marker for the mid-Brunhes Chron. The updated scheme of the Ericson zones helped the recognition of a hiatus at the northwestern slope of the Sierra Leone Basin covering oxygen-isotope stages 10 to 12.Classifying the planktonic foraminifer counts into six faunal assemblages, according to the factor analysis derived model of Pflaumann (1985), the tropical and the tropical-upwelling communities account for 57 % at Site 16415, and 86 % at Site 13519, respectively of the variance of the faunal record.A largely continuous paleotemperature record for both winter and summer seasons was obtained from the top of the Sierra Leone Rise with the winter temperatures ranging between 20 and 25 &#176;C, and the summer ones between 24 and 30 &#176;C. The record of cores from greater water depths is frequently interrupted by samples with no-analogue faunal communities and/or poor preservation. Based on the seasonality signal, during cold periods the termal equator shifted to a geographically mnore asymmetrical northern position. Dissolution altering the faunal communities becomes stronger with greater water depth, the estimated mean minimum loss of specimens increases from 70 % to 80 % between 2,860 and 3,850 water depth although some species will be more susceptible than others. Enhanced dissolution occured during stage 4 but also during cold phases in the warm stage 7 and 9. Correlations between the Foraminiferal Dissolution Index and the estimated sea-surface temperatures are significant. Foraminiferal flux rates, negatively correlated to the flux rates of organic carbon and of diatoms, may be a result of enhanced dissolution during cold stages, destroying still more of the faunal signal than indicated by the calculated minimum loss.The fluctuations of the oxygen-isotope curves and the hibernal sea-surfave temperatures are fairly coherent. During warm oxygen-isotope stages the temperature maxima lag often by 5 to 15 ka behind the respective sotope minima. During cold stages, sea-surface temperature changes are partly out of phase and contain additional fluctuations.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>GIK/IfG</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>GIK13519-1</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Communality | Commun | Temperature, mean winter | T win | Temperature, mean summer | T sum | base of stage | Age, comment | Comm | CARPOR | Age model | CARTUNE | Age model, optional | Age model opt</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>1986-11-15T14:24:29</date></data>