<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.865101</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>The effect of a reduction of nitrogen and phosphorus to eutrophic and mesotrophic conditions towards silver nanoparticle (AgNP) on freshwater green algae species</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Nutrient deficiency increases sensitivity of algae towards silver nanoparticles</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>We investigated the sensitivity of algae towards silver nanoparticles with OECD test medium and lower nutrient concentrations under standard test conditions to improve comparability and to exclude any other confounding factor aside nutrient levels. Two unicellular freshwater microalgae Desmodesmus subspicatus and Raphidocelis subcapitata were chosen due to their status as standard test organisms for the algae growth inhibition test and the response to changes in nutrient supply was compared. The original medium was used as the reference (standard). For the other four media, the amount of either nitrogen or phosphorus in the medium was lowered from half (50%) to one-fourth (25 %) of that of the OECD guideline, resulting in the following media: 50% N, 25% N, 50% P and 25% P medium. As test substance, the OECD reference material NM-300K was used. For this reason, the characterization of AgNP was done using DLS and Absorption spectra (UV/vis). Actual silver concentrations and ionic silver concentrations were measured at the highest test concentration used (100 &#181;g Ag L-1) in R. subcapitata treatments only to reduce the number of samples. All tests were run according to the OECD guideline 201 with sterilized 50 mL cell culture flask. Each medium was tested using the test conditions for culturing with 3 replicates. Test concentrations for both algae species were 0, 25, 50 and 100 &#181;g Ag L-1 for OECD, 50% P and 25% P while for both N reductions, the silver concentrations were 0, 10, 25 and 100 &#181;g Ag L-1. Samples for determining the algal density were taken at every 24 h.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Wavelength | Lambda | OECD (day0), Sample 1 | Absorbance | OECD (day0), Sample 2 | OECD (day3), Sample 1 | OECD (day3), Sample 2 | 50% N (day0), Sample 1 | 50% N (day0), Sample 2 | 50% N (day3), Sample 1 | 50% N (day3), Sample 2 | 25% N (day0), Sample 1 | 25% N (day0), Sample 2 | 25% N (day3), Sample 1 | 25% N (day3), Sample 2 | 50% P (day0), Sample 1 | 50% P (day0), Sample 2 | 50% P (day3), Sample 1 | 50% P (day3), Sample 2 | 25% P (day0), Sample 1 | 25% P (day0), Sample 2 | 25% P (day3), Sample 1 | 25% P (day3), Sample 2 | Sample code/label | Sample label | Treatment: temperature | Treat temp | Scattering an&#609;le | theta | Hydrodynamic diameter | Hydrodynamic d | Dispersity | D- | Zeta potential | Z-potential | Conductivity | Cond | Medium | Ionic | Silver | Ag | total | Test substance | Test subs | Dose | OECD | Dose response | Dose resp | 50% N | 25% N | 50% P | 25% P | &#181;g Ag/L | OECD medium, day0 | Desmodesmus subspicatus, cells | D. subspicatus cells | OECD medium, day1 | OECD medium, day2 | OECD medium, day3 | 50% N medium, day0 | 50% N medium, day1 | 50% N medium, day2 | 50% N medium, day3 | 25% N medium, day0 | 25% N medium, day1 | 25% N medium, day2 | 25% N medium, day3 | 50% P medium, day0 | 50% P medium, day1 | 50% P medium, day2 | 50% P medium, day3 | 25% P medium, day0 | 25% P medium, day1 | 25% P medium, day2 | 25% P medium, day3 | Raphidocelis subcapitata, cells | R. subcapitata cells</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>2016-09-29T07:34:26</date></data>