<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.877346</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>OSL age determination and sedimentological characteristics of the Batagay thaw slump, Northeastern Siberia</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Palaeoclimate characteristics in interior Siberia of MIS&#160;6-2: first insights from the Batagay permafrost mega-thaw slump in the Yana Highlands</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Syngenetic permafrost deposits formed extensively on and around the arising Beringian subcontinent during the Late Pleistocene sea level lowstands. Syngenetic deposition implies that all material, both mineral and organic, freezes parallel to sedimentation and remains frozen until degradation of the permafrost. Permafrost is therefore a unique archive of Late Pleistocene palaeoclimate. Most studied permafrost outcrops are situated in the coastal lowlands of northeastern Siberia, inland sections&#160;are, however, scarcely available. Here, we describe the stratigraphical, cryolithological, and geochronological characteristics of a permafrost sequence near Batagay in the Siberian Yana Highlands, the interior of the Sakha Republic (Yakutia), Russia, with focus on the Late Pleistocene Yedoma ice complex (YIC). The recently formed Batagay mega-thaw slump exposes permafrost deposits to a depth of up to 80 m and gives insight into a climate record close to Verkhoyansk, which has the most severe continental climate in the Northern Hemisphere. Geochronological dating (optically stimulated luminescence, OSL, and 14C ages) and stratigraphic implications delivered a temporal frame from the Middle Pleistocene to the Holocene for our sedimentological interpretations and also revealed interruptions in the deposition. The sequence of lithological units indicates a succession of several distinct climate phases: a Middle Pleistocene ice complex indicates cold stage climate. Then, ice wedge growth stopped due to highly increased sedimentation rates and eventually a rise in temperature. Full interglacial climate conditions existed during accumulation of an organic-rich layer - plant macrofossils reflected open forest vegetation existing under dry conditions during Marine Isotope Stage (MIS)&#160;5e. The Late Pleistocene YIC (MIS&#160;4-MIS&#160;2) suggests severe cold-stage climate conditions. No alas deposits, potentially indicating thermokarst processes, were detected at the site. A detailed comparison of the permafrost deposits exposed in the Batagay thaw slump with well-studied permafrost sequences, both coastal and inland, is made to highlight common features and differences in their formation processes and palaeoclimatic histories. Fluvial and lacustrine influence is temporarily common in the majority of permafrost exposures, but has to be excluded for the Batagay sequence. We interpret the characteristics of permafrost deposits at this location as a result of various climatically induced processes that are partly seasonally controlled. Nival deposition might have been dominant during winter time, whereas proluvial and aeolian deposition could have prevailed during the snowmelt period and the dry summer season.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>TUNDRA-STEPPE</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Sample ID | size fraction &lt;90 &#181;m | Feldspar | Fsp | size fraction 90-160 &#181;m | size fraction &gt;160 &#181;m | size fraction &lt;63 &#181;m | size fraction 63-100 &#181;m | etched | Method comment | Method comm | Quartz | Qz | Uniform resource locator/link to raw data file | URL raw | Ice content | Ice | Nitrogen, total | TN | Element analyser CNS, Elementar Vario EL III | Carbon, total | TC | Carbon, organic, total | TOC | Element analyser CNS, elementar Vario MAX C | Carbon, organic, total/Nitrogen, total ratio | TOC/TN | Calculated | Calcium carbonate | CaCO3 | Grain size, mean | Grain size mean | Size fraction &lt; 0.002 mm, &gt; 9 phi, clay | &lt;2 &#181;m, &gt;9 phi | Size fraction 0.020-0.002 mm | 20-2 &#181;m | Size fraction 0.063-0.020 mm, coarse silt | 63-20 &#181;m gU | Size fraction 0.200-0.063 mm, fine sand | 200-63 &#181;m fS | Size fraction &gt; 0.200 mm | &gt;200 &#181;m | Susceptibility, specific, low-field mass-normalized | chi_lf | Bartington MS2B bulk sensor | Susceptibility, specific, high-field mass-normalized | chi_hf | with respect to VPDB | &#948;13C | Mass spectrometer Finnigan Delta-S | Unit | Depth, top/min | Depth top | Depth, bottom/max | Depth bot | Grain size: 0.375 &#181;m | Size fraction | Fraction | Beckman Coulter Laser diffraction particle size analyzer LS 200 | Grain size: 0.412 &#181;m | Grain size: 0.452 &#181;m | Grain size: 0.496 &#181;m | Grain size: 0.545 &#181;m | Grain size: 0.598 &#181;m | Grain size: 0.657 &#181;m | Grain size: 0.721 &#181;m | Grain size: 0.791 &#181;m | Grain size: 0.869 &#181;m | Grain size: 0.953 &#181;m | Grain size: 1.047 &#181;m | Grain size: 1.149 &#181;m | Grain size: 1.261 &#181;m | Grain size: 1.385 &#181;m | Grain size: 1.52 &#181;m | Grain size: 1.669 &#181;m | Grain size: 1.832 &#181;m | Grain size: 2.01 &#181;m | Grain size: 2.207 &#181;m | Grain size: 2.423 &#181;m | Grain size: 2.66 &#181;m | Grain size: 2.92 &#181;m | Grain size: 3.206 &#181;m | Grain size: 3.519 &#181;m | Grain size: 3.862 &#181;m | Grain size: 4.241 &#181;m | Grain size: 4.656 &#181;m | Grain size: 5.111 &#181;m | Grain size: 5.611 &#181;m | Grain size: 6.158 &#181;m | Grain size: 6.761 &#181;m | Grain size: 7.421 &#181;m | Grain size: 8.147 &#181;m | Grain size: 8.944 &#181;m | Grain size: 9.819 &#181;m | Grain size: 10.78 &#181;m | Grain size: 11.83 &#181;m | Grain size: 12.99 &#181;m | Grain size: 14.26 &#181;m | Grain size: 15.65 &#181;m | Grain size: 17.18 &#181;m | Grain size: 18.86 &#181;m | Grain size: 20.7 &#181;m | Grain size: 22.73 &#181;m | Grain size: 24.95 &#181;m | Grain size: 27.38 &#181;m | Grain size: 30.07 &#181;m | Grain size: 33 &#181;m | Grain size: 36.24 &#181;m | Grain size: 39.77 &#181;m | Grain size: 43.66 &#181;m | Grain size: 47.93 &#181;m | Grain size: 52.63 &#181;m | Grain size: 57.77 &#181;m | Grain size: 63.41 &#181;m | Grain size: 69.62 &#181;m | Grain size: 76.43 &#181;m | Grain size: 83.9 &#181;m | Grain size: 92.09 &#181;m | Grain size: 101.1 &#181;m | Grain size: 111 &#181;m | Grain size: 121.8 &#181;m | Grain size: 133.7 &#181;m | Grain size: 146.8 &#181;m | Grain size: 161.2 &#181;m | Grain size: 176.8 &#181;m | Grain size: 194.2 &#181;m | Grain size: 213.2 &#181;m | Grain size: 234.1 &#181;m | Grain size: 256.8 &#181;m | Grain size: 282.1 &#181;m | Grain size: 309.6 &#181;m | Grain size: 339.8 &#181;m | Grain size: 373.1 &#181;m | Grain size: 409.6 &#181;m | Grain size: 449.7 &#181;m | Grain size: 493.6 &#181;m | Grain size: 541.9 &#181;m | Grain size: 594.9 &#181;m | Grain size: 653 &#181;m | Grain size: 716.9 &#181;m | Grain size: 786.9 &#181;m | Grain size: 863.9 &#181;m | Grain size: 948.2 &#181;m | Grain size: 1041 &#181;m | Grain size: 1143 &#181;m | Grain size: 1255 &#181;m | Grain size: 1377 &#181;m | Grain size: 1512 &#181;m | Grain size: 1660 &#181;m | Grain size: 1822 &#181;m | Grain size: 2000 &#181;m</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>2017-06-30T08:53:26</date></data>