<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.832400</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Osmium-isotope geochemistry of ODP Site 159-959</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Osmium-isotope geochemistry of Site 959: implications for Re-Os sedimentary geochronology and reconstruction of past variations in the Os-isotopic composition of seawater</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Analyses of Re, Os, and Ir concentrations, as well as Os-isotopic compositions, are reported for a suite of sediments from Ocean Drilling Program Site 959. These samples vary in age from late Neogene to Late Cretaceous, and represent a range in depositional oxidation-reduction conditions from suboxic in the Neogene to anoxic in the Late Cretaceous. Age assignments based on shipboard biostratigraphic data are used to calculate initial 187Os/186Os ratios of Neogene nannofossil/foraminifer oozes and Eocene to upper Oligocene laminated diatomites. These calculated initial ratios are in general agreement with published data constraining the Os-isotopic evolution of seawater through time, indicating that the Os-isotopic composition of these sediments is controlled largely by the Os isotopic composition of contemporaneous seawater. Results from analyses of Upper Cretaceous to lower Paleocene claystones do not exhibit elevated Ir concentrations and exhibit Re-Os systematics that are highly consistent with closed-system production of 187Os by in situ 187Re decay. Scatter in both the Cretaceous and Cenozoic data sets is likely the result of the influence of nonhydrogenous Os, carried by clastics, on the bulk sediment Os-isotopic composition, or post-depositional mobility of Re and/or Os.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>ODP</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Sample code/label | Sample label | ODP sample designation | Rhenium | Re | Iridium | Ir | Osmium | Os | Osmium 187/Osmium 188 ratio | 187Os/188Os | Osmium 187/Osmium 186 ratio | 187Os/186Os | Rhenium 187/Osmium 186 ratio | 187Re/186Os | Age, error | Age e | Age, minimum/young | Age min | Age, maximum/old | Age max | initial (minimum) | initial (maximum)</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>1998-05-08T09:21:19</date></data>