<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.879514</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Occurrence and abundance of soil-specific bacterial membrane lipid markers in the T&#234;t watershed</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Occurrence and abundance of soil-specific bacterial membrane lipid markers in the T&#234;t watershed (southern France): Soil-specific BHPs and branched GDGTs</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Recently, four bacteriohopanepolyols (BHPs), adenosylhopane, and structurally similar adenosylhopane-type 1, 2-methyl adenosylhopane, and 2-methyl adenosylhopane-type 1, have been suggested to be characteristic of soil microbial communities and therefore can serve as molecular markers for soil organic matter (OM) supply in river, lake, and marine sediments. In this study, we analyzed BHPs in peats and soils collected in the T&#234;t watershed (southern France) and compared them with branched glycerol dialkyl glycerol tetraethers (GDGTs), a more established molecular tracer of soil OM. Adenosylhopane-type I is identified in all of the samples from the study area except one collected near the T&#234;t River mouth with up to three of the related compounds also frequently present, particularly in the surface samples. The concentrations of soil-specific BHPs in peat environments have been shown to increase with lower d15N values, providing evidence that N2-fixing bacteria are probably a major source of soil-specific BHPs in acidic environments. It seems likely that soil pH is a major factor controlling BHP occurrence based on statistical analysis of environmental parameters and BHP concentration data. The comparison of the soil-specific BHP concentrations with those of branched GDGTs shows no clear relationship in the T&#234;t River system, supporting the concept that these two groups of soil-specific compounds are synthesized by different microbial organisms living in different niches in the soil profile (e.g., oxic top versus anoxic deep).</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>NIOZ_UU</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Material | Depth, top/min | Depth top | Depth, bottom/max | Depth bot | from Kim et al. (2010) | Temperature, air, annual mean | MAAT | Precipitation, annual mean | MAP | Soil pH | Nitrogen, total | TN | &#948;15N | Branched glycerol dialkyl glycerol tetraether, per unit mass total organic carbon | brGDGT/TOC | Branched and isoprenoid tetraether index | BIT | total | Bacteriohopanepolyols per unit mass total organic carbon | BHP/TOC | soil-specific | Bacteriohopanepolyols | BHPs | Number of Bacteriohopanepolyol structures | N BHPs struc | m/z = 655 | Bacteriohopanepolyol Ia per unit mass total organic carbon | Ia/TOC | m/z = 669 | 2-methyl Bacteriohopanepolyol per unit mass total organic carbon | IIa/TOC | m/z = 712 | Unsaturated aminotriol per unit mass total organic carbon | IIIb or IVb/TOC | m/z = 714 | Aminotriol per unit mass total organic carbon | Id/TOC | m/z = 728 | 2-methyl aminotriol per unit mass total organic carbon | IIb/TOC | m/z = 746 | Adenosylhopane per unit mass total organic carbon | m/z = 760 | 2-methyl adenosylhopane per unit mass total organic carbon | IIc/TOC | m/z = 761 | Adenosylhopane-type 1 per unit mass total organic carbon | m/z = 772 | 2-methyl adenosylhopane-type 1 per unit mass total organic carbon | IId/TOC | m/z = 775 | Aminotetrol unit mass total organic carbon | Ie/TOC | m/z = 830 | Aminopentol per unit mass total organic carbon | Ik/TOC | m/z = 941 | Unsaturated BHT pentose per unit mass total organic carbon | IIIg or IVg/TOC | m/z = 943 | Bacteriohopanepolyol pentosel per unit mass total organic carbon | Ig/TOC | m/z = 957 | 2-methyl Bacteriohopanepolyol pentose per unit mass total organic carbon | IIg/TOC | m/z = 1002 (C) | Bacteriohopanepolyol cyclitol ether per unit mass total organic carbon | Ih/TOC | m/z = 1002 (G) | Bacteriohopanepolyol glucosamine per unit mass total organic carbon | Ii/TOC | m/z = 1060 | BHpentol glucosamine per unit mass total organic carbon | Ij/TOC | m/z = 1118 | BHhexol cyclitol ether per unit mass total organic carbon | m/z = 1132 | 2-methylBHhexol cyclitol ether per unit mass total organic carbon | IIk/TOC</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>2011-08-09T15:19:57</date></data>