<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.839450</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Organic matter and sediment properties of samples from site GeoB15105 from the Black Sea</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Extending the analytical window for water-soluble organic matter in sediments by aqueous Soxhlet extraction</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Dissolved organic matter (DOM) in marine sediments is a complex mixture of thousands of individual constituents that participate in biogeochemical reactions and serve as substrates for benthic microbes. Knowledge of the molecular composition of DOM is a prerequisite for a comprehensive understanding of the biogeochemical processes in sediments. In this study, interstitial water DOM was extracted with Rhizon samplers from a sediment core from the Black Sea and compared to the corresponding water-extractable organic matter fraction (&lt;0.4 &#181;m) obtained by Soxhlet extraction, which mobilizes labile particulate organic matter and DOM. After solid phase extraction (SPE) of DOM, samples were analyzed for the molecular composition by Fourier Transform Ion-Cyclotron Resonance Mass Spectrometry (FT-ICR MS) with electrospray ionization in negative ion mode. The average SPE extraction yield of the dissolved organic carbon (DOC) in interstitial water was 63%, whereas less than 30% of the DOC in Soxhlet-extracted organic matter was recovered. Nevertheless, Soxhlet extraction yielded up to 4.35% of the total sedimentary organic carbon, which is more than 30-times the organic carbon content of the interstitial water. While interstitial water DOM consisted primarily of carbon-, hydrogen- and oxygen-bearing compounds, Soxhlet extracts yielded more complex FT-ICR mass spectra with more peaks and higher abundances of nitrogen- and sulfur-bearing compounds. The molecular composition of both sample types was affected by the geochemical conditions in the sediment, elevated concentrations of HS- promoted the early diagenetic sulfurization of organic matter. The Soxhlet extracts from shallow sediment contained specific three- and four-nitrogen-bearing molecular formulas that were also detected in bacterial cell extracts and presumably represent proteinaceous molecules. These compounds decreased with increasing sediment depth while one- and two-nitrogen-bearing molecules increased, resulting in a higher similarity of both sample types in the deep sediment. In summary, Soxhlet extraction of sediments accessed a larger and more complex pool of organic matter than present in interstitial water DOM.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>MARUM</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Depth, top/min | Depth top | Depth, bottom/max | Depth bot | Carbon, organic, total | TOC | Thermo Scientific Flash 2000-Delta V Plus IRMS | &#948;13C, organic carbon | &#948;13C Corg | Nitrogen, total | TN | with respect to VPDB | &#948;15N | Carbon, organic, total/Nitrogen, total ratio | TOC/TN | interstitial water | Carbon, organic, dissolved | DOC | Nitrogen, total dissolved | TDN | water extractable</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>2014-11-25T08:52:06</date></data>