<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.746240</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Occurence of flood laminae in sediments of Ammersee</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>A 450 year record of spring-summer flood layers in annually laminated sediments from Lake Ammersee (southern Germany)</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>A 450 year spring-summer flood layer time series at seasonal resolution has been established from the varved sediment record of Lake Ammersee (southern Germany), applying a novel methodological approach. The main results are (1) the attainment of a precise chronology by microscopic varve counting, (2) the identification of detrital layers representing flood-triggered fluxes of catchment material into the lake, and (3) the recognition of the seasonality of these flood layers from their microstratigraphic position within a varve. Tracing flood layers in a proximal and a distal core and correlating them by application of the precise chronology provided information on the depositional processes. Comparing the seasonal flood layer record with daily runoff data of the inflowing River Ammer for the period from 1926 to 1999 allowed the definition of an approximate threshold in flood magnitude above which the formation of flood layers becomes very likely. Moreover, it was possible for the first time to estimate the "completeness" of the flood layer time series and to recognize that mainly floods in spring and summer, representing the main flood seasons in this region, are well preserved in the sediment archive. Their frequency distribution over the entire 450 year time series is not stationary but reveals maxima for colder periods of the Little Ice Age when solar activity was reduced. The observed spring-summer flood layer frequency further shows trends similar to those of the occurrence of flood-prone weather regimes since A.D. 1881, probably suggesting a causal link between solar variability and changes in midlatitude atmospheric circulation patterns.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>AS_07-P1</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment>Modified UWITEC short-core system</md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent /><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>2010-10-14T14:48:04</date></data>