<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.713731</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Geochemistry and radiogenic isotope ratios of the volcanic sequences from Izu-Bonin Arc, Japan</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Isotopic characteristics of subduction fluids in an intra-oceanic setting, Izu&#8211;Bonin Arc, Japan</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>New radiogenic isotope and trace element data are presented for the volcanic sequences along 600 km of the active Izu-Bonin arc, the Oligocene Izu arc, and their associated rift basins. As with many intra-oceanic island arcs, the Pliocene-Recent Izu-Bonin frontal-arc lavas are highly depleted in Zr, Nb and the rare-earth elements relative to typical mid-ocean ridge basalt (MORB), indicating that the mantle wedge source has undergone a previous episode of melting. Ratios between these elements (such as Nb/Zr and La/Sm), as well as 143Nd/144Nd, do not vary significantly along the length of the frontal-arc. These parameters suggest that each of the arc volcanoes is derived from similar melt fractions of the mantle wedge. However, Ba/Zr, Ba/Rb and 87Sr/86Sr increase along the frontal-arc to the north. This leads us to propose that a variable enrichment in Ba and radiogenic Sr is superimposed on the mantle wedge. Sr-Nd and Pb-Nd isotope variation indicate that both Sr and Pb become more radiogenic after fluid addition. However, Pb isotope ratios do not correlate with increases in Pb concentration or ratios such as Ba/Zr and Nb/Pb. In other words, the Pb isotopic composition of the arc lavas appears to be independent of the amount of Pb introduced by subduction fluids into the mantle source. This buffering of Pb isotopes along the frontal-arc means that the isotopic composition of the lavas is indistinguishable from that of the fluid. Isotopic mixing models presented for the arc are only illustrative of the many plausible combinations of components and quantities. Despite this, we are able to determine that the mantle wedge has isotopic characteristics similar to Indian Ocean MORB, and that the subduction-fluid solute is primarily derived from subducted oceanic basalt with a &lt;2% contribution from subducted sediment. Lavas in the Oligocene Izu arc and fore-arc basin were derived from a mantle wedge of similar composition to the active arc. Despite levels of Pb enrichment comparable to those of the modern arc, the Pb isotopes of the Oligocene volcanics indicate a lower sediment input into the melting region.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>ODP</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>126-790A</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment>4 cores, 37.4 m cored, 0 m drilled, 95.5 % recovery</md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Area/locality | Area | Sample code/label | Sample label | Silicon dioxide | SiO2 | X-ray fluorescence (XRF) | Titanium dioxide | TiO2 | Aluminium oxide | Al2O3 | Iron oxide, Fe2O3 | Fe2O3 | Manganese oxide | MnO | Magnesium oxide | MgO | Calcium oxide | CaO | Sodium oxide | Na2O | Potassium oxide | K2O | Phosphorus oxide | P2O5 | Loss on ignition | LOI | Gallium | Ga | Strontium | Sr | Zirconium | Zr | Vanadium | V | Chromium | Cr | Nickel | Ni | Copper | Cu | Zinc | Zn | Beryllium | Be | ICP, Inductively coupled plasma | Cobalt | Co | Scandium | Sc | Rubidium | Rb | Yttrium | Y | Niobium | Nb | Caesium | Cs | Barium | Ba | Lanthanum | La | Cerium | Ce | Praseodymium | Pr | Neodymium | Nd | Samarium | Sm | Europium | Eu | Gadolinium | Gd | Terbium | Tb | Dysprosium | Dy | Holmium | Ho | Erbium | Er | Ytterbium | Yb | Lutetium | Lu | Hafnium | Hf | Tantalum | Ta | Lead | Pb | Thorium | Th | Uranium | U | Strontium 87/Strontium 86 | 87Sr/86Sr | Thermal Ionization Mass Spectrometry (TIMS) | Strontium 87/Strontium 86, error | 87Sr/86Sr e | Neodymium 143/Neodymium 144 | 143Nd/144Nd | Neodymium 143/Neodymium 144, error | 143Nd/144Nd e | Lead 206/Lead 204 ratio | 206Pb/204Pb | Lead 207/Lead 204 ratio | 207Pb/204Pb | Lead 208/Lead 204 ratio | 208Pb/204Pb | Sample comment | ODP sample designation | Sample code/label 2 | Sample label 2 | calculated assuming t = 33 Ma for both 792E and 793B data | Calculated | Rubidium/Strontium ratio | Rb/Sr</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>1998-03-02T17:13:22</date></data>