<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.744815</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Oligocene and Neogene radiolarians from the Labrador Sea</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Oligocene and Neogene radiolarians from the Labrador Sea: ODP Leg 105</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Two sites in the Labrador Sea and one site in Baffin Bay were drilled during Leg 105. Radiolarians were recovered at all three sites, although at Site 645 (Baffin Bay), radiolarians were present in useful numbers only in the mudline sample. Radiolarians of late Neogene age were recovered at Site 646 south of Greenland, while early Oligocene and early Miocene radiolarians were recovered from the Labrador Sea at Site 647. In Site 646, radiolarian and other coarse-fraction abundances vary dramatically from sample to sample and may reflect deep-water depositional processes as well as changes in surface-water conditions. Site 647 siliceous microfossils reach their peak abundance and preservation in Core 105-647A-25R and decline gradually upward into the lower Miocene (Cores 105-647A-13R and -14R). Siliceous microfossil abundances in counts of the &gt; 38-&#181;m Carbonate-free coarse fraction from the siliceous interval are correlated to each other, but not to the abundance of nonbiogenic coarse-fraction components. Radiolarian abundances in specimens per gram (but not diatom abundances) are correlated to bulk opal concentration and to the organic carbon content of the sediment. The abundance of radiolarians and other siliceous microfossils within the lower Oligocene to lower Miocene is interpreted as reflecting changes in surface-water productivity. With only a few exceptions, no stratigraphic indicator species were seen in samples from either Site 646 or Site 647. The absence of both tropical/subtropical and Norwegian-Greenland Sea stratigraphic forms is due to the dominance of subarctic North Atlantic taxa in Leg 105 assemblages. The early Oligocene and early Miocene assemblages recovered at Site 647 are of particular interest, as very little material of these ages has previously been recovered from the subarctic North Atlantic region, and virtually no descriptive work has been conducted on the more endemic components of the radiolarian assemblages from these time intervals. Thus, this report concentrates on providing, at least in part, the first comprehensive documentation of early Oligocene and early Miocene radiolarians from the subarctic North Atlantic, with emphasis on basic descriptions, measurements, and photographic documentation. However, synonymic work and formal designation of new species names has been deferred until additional material from other regions can be examined. The sole exception is the emendation of Theocalyptra tetracantha Bjorklund and Kellogg 1972 to Cycladophora tetracantha n. comb.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>ODP</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>105-646A</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment>11 core, 103.5 m cored, 0 m drilled, 89 % recovery</md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Sample code/label | Sample label | ODP sample designation | Number | No | Number of radiolarians scanned | Radiolarians | Rad | Counting &gt;38 &#181;m fraction | Diatoms, pennales | Diatom pen | Diatoms, centrales | Diatom cen | Silicoflagellate valves per unit sediment mass | Silicoflag valves/sed | Sponge spiculae | Sponge spic | Lithic grains | Lithic | sp. B | Trissocyclid sp. | sp. C | sp. D | Dorcadospyris sp. | Corythospyris sp. | sp. A | sp. 3 | Nassellaria sp. | genus questionable, sp. A | Lithomelissa sp. | sp. 1 | Velicucullus sp. | Cycladophora sp. | Ceratocyrtis mashae | C. mashae | Peridium spp. | Dictyophimus sp. | Pterocanium sp. | questionable | Cyclampterium pegetrum | C. pegetrum | Stichocorys sp. | Eucyrtidium sp. | Lamprocyclas sp. | Calocycletta sp. | Cyrtopera laguncula | C. laguncula | Cannobotryidae | Botryostrobus joides | B. joides | sp. 5 | sp. B group A | Cyrtocapsella sp. | sp. B group B | ? Calocyclas semipolita | Calocyclas semipolita | C. semipolita | Peripyramis spp. | Cornutella spp. | ? Dicolocapsa microcephala | Dicolocapsa microcephala | D. microcephala | ? Cystophormis brevispina | Cystophormis brevispina | C. brevispina | sp. 7 | sp. 8 | Siphocampe sp. | ? Dictyoprora amphora | Dictyoprora amphora | D. amphora | Siphocampe acephala | S. acephala | Druppatractus hastatus | D. hastatus | Sphaerostylus cristatus | S. cristatus | sp. E | Stylatractid sp. | ? Lithatractus timmsi | Lithatractus timmsi | L. timmsi | sp. G | Sphaerostylus rosetta | S. rosetta | genus questionable | Cenosphaera oceanica | C. oceanica | Cenosphaera sp. | Cenosphaera mariae | C. mariae | Collosphaera sp. | spp. B | Actinomma spp. | Actinomma sp. | Anomalacantha dentata | A. dentata | Arachnosphaera sp. | Sphaeropyle sp. | Heliodiscus sp. | sp. #1 | Spumellaria sp. | sp. #2 | Spongocore sp. | Amphitholus sp. | Tetrapyle spp. | Lithelius sp. | Prunopyle sp. | genus questionable, spp. C | Prunopyle spp. | Spongodiscus spp. | Porodiscus spp. | Silicoflagellate abundance | Silicoflag abund | Radiolarians abundance | Rad abund | E = excellent, G = good, P = poor, F = fair | Radiolarian preservation | Rad preserv</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>1989-08-30T13:54:22</date></data>