<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.805717</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Shell size, body mass and average pO2 in mantle cavity water of different marine mollusc species</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Mantle cavity water oxygen partial pressure (Po-2) in marine molluscs aligns with lifestyle</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Marine invertebrates with open circulatory system establish low and constant oxygen partial pressure (Po2) around their tissues. We hypothesized that as a first step towards maintenance of low haemolymph and tissue oxygenation, the Po2 in molluscan mantle cavity water should be lowered against normoxic (21 kPa) seawater Po2, but balanced high enough to meet the energetic requirements in a given species. We recorded Po2 in mantle cavity water of five molluscan species with different lifestyles, two pectinids (Aequipecten opercularis, Pecten maximus), two mud clams (Arctica islandica, Mya arenaria), and a limpet (Patella vulgata). All species maintain mantle cavity water oxygenation below normoxic Po2. Average mantle cavity water Po2 correlates positively with standard metabolic rate (SMR): highest in scallops and lowest in mud clams. Scallops show typical Po2 frequency distribution, with peaks between 3 and 10 kPa, whereas mud clams and limpets maintain mantle water Po2 mostly &lt;5 kPa. Only A. islandica and P. vulgata display distinguishable temporal patterns in Po2 time series. Adjustment of mantle cavity Po2 to lower than ambient levels through controlled pumping prevents high oxygen gradients between bivalve tissues and surrounding fluid, limiting oxygen flux across the body surface. The patterns of Po2 in mantle cavity water correspond to molluscan ecotypes.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>IPY</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Species | Sample amount | N | Shell length | Shell l | shell length | Standard deviation | Std dev | mean | Biomass, wet mass, shell-free | Biom SFWM | min | max | Sample code/label | Sample label | Mollusca, mantle cavity water, oxygen partial pressure | Mollusca pO2 (mcw) | Experiment</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>2010-01-22T10:19:15</date></data>