<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.811748</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Total organic carbon content and maceral composition of sediment at DSDP Holes 72-515B and 72-516F</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Facies and diagenesis of organic matter in sediments from the Brazil Basin and the Rio Grande Rise, Deep Sea Drilling Project Leg 72</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>The amount, type, and thermal maturation of organic matter in sediments from two DSDP holes in the South Atlantic (Leg 72) were investigated. Isolated kerogens were studied by microscopy, and nonaromatic hydrocarbons were characterized by capillary gas chromatography. Organic carbon values are low in all samples and range between 0.05 and 0.21% in Hole 515B (Brazil Basin) and only between 0.02 and 0.10% in Hole 516F (Rio Grande Rise). The organic matter is predominantly terrigenous, mixed with some unicellular marine algae, it is severely oxidized in most samples. N-alkane distributions are usually dominated by long-chain wax alkanes with odd-over-even carbon number predominance, when the marine organic matter is relatively more abundant, however, significant amounts of n-alkanes are centered upon n-C17. The organic matter is not mature enough in any sample to generate appreciable amounts of hydrocarbons.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>DSDP</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>72-515B</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment>57 cores, 541.4 m cored, 94.9 m drilled, 79.2 % recovery</md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Sample code/label | Sample label | ODP sample designation | Epoch | Carbon, organic, total | TOC | Carbon analyser, LECO | Includes vitrinite | Huminite | Liquid chromatography | Inertinite | Particulate | Liptinite | Zooclasts and phytoclasts | Clasts | Alginite | I | Bituminite | Fluorescent microscope | II</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>1983-05-16T22:34:22</date></data>