<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.846641</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Radiogenic isotope trace composition of the Labrador Sea</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Weathering versus circulation-controlled changes in radiogenic isotope tracer composition of the Labrador Sea and North Atlantic Deep Water</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Geological reconstructions and general circulation models suggest that the onset of both Northern Hemisphere glaciation, 2.7 Myr ago, and convection of Labrador Sea Water (LSW) were caused by the closure of the Panama Gateway ~4.5 Myr ago. Time series data that have been obtained from studies of ferromanganese crusts from the northwestern Atlantic suggest that radiogenic isotopes of intermediate ocean residence time (Pb and Nd) can serve as suitable tracers to reconstruct these events. However, it has been unclear until now as to whether the changes that have been observed in isotope composition at this time are the result of increased thermohaline circulation or due to the effects of increased glacial weathering. In this paper we adopt a box model approach to demonstrate that the shifts in radiogenic isotope compositions are unlikely to be due to changes in convection in LSW but can be explained in terms of increases of erosion levels due to the glaciation of Greenland and Canada. Furthermore, we provide experimental evidence for the incongruent release of a labile fraction of strongly radiogenic Pb and nonradiogenic Nd from continental detritus eroding into the Labrador Sea. This can be attributed to the glacial weathering of old continents and accounts for the paradox that one of the areas of the world most deficient in radiogenic Pb should provide such a rich supply of radiogenic Pb to the oceans. An important general conclusion is that the compositions of radiogenic isotopes in seawater are not always a reflection of their continental sources. Perhaps more importantly, the transition from chemical weathering to mechanical erosion is likely to result in significant variations in radiogenic tracers in seawater.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>ODP</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Sample code/label | Sample label | Sample comment | Area/locality | Area | Lead 208/Lead 204 ratio | 208Pb/204Pb | Lead 208/Lead 204, error | 208Pb/204Pb e | Lead 207/Lead 204 ratio | 207Pb/204Pb | Lead 207/Lead 204, error | 207Pb/204Pb e | Lead 206/Lead 204 ratio | 206Pb/204Pb | Lead 206/Lead 204, error | 206Pb/204Pb e | Lead 208/Lead 206 ratio | 208Pb/206Pb | Lead 208/Lead 206, error | 208Pb/206Pb e | Lead 207/Lead 206 ratio | 207Pb/206Pb | Lead 207/Lead 206, standard error | 207Pb/206Pb std e | Lead | Pb | Neodymium | Nd | Samarium | Sm | Samarium 147/Neodymium 144 ratio | 147Sm/144Nd | Neodymium 143/Neodymium 144 | 143Nd/144Nd | Neodymium 143/Neodymium 144, error | 143Nd/144Nd e | Method comment | Method comm | &#949;-Neodymium (0) | &#949;-Nd(0)</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>2001-06-02T09:04:11</date></data>