<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.746573</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Pelagic, turbiditic, and contouritic sequential deposits on the Cape Verde Plateau</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Pelagic, turbiditic, and contouritic sequential deposits on the Cape Verde Plateau (Leg 108, Site 659, Northwest Africa): sediment record during Neogene time</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>On the Cape Verde Plateau, Neogene deposits are composed of major pelagic and hemipelagic sediments. These sediments show climatic sequences composed of two lithologic terms that differ in their siliciclastic and carbonate contents. Several turbiditic and contouritic sequences are interbedded in these deposits.Turbidite sequences are fine grained and thin bedded with a very low frequency (about 12 sequences during the Neogene). They are composed of quartz-rich siliciclastic or volcaniclastic sediments. Quartz-rich turbidites originated from the Senegalese margin. Their slightly higher frequency during the early Pliocene indicates that the stronger turbidity currents, and probably the most abundant continental inputs, occur at that period. Volcaniclastic turbidites are only present in the early Miocene (about 17 Ma) and the early Pleistocene (1 Ma). They have flown from adjacent Cape Verde Islands and reflect two episodes of high volcanic activity in this area.Contourite sequences, composed of biogenic sandy silts, represent less than 5% of the sediment pile and seem to have been mainly deposited during the late Pleistocene.These different sequences show clay mineral variations throughout Neogene time. Kaolinite is predominant in the Miocene and lower Pliocene deposits, this mineral decreases thereafter, with an increased trend of illite in the uppermost Pliocene and Pleistocene sediments, suggesting a change in sediment sources on the Saharan continent at about 2.6 Ma.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>ODP</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>108-659</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment>59 cores, 551.9 m cored, 0 m drilled, 74.5% recovery</md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>sequenz number | Sample code/label 2 | Sample label 2 | Sample code/label | Sample label | ODP sample designation | Lithology/composition/facies | Lithology | Description | Calcium carbonate | CaCO3 | Size fraction &gt; 0.150 mm | &gt;150 &#181;m | Size fraction &lt; 0.063 mm, mud, pelite, silt+clay | &lt;63 &#181;m | Size fraction &lt; 0.002 mm, &gt; 9 phi, clay | &lt;2 &#181;m, &gt;9 phi | Median, grain size | D50 | Sorting | Sort | Feldspar/Quartz ratio | Fsp/Qz | sandy components | Quartz | Qz | Feldspar | Fsp | Volcanic components | Volcanic | Gypsum | Gp | Pyrite, FeS2 | Py | sandy components, foram total | Foraminifera | Foram | Foraminifera, planktic | Foram plankt | Foraminifera, benthic | Foram bent | Echinoidea | component assemblage | Comment | Type | in bulk sediment | Smectite | Sme | Illite | Ill | Kaolinite | Kln | Chlorite | Chl | Attapulgite | Palygorskite | Plg | Mineral assemblage | Min assembl | Epoch | component bulk sediment</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>1989-10-20T14:17:23</date></data>