<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.56156</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Dinoflagellates of sediment core GeoB1523-1</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>On the response of calcareous dinoflagellates to oligotrophy and stratification of the water column in the equatorial Atlantic Ocean</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Large numbers of calcareous dinoflagellate cysts and the vegetative calcareous coccoid species Thoracosphaera heimii are generally found in sediments underlying oligotrophic and/or stratified (sub)surface water environments. It is difficult to distinguish between the relative importance of these two environmental parameters on calcareous cyst and T. heimii distribution as they usually covary, but this information is essential if we want to apply cysts properly in the reconstruction of palaeoenvironments and past surface water hydrography. In the multi-proxy core GeoB 1523-1 from the Cear&#225; Rise region in the western equatorial Atlantic Ocean (covering the past 155 ka), periods of greatest oligotrophy are not synchronous with periods of greatest stratification (R&#252;hlemann et al., 1996, doi:10.1016/S0025-3227(96)00048-5, Mulitza et al., 1997, doi:10.1130/0091-7613(1997)025&lt;0335:PFAROP&gt;2.3.CO,2, 335-338, Mulitza et al., 1998, doi:10.1016/S0012-821X(98)00012-0), giving us the unique opportunity to differentiate between the effects of both parameters on cyst accumulation. The calcareous cyst record of the core reflects prominent increases in accumulation rate of nearly all observed species only during the nutrient-enriched but more stratified isotopic (sub)stages 5.5, 5.3, 5.1 and 1. In this respect, the distribution trends in the core are more similar to those of the eastern equatorial upwelling region (GeoB 1105-4) than they are to those of the oligotrophic north-eastern Brazilian continental slope (GeoB 2204-2), even though temporal changes in bioproductivity are principally in antiphase between the eastern and western equatorial regions. We conclude that stratification of the upper water column and the presence of a well-developed thermocline are probably the more important factors controlling cyst distribution in the equatorial Atlantic, whereas the state of oligotrophy secondarily influences cyst production within a well-stratified environment.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>GeoB</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>GeoB1523-1</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent /><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title>Reconstruction of recent and late Quaternary surface water masses of the western subtropical Atlantic Ocean based on calcareous and organic-walled dinoflagellate cysts</md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title><date>2000-02-04T13:57:00</date></data>