<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.705347</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Chemical and mineral compositions of altered peridotites from ODP Leg 209</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Geochemistry of abyssal peridotites (Mid-Atlantic Ridge, 15&#176;20'N, ODP Leg 209): implications for fluid-rock interaction in slow spreading environments</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Abyssal peridotite from the 15&#176;20'N area of the Mid-Atlantic Ridge show complex geochemical variations among the different sites drilled during ODP Leg 209. Major element compositions indicate variable degrees of melt depletion and refertilization as well as local hydrothermal metasomatism. Strongest evidence for melt-rock interactions are correlated Light Rare Earth Element (LREE) and High Field Strength Element (HFSE) additions at Sites 1270 and 1271. In contrast, hydrothermal alteration at Sites 1274, 1272, and 1268 causes LREE mobility associated with minor HFSE variability, reflecting the low solubility of HFSE in aqueous solutions. Site 1274 contains the least-altered, highly refractory, peridotite with strong depletion in LREE and shows a gradual increase in the intensity of isochemical serpentinization, except for the addition of H2O which causes a mass gain of up to 20 g/100 g. The formation of magnetite is reflected in decreasing Fe(2+)/Fe(3+) ratios. This style of alteration is referred to as rock-dominated serpentinization. In contrast, fluid-dominated serpentinization at Site 1268 is characterized by gains in sulfur and development of U-shaped REE pattern with strong positive Eu anomalies which are also characteristic for hot (350 to 400&#176;C) vent-type fluids discharging from black smoker fields. Serpentinites at Site 1268 were overprinted by talc alteration under static conditions due to interaction with high a_SiO2 fluids causing the development of smooth, LREE enriched patterns with pronounced negative Eu anomalies. These results show that hydrothermal fluid-peridotite and fluid-serpentinite interaction processes are an important factor regarding the budget of exchange processes between the lithosphere and the hydrosphere in slow spreading environments.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>ODP</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>209-1268A</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment>29 cores, 147.6 m cored, 0 m drilled, 53.3 % recovery</md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Sample code/label | Sample label | ODP sample designation | Rock type | Rock | labor | Sample code/label 2 | Sample label 2 | XRF | Laboratory | Lab | Silicon dioxide | SiO2 | X-ray fluorescence (XRF) | Titanium dioxide | TiO2 | Aluminium oxide | Al2O3 | total | Iron oxide, Fe2O3 | Fe2O3 | Magnesium oxide | MgO | Manganese oxide | MnO | Calcium oxide | CaO | Sodium oxide | Na2O | Potassium oxide | K2O | Phosphorus oxide | P2O5 | Loss on ignition | LOI | Sum | Calculated | Iron oxide, FeO | FeO | Titration | recalculated from XRF and titration data | Iron 2+/Iron total ratio | Fe2+/Fe total | Carbon dioxide | CO2 | Element analyser CHNS | Sulfur, total | S | Nitrogen, total | TN | Chromium | Cr | Nickel | Ni | ICP-MS | ICP-MS, Inductively coupled plasma - mass spectrometry | Lithium | Li | Barium | Ba | Caesium | Cs | Cobalt | Co | Arsenic | As | Vanadium | V | Copper | Cu | Lead | Pb | Zinc | Zn | Scandium | Sc | Rubidium | Rb | Strontium | Sr | Yttrium | Y | Zirconium | Zr | Niobium | Nb | Hafnium | Hf | Tantalum | Ta | Piece | modal | Olivine | Ol | Orthopyroxene | Opx | Clinopyroxene | Cpx | Spinel | Spl | Magnetite | Fe3O4 | serpentinized after olivine, modal | Minerals | after olivine, modal | Brucite | Brc | serpentinized after orthopyroxene, modal | serpentinized after uncertain precursor, modal | serpentinized in vein, modal | in vein, modal | of modal data | total primary, modal | primary, modal | number of microprobe analyses of primary phases | reconstructed | Chromium(III) oxide | Cr2O3 | total, reconstructed | of reconstructed contents | in the altered rock | total, in the altered rock | for SiO2 | Enrichment factor | EF | for FeO total | for Al2O3 | average for SiO2, MgO, and FeO total | Mass change | MCh</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>2006-10-10T13:02:44</date></data>