<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.873275</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Total V9 rDNA information organized at the OTU level for the Tara Oceans Expedition (2009-2012)</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title /><md:MetaData/md:abstract>The present data set provides a tab separated text file compressed in a zip archive. The file includes metadata for each TaraOceans V9 rDNA OTU including the following fields: md5sum = identifier of the representative (most abundant) sequence of the swarm, cid = identifier of the OTU, totab = total abundance of barcodes in this OTU, TARA_xxx = number of occurrences of barcodes in this OTU in each of the 334 samples,rtotab = total abundance of the representative barcode, pid = percentage identity of the representative barcode to the closest reference sequence from V9_PR2, lineage = taxonomic path assigned to the representative barcode , refs = best hit reference sequence(s) with respect to the representative barcode , taxogroup = high-taxonomic level assignation of the representative barcode. The file also includes three categories of functional annotations: (1) Chloroplast: yes, presence of permanent chloroplast, no, absence of permanent chloroplast , NA, undetermined. (2) Symbiont (small partner): parasite, the species is a parasite, commensal, the species is a commensal, mutualist, the species is a mutualist symbiont, most often a microalgal taxon involved in photosymbiosis, no the species is not involved in a symbiosis as small partner, NA, undetermined. (3) Symbiont (host): photo, the host species relies on a mutualistic microalgal photosymbiont to survive (obligatory photosymbiosis), photo_falc, same as photo, but facultative relationship, photo_klep, the host species maintains chloroplasts from microalgal prey(s) to survive, photo_klep_falc, same as photo_klep, but facultative, Nfix, the host species must interact with a mutualistic symbiont providing N2 fixation to survive, Nfix_falc, same as Nfix, but facultative, no, the species is not involved in any mutualistic symbioses, NA, undetermined.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>FondTara</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent /><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>2017-03-07T15:43:22</date></data>