<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.757922</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Foraminiferal oxygen and carbon isotopic measurements from 5 sites of southern Atlantic and Pacific</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Late Miocene-Early Pliocene stratigraphy and paleoceanography of the South Atlantic and southwest Pacific oceans: A synthesis</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>The stratigraphy and paleoceanography of the late Miocene and early Pliocene have been examined at six sites in the South Atlantic and southwest Pacific oceans: Deep Sea Drilling Project (DSDP) sites 284, 516A, 519, 588, and 590 and two piston cores from Chain cruise 115. A consistent stratigraphy was developed among sites using graphic correlation, which resulted in age models for all sites that are tied to the revised paleomagnetic time scale of Berggren et al. (1985). Applying these chronologies, we assessed latitudinal and interocean contrasts in the stratigraphic ranges of late Miocene-early Pliocene planktonic foraminiferal and nanno - fossil datums. Salient stratigraphic results include (1) The last appearance datum (LAD) of Globoquadrina dehiscens is a late Miocene (approx. 6.4 Ma) event in the subtropics and is not useful for the placement of the Miocene/Pliocene (M/P) boundary in this biogeographic province. (2) The first appearance datum (FAD) of Globorotalia crassaformis occurred at 5.1 Ma in the South Atlantic near the M/P boundary, suggesting that Gr. crassaformis may have first evolved in the South Atlantic and later migrated to other regions. (3) In the southwest Pacific, the FADs of Gr. margaritae (5.97 Ma), Gr. puncticulata (5.09 Ma), and Gr. crassaformis (4.87 Ma) are significantly time transgressive between temperate and warm subtropical regions. Time lags of 1.0 m.y. were required for these species to adapt to physical and/or biotic conditions peripheral to their endemic biogeographic provinces. (4) Between the subtropics of the South Atlantic and southwest Pacific, many planktonic foraminiferal datums (FAD of Dentogloboquadrina altispira, Gr. cibaoensis, Gr. conomiozea, Gr. margaritae, and Gq. dehiscens and LAD of Gr. cibaoensis) markedly depart from the correlation suggested by magnetostratigraphy, indicating that these datum levels are unreliable for correlation between these ocean basins. (5) In contrast, available calcareous nannofossil datum levels fall on or near the paleomagnetic correlation line, indicating synchroneity of events within the subtropics. (6) Biostratigraphic, magnetic, and 87Sr/86Sr correlation between sites 588 and 519 and the M/P neostratotype at Capo Rossello, Sicily, suggests that the base of the Zanclean stratotype occurs at 5.1-5.0 Ma in the lower reversed subchron of the Gilbert, about 2-3 * 10**5 years above the Gilbert/Chron 5 boundary. Oxygen isotopic results from DSDP sites 284, 519, and CH115 piston cores confirm a prolonged benthic d18O increase in the latest Miocene between 5.6 and 5.0 Ma, as originally proposed by Shackleton and Kennett (1975). At DSDP site 588, the benthic d18O record in the latest Miocene is marked by high-frequency fluctuations with amplitude variations of 0.5per mill, and a long-period wavelength component of 400,000 years. Maximum d18O values, however, occurred during the late Miocene (Kapitean Stage) between 5.5 and 5.1 Ma. The late Miocene d18O changes resulted from mid- and high-latitude cooling and pulses of ice sheet expansion and contraction. Glacial events were most intense during the latest Miocene (Kapitean Stage), and occurred at 5.50-5.35 Ma and at 5.10 Ma. Glacial events are estimated to have lowered sea level by 40 to 60 m and contributed to the isolation and desiccation of the Mediterranean Basin during the late Messinian. Interglacial conditions prevailed at 5.2 Ma and between 5.0 and 4.1 Ma in the early Pliocene. The beginning of the Pliocene was marked by changes in many proxy climatic indicators at all sites, suggesting a prolonged interval of warm, interglacial conditions between 5.0 and 4.1 Ma during the earliest Pliocene.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>DSDP</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>29-284</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment>19 cores, 179 m cored, 28.5 m drilled, 93.2 % recovery</md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Sample code/label | Sample label | Planulina wuellerstorfi, &#948;18O | P. wuellerstorfi &#948;18O | Isotope ratio mass spectrometry | Planulina wuellerstorfi, &#948;13C | P. wuellerstorfi &#948;13C | ODP sample designation | including Cibicidoides kullenbergi | Globigerinoides quadrilobatus, &#948;18O | G. quadril &#948;18O | Globigerinoides quadrilobatus, &#948;13C | G. quadril &#948;13C | Uvigerina sp., &#948;18O | Uvigerina sp. &#948;18O | Uvigerina sp., &#948;13C | Uvigerina sp. &#948;13C</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>1986-03-01T15:55:22</date></data>