<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.823371</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Reflection microscopy and geochemistry at DSDP Leg 55 Holes</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Fe-Ti oxide mineralogy of DSDP Leg 55 basalts</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Magnetic properties of volcanic rocks are controlled mainly by the physical and chemical state of their constituent ferromagnetic minerals. The most important parameters determining magnetic properties are concentration, composition, grain size, and oxidation state. In sea floor basalts, the main ferromagnetic minerals are titanomagnetites which are either unoxidized or, more commonly, have undergone various degrees of posteruptive low-temperature oxidation to become cationdeficient titanomagnetites, or titanomaghemites. The effects of this low-temperature alteration are seen in the increase of Curie temperature and decrease of saturation magnetization and lattice parameter of ferromagnetic minerals (Readman and O'Reilly, 1972). It is now believed that titanomaghemitization of newly formed mid-ocean ridge crust proceeds with a time constant of about 1 m.y., accompanying drastic decrease of the intensity of the natural remanent magnetization (NRM) (Johnson and Atwater, 1977).</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>DSDP</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>55-430A</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment>9 cores, 59 m cored, 28.5 m drilled, 31.1 % recovery</md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Sample code/label | Sample label | ODP sample designation | Flow unit number and type of rock: A, alkalic basalts | Unit | Curie temperature | Curie temp | Thermomagnetic curve | Type | Optical microscopy | Oxidation stage = degree of high-temperature oxidation of titanomagnetite: N, L, M, H = no, low, moderate, high oxidation | Stage | Presence of ilmenite lamellae in (III) planes of (titano-) magnetite host crystal | Ilmenite | Ilm | Presence of pseudobrookite as oxidation product of Ti-rich phase | Pseudobrookite | Psb | Comment | Flow unit number and type of rock: A, alkalic basalts, T, tholeiites | Type of thermomagnetic curve: NO, no oxidation, HT, high-temperature oxidation, LT, low-temperature oxidation | Presence of low-temperature oxidation product | Titanomagnetite | Timag | Degree of high-temperature oxidation of titanomagnetite: N, L, M, H = no, low, moderate, high oxidation | Number | No | Titanium dioxide | TiO2 | Electron microprobe | Aluminium oxide | Al2O3 | Chromium(III) oxide | Cr2O3 | Iron oxide, FeO | FeO | Magnesium oxide | MgO | Manganese oxide | MnO | Total | x | Hemoilmenite | y</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>1980-11-27T22:52:27</date></data>