<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.728541</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Pollen record of sediment core MD99-2348</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Palynology of the Northwestern Mediterranean Shelf (Gulf of Lions): first vegetational record for the last climatic cycle</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Palynology has been performed for the first time on Late Quaternary sediments of the Gulf of Lions. The aim is both to tighten the chronology of seismic profiles in the region, and to elucidate the vegetation of southern France during the Last Climatic Cycle.Four cores, taken on the shelf, mostly record Marine Isotope Stages (MIS) 1 and 2 and part of MIS 3 and MIS 5. The latter sediments might have been preserved in a paleodepression on the emergent shelf between the Rh&#244;ne and the H&#233;rault rivers. It would explain their preservation against transgression and regression erosions of more recent stages.This study also provides a synthesis of palynological continental data collected during the last 40 years in southern Europe. Preliminary comparisons made between the latter and new marine data demonstrate that refugia of Picea and Abies existed in southern France during MIS 3 and MIS 2. The dynamics of Artemisia, deciduous Quercus and Corylus, Abies and finally Fagus is also reconstructed for the last deglaciation. First results obtained in the Gulf of Lions confirm and complete that synthesis.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>PROMESS</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>MD99-2348</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment>Calypso/30m//Brest/16 sections</md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent /><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title>Vegetation dynamics in southern France during the last 30 ky BP in the light of marine palynology</md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title><date>2006-10-14T10:41:57</date></data>