<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.863978</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Radionuclides, Nd isotopes and biogenic Opal in Atlanic Ocean sediments</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Deep water provenance and dynamics of the (de)glacial Atlantic meridional overturning circulation</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Reconstructing past modes of ocean circulation is an essential task in paleoclimatology and paleoceanography. To this end, we combine two sedimentary proxies, Nd isotopes (epsilon-Nd) and the 231Pa/230Th ratio, both of which are not directly involved in the global carbon cycle, but allow the reconstruction of water mass provenance and provide information about the past strength of overturning circulation, respectively. In this study, combined 231Pa/230Th and epsilon-Nd down-core profiles from six Atlantic Ocean sediment cores are presented. The data set is complemented by the two available combined data sets from the literature. From this we derive a comprehensive picture of spatial and temporal patterns and the dynamic changes of the Atlantic Meridional Overturning Circulation over the past ~25 ka. Our results provide evidence for a consistent pattern of glacial/stadial advances of Southern Sourced Water along with a northward circulation mode for all cores in the deeper (&gt;3000 m) Atlantic. Results from shallower core sites support an active overturning cell of shoaled Northern Sourced Water during the LGM and the subsequent deglaciation. Furthermore, we report evidence for a short-lived period of intensified AMOC in the early Holocene.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>IODP</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>177-1089A</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment>23 cores, 216.3 m cored, 0 m drilled, 69.2 % recovery</md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent /><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title>Stable isotope fractionation and differential dissolution in recent planktonic foraminifera from Pacific box-cores</md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title><date>2016-08-22T09:21:50</date></data>