<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.726643</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Clay mineral assemblages in the western Baltic Sea</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Clay mineral assemblages of the western Baltic Sea: recent distribution and relation to sedimentary units</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Surface samples and nine cores from the western Baltic Sea and marginal water bodies were investigated for clay mineral composition. The clay mineral assemblages of recent sediments are rather homogeneous. Variations result mainly from the erosion of different glacial source deposits. High percentages of illite and low kaolinite/chlorite and quartz/feldspar ratios are characteristic for this glacial source. Advection of kaolinite-rich suspensions from the North Sea is believed to account for higher kaolinite/chlorite ratios in the Mecklenburg Bight. A contribution of the rivers Trave and Oder to the western Baltic Sea is indicated by increased smectite values in marginal water bodies. They correspond to increased kaolinite/chlorite and quartz/feldspar ratios. In the main basins the river signal is diluted beyond recognition. Cores from the Arkona, Bornholm and Gotland Basins penetrate through post-Littorina muds and sediments of the Ancylus Lake/Yoldia Sea into Late Glacial sediments of the Baltic Ice Lake. Clay mineral assemblages are characterized by an increase in kaolinite/chlorite ratios from Late Glacial to Holocene sediments, with a distinct shift at each facies change. This allows the distinction and core to core correlation of main lithological units with kaolinite/chlorite ratios. Kaolinite enrichment of Holocene muds corresponds to a brackish-marine facies and may reflect influx of kaolinite-rich suspensions from the North Sea. Cores from the lagoon of the Oderhaff show fluctuations in the contributions of the two main sediment sources: river suspension and glacial deposits during the Late Glacial and Postglacial sequence. Lacustrine sediments, which were deposited prior to 5500 years B.P. are characterized by smectite, kaolinite and quartz from the drainage area of the Oder river. Erosion of coastal and offshore glacial boulder clays with the Littorina transgression supplied a marine component rich in illite, chlorite and feldspars to the brackish muds of the Oderhaff.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>GIK18014-2</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment>Schlick</md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Smectite | Sme | X-ray diffraction TEXTUR, clay fraction | Kaolinite | Kln | Chlorite | Chl | Illite | Ill | Illite 5&#197;/10&#197; Esquevin-index | Ill EI | Illite half height width, glycolized | Ill HHW glyc | clay fraction | Quartz/Feldspar ratio | Qz/Fsp | Sand | Grain size, sieving/settling tube | Silt | Size fraction &lt; 0.002 mm, &gt; 9 phi, clay | &lt;2 &#181;m, &gt;9 phi | Quartz | Qz | X-ray diffraction (XRD) | Pyrite, FeS2 | Py</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>1997-08-20T16:28:51</date></data>