<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.856643</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Physical oceaongraphy and hydrochemistry measured on water bottle samples during METEOR cruise M84/3 in 2001</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Repeat hydrography in the Mediterranean Sea, data from the Meteor cruise 84/3 in 2011</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Here we report on data from an oceanographic cruise on the German research vessel Meteor covering large parts of the Mediterranean Sea during spring of 2011. The main objective of this cruise was to conduct measurements of physical, chemical and biological variables on a section across the Mediterranean Sea with the goal of producing a synoptic picture of the distribution of relevant physical and biogeochemical properties, in order to compare those to historic data sets. During the cruise, a comprehensive data set of relevant variables following the guide lines for repeat hydrography outlined by the GO-SHIP group (http://www.go-ship.org/) was collected. The measurements include salinity and temperature (CTD), an over-determined carbonate system, inorganic nutrients, oxygen, transient tracers (CFC-12, SF6), helium isotopes and tritium, and carbon isotopes. The cruise sampled all major basins of the Mediterranean Sea following roughly an east-to-west section from the coast of Lebanon through to the Strait of Gibraltar, and to the coast of Portugal. Also a south-to-north section from the Ionian Sea to the Adriatic Sea was carried out. Additionally, sampling in the Aegean, Adriatic and Tyrrhenian Seas were carried out. The sections roughly followed lines and positions that have been sampled previously during other programs, thus providing the opportunity for comparative investigations of the temporal development of various parameters.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Pressure, water | Press | CTD | Temperature, water | Temp | Salinity | Sal | Oxygen | O2 | ITS-90 | PSS-78 | OXYGEN | Oxygen from CTD | Quality flag | Flag | WOCE quality flag | Bottle | Oxygen from water bottle sample | Silicate | SILCAT | Nitrate | NITRAT | Nitrite | NITRIT | Phosphate | PHSPHT | Freon-12 (dichlorodifluoromethane) | CFC-12 | Sulfur hexafluoride, SF6 | SF6 | Carbon, total | TC | Alkalinity, total | AT | pH | Temperature, technical | T tech | Tritium | TRITUM | Tritium, standard deviation | TRITUM std dev | Helium | HELIUM | &#948; Helium-3 | &#948;3He | delta Helium-3 | &#948; Helium-3, standard deviation | &#948;3He std dev | Neon | NEON | &#948;14C | delta 14C | &#948;14C, standard deviation | &#948;14C std dev | &#948;13C | delta 13C | Temperature, water, potential | Tpot | Barium | Ba | Barium, standard deviation | Ba std dev | Bottle number | BEDFORD | Identification | ID</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>2013-01-06T08:41:41</date></data>