<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.819824</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Anisotropy and acoustic properties at DSDP Holes 62-463 and 62-465A</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Acoustic properties of limestones from the northcentral Pacific, Deep Sea Drilling Project Leg 62</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Variations of acoustic properties within the sediment column may significantly affect the propagation of acoustic energy in the upper portion of the oceanic crust. Moreover, the acoustic properties of sediments reflect their mineral compositions, fabrics, and degrees of compaction and cementation. Hence, the physical properties of indurated deep-sea sediments are of considerable geophysical and geological interest. Chalks and limestones are particularly important because substantial accumulations of biogenic carbonates are generally present at the base of the deep-sea sediment column, and high-standing features such as Hess Rise are capped by calcareous deposits. This paper constitutes a preliminary report of the compressional-wave velocities and densities of 31 indurated calcareous sediment samples recovered at DSDP Sites 463 and 465, in the Mid-Pacific Mountains and on Hess Rise, respectively. The sample set includes nine pairs of samples in which velocities were measured parallel and perpendicular to bedding to determine the velocity anisotropy of the sediment. This research is part of an ongoing study of the seismic properties of indurated deep-sea carbonates.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>DSDP</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>62-463</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment>92 cores, 820.5 m cored, 0 m drilled, 37.2 % recovery</md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Sample code/label | Sample label | ODP sample designation | Direction | Density, wet bulk | WBD | see reference(s) | Pressure (kbar) = 0.1 | Velocity, compressional wave | Vp | Pulse transmission technique (Birch, 1960) | Pressure (kbar) = 0.2 | Pressure (kbar) = 0.3 | Pressure (kbar) = 0.4 | Pressure (kbar) = 0.5 | Pressure (kbar) = 0.6 | Lithology/composition/facies | Lithology | Vh | V'v, Corrected vertical velocity | delta V | Difference | Diff | a = Vh/V'v | Ratio</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>1981-09-27T12:00:56</date></data>