<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.854998</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Plant height along the plant diversity gradient in the Jena Experiment (Main Experiment, year 2007)</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title /><md:MetaData/md:abstract>This data set contains measurements of plant height: vegetative height (heighest leaf) and regenerative height (heighest flower) in 2007 from the Main Experiment plots of a large grassland biodiversity experiment (the Jena Experiment, see further details below). In the Main Experiment, 82 grassland plots of 20 x 20 m were established from a pool of 60 species belonging to four functional groups (grasses, legumes, tall and small herbs). In May 2002, varying numbers of plant species from this species pool were sown into the plots to create a gradient of plant species richness (1, 2, 4, 8, 16 and 60 species) and functional richness (1, 2, 3, 4 functional groups). Plots were maintained by bi-annual weeding and mowing. In 2007, plant height was recorded twice a year just before biomass harvest (during peak standing biomass in late May and in late August). For target plant individuals at 10 points separated by 1 m each along a transect in the central area in the plots, vegetative height (heighest leaf) and regenerative height (heighest flower) were measured as standing height (without stretching the plant). In 2007, also the plots of the management experiment, that altered mowing frequency and fertilized subplots (see further details below) were sampled by measuring vegatation height five times, every 0.5m on a 3m transekt along the side of the management plots. Provided are the individual measurements and the mean over the measured plants.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>JenExp</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>JenExp_2007</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent /><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title>The Jena Experiment: six years of data from a grassland biodiversity experiment</md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title><date>2015-11-16T10:14:49</date></data>