<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.873759</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>n-Alkanes and compound-specific isotopes in the Orange River system</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Holocene hydrologic and vegetation developments in the Orange River catchment (South Africa) and their controls</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>The summer rainfall zone (SRZ) in the South African interior experienced pronounced hydrological and vegetation changes during the Holocene inferred to be driven mainly by shifts in atmospheric and oceanic circulations systems. The exact mechanisms controlling these changes are still debated. To gain better insights into the Holocene environmental changes in the South African SRZ and their driving factors, we analysed compound-specific carbon and hydrogen isotopes of plant wax n-alkanes (&#948;13Cwax and &#948;Dwax) from a marine sediment core covering the last 9900 years. The core has been recovered offshore the mouth of the Orange River, predominantly draining the South African summer rainfall region. Our data indicate a dry early Holocene and a gradual increase of wetter conditions with a higher abundance of C4 vegetation towards the middle Holocene. Wettest conditions occurred around 3900 cal. yr BP. The last 3900 years were characterised by a gradual aridification overlain by variable wetter conditions. During the 'Little Ice Age' (LIA: ca. 640&#8211;310 cal. yr BP), relatively dry conditions with elevated C4 plant contributions occurred. This opposite behaviour, that is, more C4 plant contribution during drier conditions compared to the remainder of the Holocene, points towards an influence of winter rainfall in the lower Orange River catchment during the late-Holocene and a decline in summer rainfall. We emphasise the importance of changes in the latitudinal insolation gradient (LIG) as a potentially important controlling mechanism for hydrologic and vegetation changes in the SRZ.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>MARUM</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>n-Alkane C29 per unit sediment mass | C29/sed | n-Alkane C31 per unit sediment mass | C31/sed | Sum n-alkanes C25-C33 | C25-C33 | concentration sum n-C25 - n-C33 (&#181;g/g sed) | Standard deviation | Std dev | Carbon Preference Index of n-Alkanes (C27-C33) | CPI-(27-33) | 27-33 | n-Alkane, average chain length | ACL n-Alkane | with respect to VPDB | n-Alkane C29, &#948;13C | C29 &#948;13C | n-Alkane C29, &#948;13C, standard deviation | C29 &#948;13C std dev | n-Alkane C31, &#948;13C | C31 &#948;13C | n-Alkane C31, &#948;13C, standard deviation | C31 &#948;13C std dev | with respect to VSMOW | n-Alkane C29, &#948;D | C29 &#948;D | n-Alkane C29, dD, standard deviation | C29 dD std dev | n-Alkane C31, &#948;D | C31 &#948;D | n-Alkane C31, dD, standard deviation | C31 dD std dev | Depth, top/min | Depth top | Depth, bottom/max | Depth bot | n-Alkane C33, &#948;D | C33 &#948;D | n-Alkane C33, dD, standard deviation | C33 dD std dev</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>2017-03-22T09:06:30</date></data>