<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.858957</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Manganese nodules recovered by R/V Vityaz expedition</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>On the age of iron-manganese concretions from the Indian and Pacific Oceans</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Uranium, radium, thorium and ionium were determined directly on seven concretions from three stations in the Indian Ocean, and on two concretions and a manganese-rich crust from two stations in the Pacific Ocean. The uranium content averages 3 to 5 gamma/g and the thorium content varies only slightly, but the Th/U ratio in the concretions is typically 2 to 5 in the Indian Ocean and 5 to 15.5 in the Pacific. The ionium content ranges from 1.0 x 10-9 to 3.6 10**-9 g/g in concretions from both oceans. Radium is more abundant in specimens from the Pacific Ocean (Ra = 3 - 12.7 x 10**-11 g/g) than from the Indian Ocean (1.5 - 5.2 x 10**-11 g/g).   Analyses for Ca, Mn, Fe, Si, Ni, P, and ignition loss are also given. Radioactive equilibria between uranium, ionium, and radium are strongly disturbed throughout the concretions, and the RA/U and lo/U ratios generally exceed equilibrium ratios. Migration of radium from interior layers was established, so that neither determination of the ages of the concretions nor of their rates of growth can be considered reliable. The age of the concretions cannot exceed 800,000 years, and all grew within relatively short periods of time, there may have been "dormant" periods during growth. Estimates of growth rates are calculated from the radium and ionium contents, they show marked discordance.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>NOAA-MMS</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>VITYAZ3782-TR</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Identification | ID | Position | Visual description | Deposit type | Quantity of deposit | Quantity | Size | Substrate type | Substrate | Description | Loss on ignition | LOI | Wet chemistry | Insoluble residue | Insol res | Silicon | Si | Manganese | Mn | Iron | Fe | Calcium | Ca | Nickel | Ni | Phosphorus | P | Uranium | U | Luminescent analysis | orig. Ionium [ng/g] | Thorium 230 | 230Th | X-ray radiometry | Radium | Ra | Emanescence radiometry | Thorium | Th | Gas chromatography</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title>The NOAA and MMS Marine Minerals Geochemical Database</md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title><date>1963-03-16T20:47:36</date></data>