<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.759825</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Fluxes and foraminifera fluxes of sediment traps in the Peru-Chile Current</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Seasonal variations of the particle flux in the Peru-Chile Current at 30&#176;S under normal and El Nino conditions</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Time-series sediment traps were deployed 180 km off the Chilean coast at 30&#176;S in the Peru-Chile Current during the El Ni&#241;o period 1991/1992 (6 months) and during the 'normal' period 1993/1994 (12 months). Under normal conditions in 1993/1994 the particle fluxes display a pronounced seasonal cycle marked by a settling phytoplankton bloom in September, intermediate fluxes until January, and low fluxes between January and July. This seasonal pattern is also reflected in stable isotope data, measured on the planktic foraminifera species Neogloboquadrina pachyderma (dex.) and Globigerina bulloides, which indicate persistent upwelling conditions between August and February followed by a stratified water column between March and July. The total flux under normal conditions amounts to 65.1 g m**-2 a**-1, with the main flux constituents contributing 47.6% (carbonate), 26.4% (lithogenic matter), 17.4% (biogenic opal), and 8.6% (organic matter), respectively. Based on these particle flux data the export production has been estimated to be 42 gC m**-2 a**-1. Although the main flux event in September was not sampled in the El Ni&#241;o period 1991/1992, the available record from November 1991 to April 1992 allows an interesting comparison with the fluxes of the normal year. The total amount of fluxes and the timing of minor flux events are very similar under normal and under El Ni&#241;o conditions. However, increased proportions of organic carbon and lithogenic matter under El Ni&#241;o conditions are interpreted to reflect faster sedimentation and preferred scavenging of organic matter by elevated lithogenic fluxes rather than increased productivity. The higher lithogenic fluxes under El Ni&#241;o conditions are probably due to increased precipitation and terrestial runoff in the arid to semiarid northern part of Chile.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>JGOFS</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>CH3-1_trap</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment>upper trap, 2333 m water depth (Deployment-Ship: Janequeo, Recovery-Ship: Vidal Gormaz)</md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Date/time end | Duration, number of days | Duration | Calculated | Sample code/label | Sample label | Split | split | Sample mass | Samp m | Weighted | Total mass flux per day | Mass flux | Calculated, see reference(s) | Lithogenic flux per day | Litho flux | Calcium carbonate flux | CaCO3 flux | Silica, particulate flux per day | PSiO2 flux | Organic matter, particulate, flux | POM flux | Carbon, organic, particulate flux per day | POC flux | Nitrogen, total flux | N flux | Carbon/Nitrogen ratio | C/N | &#948;13C, organic carbon | &#948;13C Corg | Mass spectrometer Finnigan MAT 251 | total | Foraminifera, planktic flux | Foram plankt flux | Globigerina bulloides flux | G. bulloides flux | Globigerinella calida flux | G. calida flux | Globigerinita glutinata flux | G. glutinata flux | Globigerinita uvula flux | G. uvula flux | Globigerinoides ruber flux | G. ruber flux | Globorotalia inflata flux | G. inflata flux | Globorotalia menardii flux | G. menardii flux | Globorotalia scitula flux | G. scitula flux | Globorotalia truncatulinoides flux | G. truncatulinoides flux | Globorotaloides hexagonus flux | G. hexagonus flux | Neogloboquadrina dutertrei flux | N. dutertrei flux | Neogloboquadrina pachyderma sinistral flux | N. pachyderma s flux | Neogloboquadrina pachyderma dextral flux | N. pachyderma d flux | Orbulina universa flux | O. universa flux | Tenuitella iota flux | T. iota flux | Turborotalita quinqueloba flux | T. quinqueloba flux</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title>Seasonal flux patterns of planktic foraminifera in the Peru-Chile Current</md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title><date>2000-04-26T14:09:05</date></data>