<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.782639</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Gotland Deep (Baltic Sea) independent age model based on Palaeomagnetic Secular Variation (PSV) and lead (Pb) deposition profiles</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Using an independent geochronology based on palaeomagnetic secular variation (PSV) and atmospheric Pb deposition to date Baltic Sea sediments and infer 14C reservoir age</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Dating of sediment cores from the Baltic Sea has proven to be difficult due to uncertainties surrounding the 14C reservoir age and a scarcity of macrofossils suitable for dating. Here we present the results of multiple dating methods carried out on cores in the Gotland Deep area of the Baltic Sea. Particular emphasis is placed on the Littorina stage (8 ka ago to the present) of the Baltic Sea and possible changes in the 14C reservoir age of our dated samples. Three geochronological methods are used. Firstly, palaeomagnetic secular variations (PSV) are reconstructed, whereby ages are transferred to PSV features through comparison with varved lake sediment based PSV records. Secondly, lead (Pb) content and stable isotope analysis are used to identify past peaks in anthropogenic atmospheric Pb pollution. Lastly, 14C determinations were carried out on benthic foraminifera (Elphidium spec.) samples from the brackish Littorina stage of the Baltic Sea. Determinations carried out on smaller samples (as low as 4 &#181;g C) employed an experimental, state-of-the-art method involving the direct measurement of CO2 from samples by a gas ion source without the need for a graphitisation step - the first time this method has been performed on foraminifera in an applied study. The PSV chronology, based on the uppermost Littorina stage sediments, produced ten age constraints between 6.29 and 1.29 cal ka BP, and the Pb depositional analysis produced two age constraints associated with the Medieval pollution peak. Analysis of PSV data shows that adequate directional data can be derived from both the present Littorina saline phase muds and Baltic Ice Lake stage varved glacial sediments. Ferrimagnetic iron sulphides, most likely authigenic greigite (Fe3S4), present in the intermediate Ancylus Lake freshwater stage sediments acquire a gyroremanent magnetisation during static alternating field (AF) demagnetisation, preventing the identification of a primary natural remanent magnetisation for these sediments. An inferred marine reservoir age offset (deltaR) is calculated by comparing the foraminifera 14C determinations to a PSV &amp; Pb age model. This deltaR is found to trend towards younger values upwards in the core, possibly due to a gradual change in hydrographic conditions brought about by a reduction in marine water exchange from the open sea due to continued isostatic rebound.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>370530-5</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Equivalent sediment depth in core 372740-3 | Depth, relative | Depth rel | Inclination | Incl | Inclination, relative | Incl rel | Declination, relative | Decl rel | +rotated to zero | detrended | Loss on ignition | LOI | Calculated from weight loss after ignition at 450 &#176;C | 95.4% confidence interval | 68.2% range | Age, dated, range, minimum | Age dated min | Age, dated, range, maximum | Age dated max | Age model | Age, calculated calendar years | Lead | Pb | Expanded uncertainty, k=2 | Lead, standard deviation | Pb std dev | Lead 206/Lead 207 ratio | 206Pb/207Pb | Expanded uncertainty | Lead 206/Lead 207, error | 206Pb/207Pb e | Susceptibility, specific | chi | NRM, Intensity | Inten (NRM) | ARM, Susceptibility, per unit mass | kappa (ARM) | Saturation isothermal remanent magnetization | SIRM | SigmaSIRM | SigmaRRM | Remanent magnetization, rotational, intensity, per unit mass | RRM</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>2012-05-20T00:06:03</date></data>