<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.810645</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Late Cretaceous volcaniclastic rocks at DSDP Holes 74-525A and 74-528</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Late Cretaceous volcaniclastic rocks from the Walvis Ridge, Southeast Atlantic, Leg 74</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Volcaniclastic rocks of Late Cretaceous age occur in four out of five sites (525, 527, 528, 529) drilled on the crest and the northwest flank of the Walvis Ridge during Leg 74. They are mostly interlayered with and overlie basement in the lowermost 10-100 m of the sedimentary section. Rocks from Holes 525A and 528 were studied megascopically and microscopically, by XRD, and XRF chemical analyses of whole-rock major and trace elements were undertaken. The dominant rock of Hole 528 volcaniclastics is a fine-grained (silt to fine sand), mostly matrix-bearing (partly matrix-rich) vitric "tuff," occurring as 5-110 cm thick, partly graded layers, some of which are distinctly bedded. Volcaniclastics of Hole 525A are generally richer in sanidine crystals. Most rocks contain some nonvolcanic clasts, chiefly foraminifers and lesser amounts of shallow-water fossil debris. Scoria shards, clasts of tachylite, and fine-grained basalts as well as chemical analyses suggest a basaltic to intermediate composition for most rocks of Hole 528, whereas volcaniclastics of Hole 525A are more silicic. The occurrence of tachylite and epiclastic, coarse-grained, basaltic clasts throughout the volcaniclastic sequence at Site 528 indicates shallow-water eruptions and perhaps even ocean island volcanism. The minor occurrence in Hole 528 of trachytic? pumice shards with phenocrysts of K-feldspar and the abundance of such shards in rocks from Hole 525A indicate Plinian eruptions characteristic of more mature stages of ocean island evolution. The sedimentary structures of volcaniclastic layers and their occurrence within deep sea calcareous oozes indicate a mass flow origin. Diagenetic alteration of the volcaniclastic rocks is pronounced, and four major stages of glass shard alteration are distinguished. Despite the effects of alteration and small-scale redistribution of elements and the admixture of nonvolcanic components, there were no drastic changes in the chemical composition of the rocks, except for pronounced increases in K and Rb and decreases in Ca and Fe. The basaltic volcaniclastic rocks very much resemble basement basalts in that they are moderately evolved tholeiites derived from an LIL-enriched mantle source with Zr/Nb ratios (Hole 528) of 5 to 6. This, in conjunction with the interbedding of volcaniclastic rocks and basement lavas, indicates contemporaneous seamount or island and basement volcanic activity involving magmas derived from similar sources.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>DSDP</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>74-525A</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment>62 cores, 549.7 m cored, 6 m drilled, 74 % recovery</md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Sample code/label | Sample label | ODP sample designation | Smectite | Sme | X-ray diffraction (XRD) | Mica | Calcite | Cal | Quartz | Qz | Sanidine | Sa | Undifferentiated | Feldspar | Fsp | Clinoptilolite | Cpt | Phillipsite | Php | Volcaniclastic | Rock fragments | Rock fragm | Including volcanics | Ooze | Insoluble | Residual | Total residue | Size fraction &lt; 0.002 mm, &gt; 9 phi, clay | &lt;2 &#181;m, &gt;9 phi | Size fraction 0.063-0.002 mm, silt, mud | 63-2 &#181;m | Size fraction 0.250-0.063 mm | 250-63 &#181;m | Size fraction &gt; 0.250 mm | &gt;250 &#181;m | Comment | Silicon dioxide | SiO2 | X-ray fluorescence (XRF) | Titanium dioxide | TiO2 | Aluminium oxide | Al2O3 | Iron oxide, Fe2O3 | Fe2O3 | Total iron | Iron oxide, FeO | FeO | Manganese oxide | MnO | Magnesium oxide | MgO | Calcium oxide | CaO | Sodium oxide | Na2O | Potassium oxide | K2O | Phosphorus oxide | P2O5 | + | Water in rock | H2O | Carbon dioxide | CO2 | Total | Sulfur, total | S | Chlorine | Cl | Chromium | Cr | Nickel | Ni | Copper | Cu | Zinc | Zn | Rubidium | Rb | Strontium | Sr | Yttrium | Y | Zirconium | Zr | Niobium | Nb | Barium | Ba | Unit questionable | Clasts, vitric | Volcanic fragments | Volc fragm | Clasts, lithic | Clasts, crystal | Shards, scoria | Volcanic glass | Volc glass | Shards, spalling | Shards, pumice | Volcanic clasts, tachylite | Lithic grains | Lithic | Volcanic clasts, "trachyte" | Crystal clasts | Plagioclase | Pl | Crystal clasts, "hollow" | Kalifeldspar | Kfs | Clinopyroxene | Cpx | Spinel | Spl | Crystal clasts, "fresh" | Glasses | Diagenetic alteration sequence, smectite fibrous rim | Alteration | Diagenetic alteration sequence, smectite granular | Diagenetic alteration sequences, thomsonite? | Diagenetic alteration sequences, phillipsite needle | Diagenetic alteration sequences, phillipsite prismatic | Diagenetic alteration sequences, analcite | Diagenetic alteration sequences, clinoptilolite | Diagenetic alteration sequences, adularia | Diagenetic alteration sequences, carbonate | Interparticle, smectite pellets | Cement | Interparticle, smectite fibrous | Interparticle, "hollows" | Interparticle, phillipsite needle | Interparticle, phillipsite prismatic | Interparticle, clinoptilolite | Interparticle, carbonate</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>1984-04-24T16:31:56</date></data>