<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.854306</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Annotated record of the detailed examination of Mn deposits from &#8220;Michael Sars&#8221; North Atlantic Deep-Sea Expedition 1910</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Report on the deposit-samples collected during the "Michael Sars" North Atlantic Deep-Sea Expedition 1910. In: Report on the scientific results of the "Michael Sars" north Atlantic deep-sea expedition 1910, carried out under the auspices of the Norwegian government and the superintendence of Sir John Murray, K.C.B., and Dr. Johan Hjort</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>The deposit-samples and rock specimens brought home by the "Michael Sars" were received in the Challenger Office shortly after the return of the expedition, and upon examination the rock specimens proved to be so numerous and to offer so many points of interest that Dr. B. N. Peach, F. R. S., was requested to report upon them. A brief note on his results appeared in "The Depths of the Ocean" (London, Macmillan, 1912), pp. 202-209, and his detailed report was published in the Proc. Roy. Soc. Edin., vol. XXXII., pp. 262&#8212;291, 1912. When the author met Dr. Hjort in London in May 1914 he desired me to prepare, for publication in the series of Reports on the scientific Results of the "Michael Sars" North Atlantic Expedition, descriptions of the deposit samples, including for each station a brief summary of Dr. Peach's observations on the rock-specimens obtained. The accompanying Report shows that the "Michael Sars" expedition has made a notable contribution to our knowledge regarding the materials covering the floor of the North Atlantic Ocean.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>NOAA-MMS</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>MSARS-48</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent /><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title>The NOAA and MMS Marine Minerals Geochemical Database</md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title><date>1932-10-23T12:23:03</date></data>