<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.704663</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Carbon and carbonate concentrations of recent and Pleistocene sediments of the Norwegian-Greenland Sea</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Recent and Pleistocene carbonate dissolution in sediments of the Norwegian-Greenland Sea</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Surface sediment samples from the Norwegian-Greenland Sea were investigated to reconstruct the spatial distribution of recent carbonate dissolution on the seafloor. Additionally, carbonate dissolution records of Ocean Drilling Program sites 985 and 987 are presented to outline the development of Pleistocene carbonate preservation.Today, well-preserved carbonate tests can be observed along the inflow of warm Atlantic surface water, extending as far as into the northernmost Norwegian-Greenland Sea. Increased dissolution is indicated along the continental margins and in the deepest parts of the Greenland Basin. Factors favoring carbonate preservation were found to be supersaturation of the water column with respect to calcium carbonate, high carbonate rain and probably excess alkalinity of bottom waters supplied by the arctic river discharge. Supralysoklinal dissolution is most important for recent carbonate dissolution in the Norwegian-Greenland Sea, whereas the deepest parts of the Greenland Basin reaches the calcite saturation horizon.Pleistocene dissolution records show some prominent peaks of extreme carbonate dissolution. During the Brunhes chron, carbonate dissolution maxima can be related to meltwater pulses, which probably inhibited deep-water formation in the Norwegian-Greenland Sea during deglaciation events. Long-term severe carbonate dissolution is evident during the late Matuyama chron. This can be probably related to low carbonate rain, due to a more eastwards located East Greenland Current and the nearly absence of the not yet polar adapted Neogloboquadrina pachyderma sin. during that period. Extreme dissolution events during the late Matuyama indicate strongly reduced deep-water formation.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>ODP</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>162-985A</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment>62 cores, 587.9 m cored, 0 m drilled, 94.1 % recovery</md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Sample code/label | Sample label | ODP sample designation | Depth, composite | Depth comp | Intercore correlation | Carbon, organic, total | TOC | Element analyser CHN, LECO | Carbon, inorganic, total | TIC | Carbon, total | TC | Calcium carbonate | CaCO3</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>2000-09-24T14:07:09</date></data>