<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.841496</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>(Table 1) Seasonal sea ice concentration and the observed changes from 1972 to 2007 for the Southern Beaufort Sea</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Changes in the climate of the Alaskan North Slope and the ice concentration of the adjacent Beaufort Sea</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>A reliable data set of Arctic sea ice concentration based on satellite observations exists since 1972. Over this time period of 36 years western arctic temperatures have increased, the temperature rise varies significantly from one season to another and over multi-year time scales. In contrast to most of Alaska, however, on the North Slope the warming continued after 1976, when a circulation change occurred, as expressed in the PDO index. The mean temperature increase for Barrow over the 36-year period was 2.9&#176;C, a very substantial change. Wind speeds increased by 18% over this time period, however, the increase were non-linear and showed a peak in the early 1990s. The sea ice extent of the Arctic Ocean has decreased strongly in recent years, and in September 2007 a new record in the amount of open water was recorded in the Western Arctic. We observed for the Southern Beaufort Sea a fairly steady increase in the mean annual amount of open water from 14% in 1972 to 39% in 2007, as deduced from the best linear fit. In late summer the decrease is much larger, and September has, on average, the least ice concentration (22%), followed by August (35%) and October (54%). The correlation coefficient between mean annual values of temperature and sea ice concentration was 0.84. On a monthly basis, the best correlation coefficient was found in October with 0.88. However, the relationship between winter temperatures and the sea ice break-up in summer was weak. While the temperature correlated well with the CO2 concentration (r=0.86), the correlation coefficient between CO2 and sea ice was lower (r=-0.68). After comparing the ice concentration with 17 circulation indices, the best relation was found with the Pacific Circulation Index (r=-0.59).</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>IPY</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>Beaufort_Sea_coastNA</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent /><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>2010-01-13T10:28:22</date></data>