<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.770305</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Radiocarbon dataing, stable oxygen isotopes, and Mg/Ca ratios in surface sediment samples of the tropical eastern Indian Ocean</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Reconstructing the thermal structure of the upper ocean: Insights from planktic foraminifera shell chemistry and alkenones in modern sediments of the tropical eastern Indian Ocean</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Shell chemistry of planktic foraminifera and the alkenone unsaturation index in 69 surface sediment samples in the tropical eastern Indian Ocean off West and South Indonesia were studied. Results were compared to modern hydrographic data in order to assess how modern environmental conditions are preserved in sedimentary record, and to determine the best possible proxies to reconstruct seasonality, thermal gradient and upper water column characteristics in this part of the world ocean. Our results imply that alkenone-derived temperatures record annual mean temperatures in the study area. However, this finding might be an artifact due to the temperature limitation of this proxy above 28&#176;C. Combined study of shell stable oxygen isotope and Mg/Ca ratio of planktic foraminifera suggests that Globigerinoides ruber sensu stricto (s.s.), G. ruber sensu lato (s.l.), and G. sacculifer calcify within the mixed-layer between 20 m and 50 m, whereas Globigerina bulloides records mixed-layer conditions at ~50 m depth during boreal summer. Mean calcifications of Pulleniatina obliquiloculata, Neogloboquadrina dutertrei, and Globorotalia tumida occur at the top of the thermocline during boreal summer, at ~75 m, 75-100 m, and 100 m, respectively. Shell Mg/Ca ratios of all species show a significant correlation with temperature at their apparent calcification depths and validate the application of previously published temperature calibrations, except for G. tumida that requires a regional Mg/Ca-temperature calibration (Mg/Ca = 0.41 exp (0.068*T)). We show that the difference in Mg/Ca-temperatures of the mixed-layer species and the thermocline species, particularly between G. ruber s.s. (or s.l.) and P. obliquiloculata, can be applied to track changes in the upper water column stratification. Our results provide critical tools for reconstructing past changes in the hydrography of the study area and their relation to monsoon, El Ni&#241;o-Southern Oscillation, and the Indian Ocean Dipole Mode.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>MARUM</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>GeoB10008-4</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment>6/6 4/4</md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Sample comment | Area/locality | Area | Depth, top/min | Depth top | Depth, bottom/max | Depth bot | G. ruber s.s., b | Globigerinoides ruber white, &#948;18O | G. ruber w &#948;18O | Mass spectrometer Finnigan MAT 251 | G. ruber s.s. | Globigerinoides ruber white, Magnesium/Calcium ratio | G. ruber w Mg/Ca | ICP-OES, Perkin-Elmer, Optima 3300R | G. ruber s.l. | Globigerinoides sacculifer, &#948;18O | G. sacculifer &#948;18O | Globigerinoides sacculifer, Magnesium/Calcium ratio | G. sacculifer Mg/Ca | Globigerina bulloides, &#948;18O | G. bulloides &#948;18O | Globigerina bulloides, Magnesium/Calcium ratio | G. bulloides Mg/Ca | Pulleniatina obliquiloculata, &#948;18O | P. obliqu. &#948;18O | Pulleniatina obliquiloculata, Magnesium/Calcium ratio | P. obliqu. Mg/Ca | b | Neogloboquadrina dutertrei, &#948;18O | N. dutertrei &#948;18O | Neogloboquadrina dutertrei, Magnesium/Calcium ratio | N. dutertrei Mg/Ca | Globorotalia tumida, &#948;18O | G. tumida &#948;18O | Globorotalia tumida, Magnesium/Calcium ratio | G. tumida Mg/Ca | Alkenone, unsaturation index UK'37 | UK'37 | Uk'37 | Sea surface temperature | SST | Calculated after Conte et al. (2006) | Sample code/label | Sample label | see comment | Species | Age, dated | Age dated | Age, 14C AMS | Age, error | Age e | 1 sigma (68%), [BP = 1950 AD] | Calendar age | Cal age | Calendar age, standard deviation | Cal age std dev | Age, comment | Comm</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>2011-10-05T13:27:01</date></data>