<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.811249</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Early Eocene benthic foraminifera of DSDP Hole 48-401</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Multiple early Eocene benthic foraminiferal assemblage and d13C fluctuations at DSDP Site 401 (Bay of Biscay - NE Atlantic)</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Within the last decade, several early Eocene hyperthermals have been detected globally. These transient warming events have mainly been characterized geochemically - using stable isotopes, carbonate content measurements or XRF core scanning - yet detailed micropaleontological records are sparse, limiting our understanding of the driving forces behind hyperthermals and of the contemporaneous paleoceanography. Here, detailed geochemical and quantitative benthic foraminiferal records are presented from lower Eocene pelagic sediments of Deep Sea Drilling Project Site 401 (Bay of Biscay, northeast Atlantic). In calcareous nannofossil zone NP11, several clay-enriched levels correspond to negative d13C and d18O bulk-rock excursions with amplitudes of up to ~0.75 per mil, suggesting that significant injections of 12C-enriched greenhouse gasses and small temperature rises took place. Coeval with several of these hyperthermal events, the benthic foraminiferal record reveals increased relative abundances of oligotrophic taxa (e.g. Nuttallides umbonifera) and a reduction in the abundance of buliminid species followed by an increase of opportunistic taxa (e.g. Globocassidulina subglobosa and Gyroidinoides spp.). These short-lived faunal perturbations are thought to be caused by reduced seasonality of productivity resulting in a decreased Corg flux to the seafloor. Moreover, the sedimentological record suggests that an enhanced influx of terrigenous material occurred during these events. Additionally, the most intense d13C decline (here called level d) gives rise to a small, yet pronounced long-term shift in the benthic foraminiferal composition at this site, possibly due to the reappraisal of upwelling and the intensification of bottom water currents. These observations imply that environmental changes during (smaller) hyperthermal events are also reflected in the composition of deep-sea benthic communities on both short (&lt;100 kyr) and longer time scales. We conclude that the faunal patterns of the hyperthermals observed at Site 401 strongly resemble those observed in other deep-sea early Paleogene hyperthermal deposits, suggesting that similar processes have driven them.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>DSDP</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Sample code/label | Sample label | ODP sample designation | Calcium carbonate | CaCO3 | Carbonate bomb (M&#252;ller &amp; Gastner, 1971) | Size fraction &gt; 0.063 mm, sand | &gt;63 &#181;m | Carbon, organic, total | TOC | Element analyser, Metalyt CS-100 (ELTRA Corp.) | &#948;13C, carbonate | &#948;13C carb | Mass spectrometer Finnigan MAT 252 | &#948;18O, carbonate | &#948;18O carb | fauna, X = analyzed, - not analyzed | Method comment | Method comm | Nuttallides umbonifera | N. umbonifera | Counting &gt;63 &#181;m fraction | Cibicidoides eocaenus | C. eocaenus | Pseudoparrella minuta | P. minuta | Bulimina virginiana | B. virginiana | Globocassidulina subglobosa | G. subglobosa | Bulimina thanetensis | B. thanetensis | including B. huneri | Bolivina crenulata | B. crenulata | Anomalinoides praespissiformis | A. praespissiformis | Buliminella grata | B. grata | Stilostomella plummerae | S. plummerae | Brizalina carinata | B. carinata | including E. bronnimanni | Eponides bollii | E. bollii | Gyroidinoides complanata | G. complanata | Praebulimina reussi | P. reussi | Bulimina tuxpamensis | B. tuxpamensis | sp. 1 | Praebulimina sp. | Heronallenia pusilla | H. pusilla | Oridorsalis umbonatus | O. umbonatus | Pleurostomella paleocenica | P. paleocenica | Osangularia mexicana | O. mexicana | Nuttallides truempyi | N. truempyi | Nonion havanense | N. havanense | Anomalinoides alazanensis | A. alazanensis | Discorbis sp. | Stilostomella gracillima | S. gracillima | Bulimina semicostata | B. semicostata | Turrilina brevispira | T. brevispira | Angulogerina muralis | A. muralis | Aragonia aragonensis | A. aragonensis | Cibicidoides ungerianus | C. ungerianus | Seabrookia lagenoides | S. lagenoides | Rosalina sp. | Siphonina tenuicarinata | S. tenuicarinata | Coryphostoma sp. | Tappanina selmensis | T. selmensis | Dentalina sp. | Gyroidinoides naranjoensis | G. naranjoensis | &lt;2% + indet. | Foraminifera, benthic indeterminata | Foram bent indet | Foraminifera, benthic | Foram bent | Number of species | Spec No | Shannon Diversity Index | H' | Dominance | Buliminacea | Foraminifera, benthic, endobenthic | Foraminifera, planktic | Foram plankt | deternded Eigenvalue = 0.08283 | Factor 1 | PC1 | Detrended Correspondence Analysis | deternded Eigenvalue = 0.05365 | Factor 2 | PC2 | Species | Counting 63-125 &#181;m fraction | Counting 125-180 &#181;m fraction | Counting 180-250 &#181;m fraction | Counting &gt;300 &#181;m fraction</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>2012-05-06T12:22:05</date></data>