<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.829379</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Potential impact of DOM accumulation on fCO2 and carbonate ion computations in ocean acidification experiments</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Potential impact of DOM accumulation on fCO2 and carbonate ion computations in ocean acidification experiments</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Culture and mesocosm experiments are often carried out under high initial nutrient concentrations, yielding high biomass concentrations that in turn often lead to a substantial build-up of DOM. In such experiments, DOM can reach concentrations much higher than typically observed in the open ocean. To the extent that DOM includes organic acids and bases, it will contribute to the alkalinity of the seawater contained in the experimental device. Our analysis suggests that whenever substantial amounts of DOM are produced during the experiment, standard computer programmes used to compute CO2 fugacity can underestimate true fCO2 significantly when the computation is based on AT and CT. Unless the effect of DOM-alkalinity can be accounted for, this might lead to significant errors in the interpretation of the system under consideration with respect to the experimentally applied CO2 perturbation. Errors in the inferred fCO2 can misguide the development of parameterisations used in simulations with global carbon cycle models in future CO2-scenarios. Over determination of the CO2-system in experimental ocean acidification studies is proposed to safeguard against possibly large errors in estimated fCO2.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>BIOACID</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Species | Day of experiment | DOE | fCO2(CT, pH) | Fugacity of carbon dioxide in seawater | fCO2w | fCO2(AT,CT) | fCO2(AT,pH), | carbonate ion(CT,pH) | Carbonate ion | [CO3]2- | carbonate ion(AT,CT) | carbonate ion(AT,pH) | (imposed) | Alkalinity, total | AT | Carbon dioxide | CO2 | (computed from imposed fCO2  and AT) | pH | fCO2(AT,pH) | fCO2(CT,pH) | computed from imposed fCO2 and AT with CO2SYS_DOC | Bicarbonate ion | [HCO3]- | Hydrogen ion concentration | H+ | computed from CT and AT unsing CO2SYS | Alkalinity, dissolved organic matter | DOM-AT | (TCO2 computed from fCO2 and alkalinity (AT) with CO2SYS_DOC) | (AT,CT) | (AT,pH) | pKDOC (imposed) | Carbon, organic, dissolved | DOC | DOM-alkalinity (imposed) | Alkalinity, potential of dissolved organic matter | DOM-AT pot | (TCO2 computed from imposed fCO2 and AT with CO2SYS_DOC) | (computed from imposed fCO2 and AT with CO2SYS_DOC) | (AT,CT) computed with CO2SYS | (AT,pH) computed with CO2SYS</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>2014-02-11T13:08:26</date></data>