<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.842937</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Temperature tolerance of western Baltic Sea Fucus vesiculosus - growth, photosynthesis and survival</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Temperature tolerance of western Baltic Sea Fucus vesiculosus &#8211; growth, photosynthesis and survival</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Fucus vesiculosus L. (Phaeophyceae) is the most abundant and hence ecologically most important primary producer, carbon sink and habitat provider in the western Baltic Sea. All F. vesiculosus L. specimens were collected on 23 April 2014 from a depth of 0.2-1 m in the non-tidal Kiel Fjord, western Baltic Sea (54&#176;27'N, 10&#176;12'E), where this species forms dense and almost monospecific stands on stones. After sampling the algal thalli were stored in a refrigerator box with water from the sampling site, transported to Bremerhaven and stored at 10 &#176;C for one day in filtered seawater. Experiments were conducted with vegetative apical tips (6.7&#177;0.5 cm length), the actively growing region of F. vesiculosus, which were randomly selected and cut from 144 different individuals prior to the experiments. These tips were acclimated to laboratory conditions for three days in filtered seawater at 10 &#176;C before the start of the experiment. Furthermore, 30 additional vegetative apices were freeze-dried to document the initial biochemical status of F. vesiculosus in its native habitat. A temperature gradient was installed in a walk-in constant cooling chamber (15 &#176;C) in nine water baths (5, 10, 15, 20, 24, 26, 27, 28 and 29 &#176;C &#177; 0.1 &#176;C) which were tempered by thermostats (5, 10 and 15 &#176;C: Huber Variostat CC + Pilot ONE, Peter Huber K&#228;ltemaschinen GmbH, Offenburg, Germany, 20 and 28 &#176;C: Haake DC3, Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc., Waltham, USA, 24, 26, 27 and 29 &#176;C: Haake DC10). Every temperature treatment consisted of four 2 L glass beakers (n = 4). In each beaker four F. vesiculosus apices were grown in 2 &#181;m-filtered North Sea water diluted with demineralized water in a ratio of 1:1 and enriched with nutrients after Provasoli (1968, 1/10 enrichment), leading to a salinity of about 15.6 which equaled habitat conditions. The algae were exposed to an irradiance of 130 &#181;mol photons m-2 s-1 &#177;10 % (Powerstar HGI-TS 150 W, OSRAM GmbH, Bad Homburg, Germany) measured at the top of the beaker under a 16:8 h L:D cycle. The media in the beakers was changed every third or fourth day and aerated with artificial air containing 380 ppm CO2 (gas mixing device, HTK Hamburg GmbH, Hamburg, Germany). Before the experiment, the algae were acclimated to the final temperatures in steps of 5 &#176;C for 2 days each, beginning at 10 &#176;C. After 21 days exposure time, three out of four samples per replicate were freeze-dried for further biochemical analyses, and afterwards the thermostats were turned off to reduce the temperature to 16&#177;0.4 &#176;C for another 10 days permitting growth under post-culture conditions.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>BIOACID</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Experiment day | Exp day | Temperature, water | Temp | Sample code/label | Sample label | Wet mass | Wet m | Area | Length | l | Period | Biomass | Growth rate | &#181; | Biomass, wet mass | Biom wm | Number | No | &#181;mol photons/m**2/s | Radiation, photosynthetically active | PAR | Fluorescence, yield at any given time | Ft | Electron transport rate | ETR | Yield | Photochemical quenching | qP | Non photochemical quenching | NPQ | Fluorescence, maximum, without dark adaptation | Fm' | Fluorescence, minimum, without dark adaptation | Fo' | PAR*Yield | Electron transport rate, relative | rETR | calculated after Walsby et al. (1997) | Fluorescence, minimum | Fo | Maximum photochemical quantum yield of photosystem II | Fv/Fm | Fluorescence, maximum | Fm | Effective quantum yield | Y | Species | Nitrogen, total | TN | Carbon | C | Carbon/Nitrogen ratio | C/N | Mannitol | Electron transfer rate, light-limited | alpha | Photoinhibition | beta | Maximal electron transport rate, relative | rETR max | Light saturation | Ek</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>2015-02-19T13:36:42</date></data>