<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.837617</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Alkenone stable carbon isotopes, carbonate stable carbon and oxygen isotopes, planktic foraminifera boron isotopes and atmospheric CO2 calculations and box model results from Ras il-Pellegrin section, Malta</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>CO2 drawdown following the middle Miocene expansion of the Antarctic Ice Sheet</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>The development of a permanent, stable ice sheet in East Antarctica happened during the middle Miocene, about 14 million years (Myr) ago. The middle Miocene therefore represents one of the distinct phases of rapid change in the transition from the "greenhouse" of the early Eocene to the "icehouse" of the present day. Carbonate carbon isotope records of the period immediately following the main stage of ice sheet development reveal a major perturbation in the carbon system, represented by the positive d13C excursion known as carbon maximum 6 ("M6"), which has traditionally been interpreted as reflecting increased burial of organic matter and atmospheric pCO2 drawdown. More recently, it has been suggested that the d13C excursion records a negative feedback resulting from the reduction of silicate weathering and an increase in atmospheric pCO2. Here we present high-resolution multi-proxy (alkenone carbon and foraminiferal boron isotope) records of atmospheric carbon dioxide and sea surface temperature across CM6. Similar to previously published records spanning this interval, our records document a world of generally low (~300 ppm) atmospheric pCO2 at a time generally accepted to be much warmer than today. Crucially, they also reveal a pCO2 decrease with associated cooling, which demonstrates that the carbon burial hypothesis for CM6 is feasible and could have acted as a positive feedback on global cooling.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>Ras_il-Pellegrin</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Alkenone, unsaturation index UK'37 | UK'37 | Sea surface temperature, annual mean | SST (1-12) | Calculated from UK'37 (M&#252;ller et al, 1998) | Comment | Globigerinoides trilobus, magnesium/calcium ratio | G. trilobus Mg/Ca | Calculated from Mg/Ca ratios | fine fraction &lt;63 &#181;m | &#948;13C, carbonate | &#948;13C carb | Alkenone C37:2, &#948;13C | C37:2 &#948;13C | carbonate | between calcite and aqueous CO2 in seawater | Isotopic fractionation | epsilon | between aqueous and gaseous CO2 in seawater | Henry's law constant | kH | &#948;13C, organic carbon | &#948;13C Corg | &#948;13C, carbon dioxide, gaseous | &#948;13C CO2(g) | &#948;13C, carbon dioxide, aquatic | &#948;13C CO2 aq | Isotopic fractionation, during photosynthis | epsilon p | Uncertainty | Carbon dioxide | CO2 | Carbon dioxide, partial pressure | pCO2 | pCO2, 2 sigma based on monte carlo modelling | Globigerinoides trilobus | &#948;11B | Boron/Calcium ratio | B/Ca | Carbon dioxide, partial pressure, standard deviation | pCO2 std dev | &#948;13C, bulk carbonate | &#948;13C bulk carb | Mass spectrometer Finnigan MAT 252 | &#948;18O, bulk carbonate | &#948;18O bulk carb | fine  fraction &lt;63 &#181;m | Mass spectrometer VG Optima | clock = model time in Ka | - | M0_t = amount of carbon in the ocean and atmosphere [mol] | Fw_sil = flux of carbon from silicate weathering of continental rocks [mol/kyr] | CO2_t | Fb_org = flux of carbon from burial of organic matter [mol/kyr]</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>2013-10-29T15:00:57</date></data>