<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.805730</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Geochemistry of the lower sheeted dike complex of ODP Holes 137-504B and 140-504B</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Geochemistry of the lower sheeted dike complex, Hole 504B, Leg 140</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Sixty-three samples representing 379 m of sheeted dikes from Deep Sea Drilling Project/Ocean Drilling Program Site 504B have been analyzed for major and selected trace elements by X-ray fluorescence. The samples range from microcrystalline aphyric basalts to moderately phyric (2%-10% phenocrysts) diabase that are typically multiply saturated with plagioclase, olivine, and clinopyroxene, in order of relative abundance. All analyzed samples are classified as Group D compositions with moderate to slightly elevated compatible elements (Mg&#198;-value = 0.65% &#177; 0.03%, Al2O3 = 15.5% &#177; 0.8%, CaO = 13.0% &#177; 0.3%, Ni = 114 &#177; 29 ppm), and unusually depleted levels of moderate to highly incompatible elements (Nb &lt; 1 ppm, Zr = 44 &#177; 7 ppm, Rb &lt; 0.5 ppm, Ba ~ 1 ppm, P2O5 = 0.07% &#177; 0.02%). These compositions are consistent with a multistage melting of a normal ocean ridge basaltic mantle source followed by extensive fractionation of olivine, plagioclase, and clinopyroxene.Leg 140 aphyric to sparsely phyric (0%-2% phenocrysts) basalts and diabases are compositionally indistinguishable from similarly phyric samples at higher levels in the hole. An examination of the entire crustal section, from the overlying volcanics through the sheeted dikes observed in Leg 140, reveals no significant trends indicating the enrichment or depletion of Costa Rica Rift Zone source magmas over time. Similarly, significant trends toward increased or decreased differentiation cannot be identified, although compositional patterns reflecting variable amounts of phenocryst addition are apparent at various depths. Below ? 1700 mbsf to the bottom of the Leg 140 section, there is a broadly systematic pattern of Zn depletion with depth, the result of high-temperature hydrothermal leaching. This zone of depletion is thought to be a significant source of Zn for the hydrothermal fluids depositing metal sulfides at ridge-crest hydrothermal vents and the sulfide-mineralization zone, located in the transition between pillow lavas and sheeted dikes.Localized zones of intense alteration (60%-95% recrystallization) are present on a centimeter to meter scale in many lithologic units. Within these zones, normally immobile elements Ti, Zr, Y, and rare-earth elements are strongly depleted compared with "fresher" samples centimeters away. The extent of compositional variability of these elements tends to obscure primary igneous trends if the highly altered samples are not identified or removed. At levels up to 40% (or possibly 60%) recrystallization, Ti, Zr, and Y retain their primary signatures. Although the mechanisms are unclear, it is possible that these intense alteration zones are a source of Y and rare-earth elements for the typically rare-earth-element-enriched hydrothermal vent fluids of mid-ocean ridges.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>ODP</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Sample code/label | Sample label | ODP sample designation | Piece | Lithologic unit/sequence | Unit | Rock type | Rock | Alteration | Silicon dioxide | SiO2 | X-ray fluorescence (XRF) | Titanium dioxide | TiO2 | Aluminium oxide | Al2O3 | Iron oxide, Fe2O3 | Fe2O3 | Manganese oxide | MnO | Magnesium oxide | MgO | Calcium oxide | CaO | Sodium oxide | Na2O | Phosphorus oxide | P2O5 | anhydrous | Elements, total | total | Loss on ignition | LOI | Chlorine | Cl | Sulfur, total | S | Niobium | Nb | Zirconium | Zr | Yttrium | Y | Strontium | Sr | Rubidium | Rb | Gallium | Ga | Zinc | Zn | Copper | Cu | Nickel | Ni | Chromium | Cr | Vanadium | V | MgO/(MgO + FeO), molar | Magnesium number | Mg# | Calculated | Calcium oxide/Sodium oxide | CaO/Na2O | Zirconium/Yttrium ratio | Zr/Y | Titanium/Zirconium ratio | Ti/Zr | precision (2 sigma) = 0.25 | Barium | Ba | precision (2 sigma) = 0.03 | Lanthanum | La | precision (2 sigma) = 0.1 | Cerium | Ce | precision (2 sigma) = 0.01 | Praseodymium | Pr | precision (2 sigma) = 0.09 | Neodymium | Nd | precision (2 sigma) = 0.06 | Samarium | Sm | precision (2 sigma) = 0.04 | Europium | Eu | precision (2 sigma) = 0.05 | Gadolinium | Gd | precision (2 sigma) = 0.02 | Terbium | Tb | precision (2 sigma) = 0.07 | Dysprosium | Dy | Holmium | Ho | precision (2 sigma) = 0.12 | Erbium | Er | Thulium | Tm | precision (2 sigma) = 0.08 | Ytterbium | Yb | Lutetium | Lu</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>1995-01-22T13:03:38</date></data>