<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.831204</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Spatially explicit estimates of length and biomass of Micromesistius poutassou (Blue Whiting) and Clupea harengus (Norwegian spring spawning herring) from acoustic and trawl surveys in the North-East Atlantic (2004-2012)</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Spatially explicit estimates of stock sizes, structure and biomass of herring and blue whiting, and catch data of bluefin tuna</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Acoustic estimates of herring and blue whiting abundance were obtained during the surveys using the Simrad ER60 scientific echosounder. The allocation of NASC-values to herring, blue whiting and other acoustic targets were based on the composition of the trawl catches and the appearance of echo recordings. To estimate the abundance, the allocated NASC -values were averaged for ICES-squares (0.5&#176; latitude by 1&#176; longitude). For each statistical square, the unit area density of fish (rA) in number per square nautical mile (N*nm-2) was calculated using standard equations (Foote et al., 1987, Toresen et al., 1998). To estimate the total abundance of fish, the unit area abundance for each statistical square was multiplied by the number of square nautical miles in each statistical square and then summed for all the statistical squares within defined subareas and over the total area. Biomass estimation was calculated by multiplying abundance in numbers by the average weight of the fish in each statistical square then summing all squares within defined subareas and over the total area. The Norwegian BEAM soft-ware (Totland and God&#248; 2001) was used to make estimates of total biomass.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>EURO-BASIN</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>unique identifier of the grid | Code | of the grid | Area extent | Area | Clupea harengus abundance as Nautical Area Scattering Coefficient | C. harengus NASC | after MacLennan et al. (2002) | Clupea harengus, biomass | C. harengus biom | Calculated from nautical area scattering coefficient | mean | Clupea harengus, length | C. harengus l | Micromesistius poutassou abundance as Nautical Area Scattering Coefficient | M. poutassou NASC | Micromesistius poutassou, biomass | M. poutassou biom</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title>Download a text version of Blue Whiting and Herring child datasets</md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title><date>2014-03-27T17:26:04</date></data>