<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.856696</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Physical oceanography and ADCP measurements during Maria S. Merian cruise MSM13/2</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title /><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Up to the end of the eighties the main source of deep water masses in the Ionian Basin was the southern Adriatic Sea. However, during the nineties a dramatic climatic change took place in the eastern Mediterranean Sea: the Eastern Mediterranean Transient (EMT). Since then, deep water has been formed by waters originating in the Aegean Sea. Expeditions carried out in this region in recent years indicate that the process of deep water formation might reverse again. To what extent this assumption applies and what characteristics the deep water in the Ionian Sea exhibit nowadays, should be determined on the cruise. The process of a re-reversal of abyssal water production in the Ionian Sea is a long-term process and must therfore be monitored for several years. Hence, this cruise is part of a series of cruises investigating this question (POS98, M71/3, MSM13/1-2, MSM15/4). The investigations were carried out by means of CTD/lADCP measurements.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Uniform resource locator/link to raw data file | URL raw | Pressure, water | Press | CTD | Temperature, water | Temp | Salinity | Sal | Oxygen | O2</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title>Dynamic processes in the deep Eastern Mediterranean: deep water formation and energy sources for chemosynthetic ecosystems - Cruise No. MSM13/1-2 - September 28-October 22, 2009 - Rostock (Germany)-Limassol (Cyprus)</md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title><date>2016-01-07T14:03:34</date></data>