<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.869799</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Moored measurements of current, temperature and salinity in the southern Weddell Sea, January 2009-January 2010</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title /><md:MetaData/md:abstract>This data set includes measurements from moored instruments, collected at the southern Weddell Sea continental slope, in the period between 10 January 2009 and 10 January 2010. The data set was collected as a part of the International Polar Year project entitled &#8220;Bipolar Atlantic Thermohaline Circulation (BIAC)&#8221;, under the working theme &#8220;Downslope processes, pathways, cascading and mixing&#8221;. The objective was to study the dynamics and mixing of the dense overflow plume on the continental slope of the Weddell Sea northwest of Filchner Depression. Due to difficult ice conditions, the Filchner outflow site could not be accessed. Moorings were instead deployed on the southeastern Weddell Sea, on the central Crary Fan and further to the east. The positions were chosen to capture the variability associated with the slope current in the region, basin-shelf exchange as well as the tidal band variability.The data set includes time series of ocean temperature, salinity and currents on the continental slope of the southeastern Weddell Sea at five locations in the region 74-75&#176;S, 29-33&#176;W. The observations from these moorings were reported in Jensen et al. [2013] who discuss the subinertial mesoscale variability attributed to trapped vorticity waves. Complete set of mooring drawings and detailed description can be found in the report (Fer, 2016) under 'Further details'.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Gear identification number | Gear ID | Pressure, water | Press | Temperature, water | Temp | Salinity | Sal | Current velocity, east-west | UC | Current velocity, north-south | VC</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title>Low frequency variability on the continental slope of the southern Weddell Sea</md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title><date>2016-12-22T14:48:38</date></data>