<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.743320</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Sea surface temperature reconstruction based on dinoflagellates from the North Atlantic</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Pliocene paleoclimatic reconstruction using dinoflagellate cysrs: comparison of methods</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>The application of quantitative and semiquantitative methods to assemblage data from dinoflagellate cysts shows potential for interpreting past environments, both in terms of paleotemperature estimates and in recognizing water masses and circulation patterns.Estimates of winter sea-surface temperature (WSST) were produced by using the Impagidinium Index (II) method, and by applying a winter-temperature transfer function (TFw). Estimates of summer sea-surface temperature (SSST) were produced by using a summer-temperature transfer function (TFs), two methods based on a temperature-distribution chart (ACT and ACTpo), and a method based on the ratio of gonyaulacoid:protoperidinioid specimens (G:P).WSST estimates from the II and TFw methods are in close agreement except where Impagidinium species are sparse. SSST estimates from TFs are more variable. The value of the G:P ratio for the Pliocene data in this paper is limited by the apparent sparsity of protoperidinioids, which results in monotonous SSST estimates of 14-26&#176;C. The ACT methods show two biases for the Pliocene data set: taxonomic substitution may force 'matches' yielding incorrect temperature estimates, and the method is highly sensitive to the end-points of species distributions.Dinocyst assemblage data were applied to reconstruct Pliocene sea-surface temperatures between 3.5-2.5 Ma from DSDP Hole 552A, and ODP Holes 646B and 642B, which are presently located beneath cold and cool-temperate waters north of 56&#176;N.Our initial results suggest that at 3.0 Ma, WSSTs were a few degrees C warmer than the present and that there was a somewhat reduced north-south temperature gradient. For all three sites, it is likely that SSSTs were also warmer, but by an unknown, perhaps large, amount. Past oceanic circulation in the North Atlantic was probably different from the present.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>DSDP</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>104-642B</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment>25 cores, 221.1 m cored, 0 m drilled, 97.1 % recovery</md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Sample code/label | Sample label | ODP sample designation | Dinoflagellates, total | Dinofl total | Operculodinium centrocarpum | O. centrocarpum | Operculodinium longispinigerum | O. longispinigerum | Operculodinium israelianum | O. israelianum | Nematosphaeropsis labyrinthus | N. labyrinthus | Spiniferites elongatus | S. elongatus | Spiniferites mirabilis | S. mirabilis | Spiniferites spp. | Impagidinium aculeatum | I. aculeatum | genus questionable | Impagidinium pallidum | I. pallidum | Impagidinium paradoxum | I. paradoxum | Impagidinium patulum | I. patulum | Impagidinium japonicum | I. japonicum | Impagidinium velorum | I. velorum | Tectatodinium pellitum | T. pellitum | Filisphaera filifera | F. filifera | Invertocysta lacrymosa | I. lacrymosa | Lingulodinium machaerophorum | L. machaerophorum | Polyspaeridium zoharyi | P. zoharyi | Batiacasphaera sphaerica | B. sphaerica | Corrudinium spp. | including Brigantedinium simplex | Brigantedinium spp. | miscellaneous peridiniacean forms including Selenopemphix nephroides and Lejeunecysta spp. | Dinoflagellate cyst indeterminata | Dinofl cyst indet | any other forms | Impagidinium sphaericum | I. sphaericum | Impagidinium strialatum | I. strialatum | Fibrocysta fusiforma | F. fusiforma | Amiculosphaera umbracula | A. umbracula | Melitasphaeridium choanophorum | M. choanophorum | Reticulatosphaera actinocoronata | R. actinocoronata | Bitectatodinium tepikiense | B. tepikiense | Multispinula minuta | M. minuta | Impagidinium index | Sea surface temperature, winter min | SST win min | Sea surface temperature, winter max | SST win max | Transfer function, standard error 2.4&#176; | Sea surface temperature, winter | SST win | Transfer function, standard error 2.6&#172;&#176; | Sea surface temperature, summer | SST sum | ACT = aczualistic based on relative abundances | Sea surface temperature, summer min | SST sum min | Sea surface temperature, summer max | SST sum max | questionable values, ACT = aczualistic based on relative abundances | ACTpo = actualistic based on presenves only without regard to abundances | G:P = gonyaulacoid : ptotoperidinioid ratio | Communality | Commun</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>1991-07-22T15:48:13</date></data>