<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.838979</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Vertical profiles of environmental parameters measured on discrete water samples collected with Niskin bottles at station TARA_021 during the Tara Oceans expedition 2009-2013</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title /><md:MetaData/md:abstract>The Tara Oceans Expedition (2009-2013) was a global survey of ocean ecosystems aboard the Sailing Vessel Tara. It carried out extensive measurements of evironmental conditions and collected plankton (viruses, bacteria, protists and metazoans) for later analysis using modern sequencing and state-of-the-art imaging technologies. Tara Oceans Data are particularly suited to study the genetic, morphological and functional diversity of plankton. The present data set includes properties of seawater, particulate matter and dissolved matter that were measured from discrete water samples collected with Niskin bottles during the 2009-2013 Tara Oceans expedition. Properties include pigment concentrations from HPLC analysis (10 depths per vertical profile, 25 pigments per depth), the carbonate system (Surface and 400m, pH (total scale), CO2, pCO2, fCO2, HCO3, CO3, Total alkalinity, Total carbon, OmegaAragonite, OmegaCalcite, and dosage Flags), nutrients (10 depths per vertical profile, NO2, PO4, N02/NO3, SI, quality Flags), DOC, CDOM, and dissolved oxygen isotopes. The Service National d'Analyse des Param&#232;tres Oc&#233;aniques du CO2, at the Universit&#233; Pierre et Marie Curie, determined CT and AT potentiometrically. More than 200 vertical profiles of these properties were made across the world ocean. DOC, CDOM and dissolved oxygen isotopes are available only for the Arctic Ocean and Arctic Seas (2013).</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>FondTara</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>TARA_20091115T1131Z_021_EVENT_CAST</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment>Device: equipped with [SENSORS] SEABIRD components, WETLabs optical sensors, HYDROPTIC Underwater Vision Profiler (UVP), SATLANTIC In Situ Ultraviolet Spectrophotometer nitrate sensor (ISUS) and [NISKIN] 10 Niskin bottles (6 x 8-L and 4 x 12-L) equipped with silicon and Teflon parts] [Engineer: 3x Salinity Samples]</md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent /><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title>Open science resources for the discovery and analysis of Tara Oceans data</md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title><date>2014-11-17T14:41:59</date></data>