<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.726281</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Heavy metal and petroleum product concentrations in waters at the Obskaya 1 drill site</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Ecological and geochemical investigations in the Ob estuary at sites of hydrocarbon exploration drilling</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>During recent years, the basins of the Kara Sea (Kamennomysskaya, Obskaya, and Chugor'yakhinskaya structures) in the Russian Federation have been considered as promising regions for oil and gas exploration and, simultaneously, as possible paths of relatively cheap pipeline and tanker transportation of hydrocarbons projected for recovery. On the other hand, exploration operations, recovery, and transportation of gas pose a considerable risk of accidents and environmental pollution, which causes a justified concern about the future state of the ecological system of the Gulf of Ob and the adjoining parts of the Kara Sea. Therefore, regular combined environmental investigations (monitoring) are the most important factor for estimating the current state and forecasting the dynamics of the development of estuary systems. The program of investigations (schedule, station network, and measured parameters) is standardized in accordance with the international practice of such work and accounts for the experience of monitoring studies of Russian and foreign researchers. Two measurement sessions were performed during ecological investigations in the region of exploration drilling: at the beginning at final stage of drilling operations and borehole testing, in addition, natural parameters were determined in various parts of the Ob estuary before the beginning of investigations. Hydrophysical and hydrochemical characteristics of the water medium were determined and bottom sediments and water were analyzed for various pollutants (petroleum products, heavy metals, and radionuclides). The forms of heavy-metal occurrence in river and sea waters were determined by the method of continuous multistep filtration, which is based on water component fractionation on membrane filters of various pore sizes. These investigations revealed environmental pollution by chemical substances during the initial stage of drilling operations, when remains of fuels, oils, and solutions could be spilled, and part of the chemical pollutants could enter the environment. Owing to horizontal and vertical turbulent diffusion, wave mixing, and the effect of the general direction of currents in the Ob estuary from south to north, areas are formed with elevated concentrations of the analyzed elements and compounds. However, the concentration levels of chemical pollutants are practically no higher than the maximum admissible concentrations, and their substantial dissipation to the average regional background contents can be expected in the near future. Our investigations allowed us to determine in detail the parameters of anthropogenic pollution in the regions affected by hydrocarbon exploration drilling in the Obskii and Kamennomysskii prospects in the Gulf of Ob and estimate their influence on the ecological state of the basin of the Ob River and the Kara Sea on the whole.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>ARCOD</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>Obskaya-1/0</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Sample type | Samp type | Cadmium | Cd | ICP-AES, Inductively coupled plasma - atomic emission spectroscopy | Cobalt | Co | Copper | Cu | Iron | Fe | Manganese 2+ | Mn2+ | Nickel | Ni | Lead | Pb | Titanium | Ti | Vanadium | V | Zinc | Zn | surface water | Oil products | OP | Fluorometric liquid analyzer Fluorat-2 | near-bottom water</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>2006-07-30T10:28:13</date></data>