<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.770724</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Age model, raw data and interpolated raw data from proxy records of sediment cores GeoB6007-1 and GeoB6007-2</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title /><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Here we present a 1200 yr long benthic foraminiferal Mg/Ca based temperature and oxygen isotope record from a ~900 m deep sediment core off northwest Africa to show that atmosphere-ocean interactions in the eastern subpolar gyre are transferred at central water depth into the eastern boundary of the subtropical gyre. Further we link the variability of the NAO (over the past 165 yrs) and solar irradiance (Late Holocene) and their control on subpolar mode water formation to the multidecadal variability observed at mid-depth in the eastern subtropical gyre. Our results show that eastern North Atlantic central waters cooled by up to ~0.8&#177; 0.7 &#176;C and densities decreased by Sigma theta=0.3&#177;0.2 during positive NAO years and during minima in solar irradiance during the Late Holocene. The presented records demonstrate the sensitivity of central water formation to enhanced atmospheric forcing and ice/freshwater fluxes into the eastern subpolar gyre and the importance of central water circulation for cross-gyre climate signal propagation during the Late Holocene.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>INTERDYNAMIK</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>GeoB6007-1</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Raw data | Age | Raw data, (T=Mg/Ca/0.49) | Bottom water temperature | BWT | Calculated from Mg/Ca ratios in Hyalinea balthica | Raw data, corrected for global ice volume changes | Hyalinea balthica, &#948;18O | H. balthica &#948;18O | Mass spectrometer Finnigan MAT 251 | Raw data, d18Osw | Calculated from Mg/Ca ratios and d18O corrected | Hyalinea balthica, &#948;13C | H. balthica &#948;13C | Globigerina bulloides, &#948;13C | G. bulloides &#948;13C | Interpolated raw data (BWT) | Age, 14C AMS, linear interpolation | Calculated from Mg/Ca ratios | Interpolated raw data (d18Osw) | Interpolated raw data, (d18Osw) | Interpolated raw data (d13C) | Raw data, d18Osw, corrected for global ice volume changes | IInterpolated raw data (BWT) | Lab ID | Sample code/label | Sample label | Species (planktic) | Material | +- 1 Sigma error | Age, dated | Age dated | Age, 14C AMS | Age, dated standard deviation | Age dated std dev | Calibrated Age WMA | Age, calibrated | 2 Sigma range | Age, minimum/young | Age min | Age, maximum/old | Age max | Reference/source | Reference</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title>Solar modulation of North Atlantic central water formation at multidecadal timescales during the late Holocene</md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title><date>2011-10-20T10:36:59</date></data>