<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.807315</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Short-term variations in radiolarian faunal dsitribution in the eastern equatorial Pacific</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Radiolarian response to oceanographic changes in the eastern Equatorial Pacific at 2.3 and 4.8 Ma: Relationship between changing carbonate deposition and surface oceanography</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Two short time intervals centered at 2.3 and 4.7 Ma were studied to investigate short-term variations in surface-ocean processes as indicated by changes in the radiolarian microfossil population. These time intervals represent two different settings of late Neogene climate. The older interval represents a time when tropical circulation between the Pacific and Atlantic oceans was not blocked by the Isthmus of Panama, whereas the younger interval represents a time when Northern Hemisphere glaciation was present but did not display the dominance of the 100,000-yr cycle that characterizes the late Pleistocene. The younger time slice at 2.3 Ma was sampled at all Leg 138 sites except Site 844, where significant reworking was evident. All sites except 844, 853, and 854 were sampled for the older time slice. Samples were taken at 10- to 20-cm intervals at each site and spanned a GRAPE density maximum and minimum. Thus, it was possible to investigate whether the changes in carbonate content (as indicated by GRAPE density) were associated with changes in surface-ocean conditions (indicated by radiolarian assemblage variations).For both time slices, the radiolarian data indicate that intervals of decreased carbonate content are periods of cooler water conditions and possibly enhanced biogenic production. Times of increased carbonate content are associated with inferred warmer oceanographic conditions, as indicated by the dominance of tropical assemblages at 2.3 Ma and tropical and western Pacific assemblages during the time slice centered at 4.8 Ma. However, the spatial patterns of change during each time slice show a distinct difference in the mapped patterns of radiolarian assemblage dominance. The older time slice, representing a period before the closing of the Isthmus of Panama, shows more zonal patterns presumably associated with a more zonal character of equatorial circulation. After the closing of the isthmus, the shifts in faunal patterns between times of high and low carbonates are characterized by shifts in the dominance of the tropical and transitional assemblages, respectively, throughout the region.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>ODP</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Sample code/label | Sample label | ODP sample designation | Depth, composite | Depth comp | Intercore correlation | Communality | Commun | Factor analysis | subtropical assemblage | Factor 1 | PC1 | transitional assemblage | Factor 2 | PC2 | Eastern Boundary Current assemblage | Factor 3 | PC3 | Max. = sample(s) used to map GRAPE maximum at each site, and Min. = sample(s) used to map GRAPE minimum at each site | Comment</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>1995-02-14T14:55:53</date></data>