<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.898245</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>XRF measurements on split-core surfaces and on individual core samples of IODP Expedition 313 holes</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title /><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Integrated Ocean Drilling Program Expedition 313 recovered siliciclastic sediments from three holes cored through a series of Miocene clinoforms offshore New Jersey. The clinoform sequence that lies between seismic reflectors m5.2 and m4.1 has been dated as mid-Miocene within an interval of major climatic change and displays interesting sedimentological and petrophysical features. However, the depth ties between surfaces in the recovered succession and seismic reflectors, correlation across sites, and depositional environments are not all well defined in this interval. Additionally, features observed in the two more proximal boreholes are absent from the most distal borehole.This report presents X-ray fluorescence (XRF) measurements from scanning the split surface of archive sediment cores and from individual core samples from Holes M0027A, M0028A, and M0029A. Major trends are identified and described, aided by statistical analyses (correlation coefficient matrix plots and principal component analyses). Si/Al and Zr/Rb ratios and, to a lesser extent, Th correspond with changes in the ratio of clay minerals to quartz. In the most proximal Hole M0027A, an alternating sequence of dark and light bands in an extended sequence of clays is characterized by distinctive high and variable magnetic susceptibility and equivalently variable Fe/S ratios. A similar sequence is observed in Hole M0028A, with both sequences located above the inferred m4.1 seismic sequence boundary. Redox elements in this interval are highly variable and suggest the influence of postdepositional processes. In Hole M0029A, despite an expanded sequence, similar characteristics are absent from the clay sequences, which are also geochemically more homogeneous. The analyzed geochemical compositions are compared with sedimentological observations and petrophysical analyses before discussing in their wider context.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>IODP</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-4.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Sample code/label | Sample label | Core length with CC | Liner Length | LL | Core length without CC | Core length | Core top depth CSF-A | Section Top in meters below surface | Top | Core bottom depth CSF-A | Section Bot in meters below surface | Bot | Recovered core with CC bottom depth CSF-A | Recovered core without CC bottom depth CSF-A | Overlap of overlying core with CC | Overlap of overlying core | Overlap | Cumulative depth shift with CC | Cumulative depth | Cum depth | Scale factor of drilled/recovered length with CC | Ratio | CC length | Unique section ID | Unique core ID | Core | Sample ID | Expanded depth CSF-append if long | Depth, expanded | Exp depth | 50kV | Barium, area, total counts | Ba count | X-ray fluorescence core scanner (XRF) II, Bremen, (AVAATECH) | 30kV | Bromine, area, total counts | Br count | Rubidium, area, total counts | Rb count | Strontium, area, total counts | Sr count | Zirconium, area, total counts | Zr count | Lead, area, total counts | Pb count | 10kV | Aluminium, area, total counts | Al count | Silicon, area, total counts | Si count | Phosphorus, area, total counts | P count | Sulfur, area, total counts | S count | Potassium, area, total counts | K count | Calcium, area, total counts | Ca count | Titanium, area, total counts | Ti count | Manganese, area, total counts | Mn count | Iron, area, total counts | Fe count | Total area, total counts | Total area | Silicon dioxide | SiO2 | X-ray fluorescence spectrometer, PANalytical Axios Advanced | Titanium dioxide | TiO2 | Aluminium oxide | Al2O3 | Iron oxide, Fe2O3 | Fe2O3 | Manganese oxide | MnO | Magnesium oxide | MgO | Calcium oxide | CaO | Sodium oxide | Na2O | Potassium oxide | K2O | Phosphorus oxide | P2O5 | * | Sulfur trioxide | SO3 | Loss on ignition | LOI | Total | Arsenic | As | Barium | Ba | Bromine | Br | Cerium | Ce | Chlorine | Cl | Cobalt | Co | Chromium | Cr | Caesium | Cs | Copper | Cu | Gallium | Ga | Mercury | Hg | Iodine | I | Lanthanum | La | Molybdenum | Mo | Niobium | Nb | Neodymium | Nd | Nickel | Ni | Lead | Pb | Rubidium | Rb | Antimony | Sb | Scandium | Sc | Selenium | Se | Tin | Sn | Strontium | Sr | Thorium | Th | Uranium | U | Vanadium | V | Tungsten | W | Yttrium | Y | Zinc | Zn | Zirconium | Zr</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title>Data report: Expedition 313 elemental data from X-ray fluorescence scanning and measurements on core samples</md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title><date>2019-02-11T12:36:52</date></data>