<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.875552</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Analysis of remotely-sensed and surface data of aerosols and meteorology for the Mexico Megalopolis Area between 2003-2015</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title /><md:MetaData/md:abstract>This datasets are part of an aerosol climatology study from 2003-2015 for the Mexico City Metropolitan Area (MCMA) using remotely sensed aerosol data, ground-based measurements, air mass trajectory modeling, aerosol chemical composition modeling, and reanalysis data for the broader Megalopolis of Central Mexico region. The most extensive biomass burning emissions occur between March and May concurrent with the highest aerosol optical depth, ultraviolet aerosol index, and surface particulate matter (PM) values. A notable enhancement in coarse PM levels is observed during vehicular rush hour periods on weekdays versus weekends owing to non-engine related emissions such as re-suspended dust. Among different species modeled using Goddard Ozone Chemistry Aerosol Radiation and Transport model (GOCART), sulfate accounted for most of the aerosol optical depth (highest in May-June), followed by organics. Among wet deposition species measured, PM2.5, PM10, and PMcoarse (PM10 &#8211; PM2.5) were best correlated with NH4+, SO42-, and Ca2+, suggesting that the latter three constituents are important components of the aerosol seeding rain drops that eventually deposit to the surface in the study region. Inter-annual trend analysis of measured parameters is presented with a key result being a statistically significant increase in wind speed and ambient temperature from 2003 to 2015 in the study region. Air quality improvements were observed for 2014-2015 owing to reduced regional biomass burning as compared to 2003-2013.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>daily avg | Aerosol optical thickness at 1020 nm | AOT_1020 | Aerosol optical thickness at 870 nm | AOT_870 | Aerosol optical thickness at 675 nm | AOT_675 | Aerosol optical thickness at 500 nm | AOT_500 | Aerosol optical thickness at 440 nm | AOT_440 | Aerosol optical thickness at 380 nm | AOT_380 | Aerosol optical thickness at 340 nm | AOT_340 | 935 nm daily avg | Column of water vapor | CWV | 440-870 nm, daily avg | Aerosol angstrom exponent | AAE | 380-500 nm, daily avg | 440-675 nm, daily avg | 500-870 nm, daily avg | 340-440 nm, daily avg | weighted avg | 935 nm weighted avg | 440-870 nm, weighted avg | 380-500 nm, weighted avg | 440-675 nm, weighted avg | 500-870 nm, weighted avg | 340-440 nm, weighted avg | Duration, number of days | Duration | Water(cm) | 440-870 Angstrom | 380-500 Angstrom | 440-675 Angstrom | 500-870 Angstrom | 340-440 Angstrom | Number of observations | NOBS | Month | MISR Level3 (MIL3MAE) | Aerosol optical thickness | AOT | MIL3MAE | Aerosol optical thickness, standard deviation | AOT std dev | MODIS_Terra_v6 (MOD08_M3v6) | MOD08_M3v6 | MODIS_Aqua_v6 (MYD08_M3v6) | MYD08_M3v6 | SeaWiFS Deep Blue (SWDB_L3M10) | SWDB_L3M10 | total | mean, MYD08_M3_6_Deep_Blue_Angstrom_Exponent_Land_Mean | MYD08_M3_6_Deep_Blue_Angstrom_Exponent_Land_Mean | Aerosol angstrom exponent, standard deviation | AAE std dev | Counts | min, MYD08_M3_6_Deep_Blue_Angstrom_Exponent_Land_Mean | max, MYD08_M3_6_Deep_Blue_Angstrom_Exponent_Land_Mean | mean | Aerosol index | AI | Level-3 OMI Total Ozone, Aerosol Index and Cloud Radiance Fraction- OMTO3d | Aerosol index, standard deviation | AI std dev | min | max | Black carbon | Goddard Ozone Chemistry Aerosol Radiation and Transport model | Organics | Dust | Dust, coarse | Dust, fine | Sulfate | Sea salt | mean_MOD13C2_5_CMG_0_05_Deg | Vegetation index, normalized difference | NDVI | derived from MODIS remote sensing data</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title>Contribution of Biomass Burning to Carbonaceous Aerosols in Mexico City during May 2013</md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title><date>2017-05-19T08:31:51</date></data>