<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.837756</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Geochemistry of Eocene/Oligocene sediments of ODP Site 177-1090</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Middle Eocene to early Oligocene paleoceanography from Agulhas Ridge, Southern Ocean (Ocean Drilling Program Leg 177, Site 1090)</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>The Agulhas Ridge, off the tip of Africa between the Atlantic and Indian Oceans, is ideally located to capture the evolution of Paleogene-early Neogene circulation patterns associated with global cooling. Multiproxy records of productivity (biogenic barium (Baex), opal, CaCO3 mass accumulation rates (MARs)), nutrient and organic carbon burial (reactive phosphorus (Pr) MARs), and redox state of deep waters (U enrichment) from Ocean Drilling Program (ODP) Site 1090 reflect hydrographic shifts in this region between the middle Eocene and early Oligocene (~9&#8211;33 Ma). Several peaks in increased export productivity and burial of organic matter occurred within the late Eocene (~36.5, ~34, and ~33.7 Ma), which along with surface hydrologic conditions favoring opaline organisms over calcareous organisms could have aided in the draw down of pCO2 to a threshold level that facilitated large ice sheet development on Antarctica in the earliest Oligocene. Our multiproxy approach illustrates the importance of vertical as well as spatial hydrographic reorganization in amplifying or driving climatic cooling of the middle Eocene to early Oligocene by facilitating increases in the relative or absolute burial of organic carbon.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>ODP</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>177-1090B</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment>43 cores, 397.5 m cored, 0 m drilled, 93.9 % recovery</md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent /><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title>Southern Ocean Middle Eocene to Early Oligocene paleoceanographic data</md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title><date>2005-11-03T08:35:42</date></data>