<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.710916</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Mineraly of oceanic crust from the Kane Transform, Mid-Atlantic Ridge</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Evidence for the protracted construction of slow-spread oceanic crust by small magmatic injections</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Gabbroic cumulates drilled south of the Kane Transform Fault on the slow-spread Mid-Atlantic Ridge preserve up to three discrete magnetization components. Here we use absolute age constraints derived from the paleomagnetic data to develop a model for the magmatic construction of this section of the lower oceanic crust. By comparing the paleomagnetic data with mineral compositions, and based on thermal models of local reheating, we infer that magmas that began crystallizing in the upper mantle intruded into the lower oceanic crust and formed meter-scale sills. Some of these magmas were crystal-laden and the subsequent expulsion of interstitial liquid from them produced '&#8221;cumulus&#8221; sills. These small-scale magmatic injections took place over at least 210 000 years and at distances of ~3 km from the ridge axis and may have formed much of the lower crust. This model explains many of the complexities described in this area and can be used to help understand the general formation of oceanic crust at slow-spread ridges.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>ODP</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>153-921E</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment>9 cores, 82.6 m cored, 0 m drilled, 21.4 % recovery</md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Sample code/label | Sample label | ODP sample designation | Lithology/composition/facies | Lithology | Grain size description | Grain size descr | Plagioclase | Pl | Anorthite | An | Plagioclase, root square deviation | - | Olivine | Ol | Magnesium number | Mg# | Olivine, root square deviation | Oxide size in mm, volumetric proportions are for discrete grains only | Comment | Alteration | Deformation structure, type | Deformation</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>2002-01-02T11:50:06</date></data>