<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.742919</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Physical and geotechnical properties of Norwegian Sea sediments</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>The influence of biogenic silica on the geotechnical stratigraphy of the V&#248;ring Plateau, Norwegian Sea</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Sediment composition and rate of deposition are the primary factors responsible for determining the spatial distribution of geotechnical properties on the Wring Plateau. Grain size and depth of burial have no significant influence. Vertical and lateral changes in geotechnical properties are associated with vertical and lateral composition changes in which biogenic silica is the most important variable. Anomalous trends of decreasing density and increasing porosity and water content with depth are associated with increasing silica content downsection. Void ratios, inferred in-situ permeability, and change in void ratio during consolidation testing are relatively high in siliceous sediments and tend to increase as the biogenic silica content increases. Portions of the section are overconsolidated, probably as a result of changes in sediment accumulation rates. However, the higher permeabilities of siliceous sediments may also be a factor influencing consolidation state.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>ODP</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>104-642B</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment>25 cores, 221.1 m cored, 0 m drilled, 97.1 % recovery</md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Sample code/label | Sample label | ODP sample designation | Sand | Silt | Size fraction &lt; 0.002 mm, &gt; 9 phi, clay | &lt;2 &#181;m, &gt;9 phi | Lithology/composition/facies | Lithology | Atterberg limit | Liquid limit | Liq limit | Plastic limit | Plastic index | Density, dry bulk | DBD | Specific gravity | Water in rock | H2O | Porosity | Poros | Shear strength, primary | Shear str | Compression index | Cc | Preconsolidation pressure | Pc | Overburden pressure | Overb press | Overconsolidation ratio | Pc/Po | observed | Liquidity index | LI | predicted | Opal, biogenic silica | bSiO2</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>1989-07-07T13:56:29</date></data>