<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.745201</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Composition of sedimentary rocks from the Burun-Tas Formation, Bol'shoi Lyakhov Island (New Siberian Islands)</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Mesozoic syncollision siliciclastic sediments of the Bol'shoi Lyakhov Island (New Siberian Islands)</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Graywackes and shales of the Bol'shoi Lyakhov Island originally attributed to Mesozoic were subsequently considered based on microfossils as Late Proterozoic in age. At present, these sediments in the greater part of the island are dated back to Permian based on palynological assemblages. In the examined area of the island, this siliciclastic complex is intensely deformed and tectonically juxtaposed with blocks of oceanic and island-arc rocks exhumed along the South Anyui suture. The complex is largely composed of turbidites with members displaying hummocky cross-stratification. Studied mineral and geochemical charac&#172;teristics of the rocks defined three provenances of clastic material: volcanic island arc, sedimentary cover and/or basement of an ancient platform, and exotic blocks of oceanic and island-arc rocks such as serpentinites and amphibolites. All rock associations represent elements of an orogenic structure that originated by collision of the New Siberian continental block with the Anyui-Svyatoi Nos island arc. Flyschoid sediments accumu&#172;lated in a foredeep in front of the latter structure in the course of collision. Late Jurassic volcanics belonging to the Anyui-Svyatoi Nos island arc determine the lower age limit of syncollision siliciclastic rocks. Presence of Late Jurassic zircons in sandstones of the flyschoid sequence in the Bol'shoi Lyakhov Island is confirmed by fission-track dating. The upper age limit is determined by Aptian-Albian postcollision granites and diorites intruding the siliciclastic complex. Consequently, the flyschoid sequence is within stratigraphic range from the terminal Late Jurassic to Neocomian. It appears that Permian age of sediments suggested earlier is based on redeposited organic remains. The same Late Jurassic-Neocomian age and lithology are characteristic of fossiliferous siliciclastic sequences of the Stolbovoi and Malyi Lyakhov islands, the New Siberian Archipelago, and of graywackes in the South Anyui area in the Chukchi Peninsula. All these sediments accumulated in a spacious foredeep that formed in the course the late Cimmerian orogeny along the southern margin of the Arctic conti&#172;nental block.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>ARCOD</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>B-TF135</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Sample code/label | Sample label | Quartz, monocrystalline | MonoQz | Quartz, polycrystalline | PolyQz | intergrows | Quartz and Feldspar | Qz+Fsp | Feldspar | Fsp | Plagioclase | Pl | Orthoclase | Or | of volcanic rocks | Lithic grains | Lithic | of sedimentary rocks | of metamorphic rocks | colored | Minerals | ore | Sum | Silicon dioxide | SiO2 | CAMECA electron microprobe | Titanium dioxide | TiO2 | Aluminium oxide | Al2O3 | Chromium(III) oxide | Cr2O3 | Iron oxide, FeO | FeO | Manganese oxide | MnO | Magnesium oxide | MgO | Calcium oxide | CaO | Sodium oxide | Na2O | Potassium oxide | K2O | step | Sample comment | Age, dated | Age dated | Age, dated standard deviation | Age dated std dev | Argon-40/Argon-39 | 40Ar/39Ar | Argon-40/Argon-39, standard deviation | 40Ar/39Ar std dev | Argon-38/Argon-39 | 38Ar/39Ar | Argon-38/Argon-39, standard deviation | 38Ar/39Ar std dev | Argon-37/Argon-39 | 37Ar/39Ar | Argon-37/Argon-39, standard deviation | 37Ar/39Ar std dev | Argon-36/Argon-39 | 36Ar/39Ar | Argon-36/Argon-39, standard deviation | 36Ar/39Ar std dev | Argon-39 | 39Ar | Sample type | Samp type | Wet chemistry | Iron oxide, Fe2O3 | Fe2O3 | Phosphorus oxide | P2O5 | Loss on ignition | LOI | Loss of ignition analysis | Scandium | Sc | ICP-MS, Inductively coupled plasma - mass spectrometry | Vanadium | V | Chromium | Cr | Cobalt | Co | Nickel | Ni | Rubidium | Rb | Strontium | Sr | Yttrium | Y | Zirconium | Zr | Niobium | Nb | Barium | Ba | Hafnium | Hf | Lead | Pb | Thorium | Th | Uranium | U | Lanthanum | La | Cerium | Ce | Praseodymium | Pr | Neodymium | Nd | Samarium | Sm | Europium | Eu | Gadolinium | Gd | Terbium | Tb | Dysprosium | Dy | Holmium | Ho | Erbium | Er | Thulium | Tm | Ytterbium | Yb | Lutetium | Lu</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>2006-09-13T20:19:32</date></data>