<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.830713</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Seawater carbonate chemistry, the abiotic conditions in the fluid surrounding the embryo, growth, calcification of the cuttlefish Sepia officinalis in a laboratory experiment</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Ocean acidification and temperature rise: effects on calcification during early development of the cuttlefish Sepia officinalis</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>This study investigated the effects of seawater pH (i.e., 8.10, 7.85 and 7.60) and temperature (16 and 19 &#176;C) on (a) the abiotic conditions in the fluid surrounding the embryo (viz. the perivitelline fluid), (b) growth, development and (c) cuttlebone calcification of embryonic and juvenile stages of the cephalopod Sepia officinalis. Egg swelling increased in response to acidification or warming, leading to an increase in egg surface while the interactive effects suggested a limited plasticity of the swelling modulation. Embryos experienced elevated pCO2 conditions in the perivitelline fluid (&gt;3-fold higher pCO2 than that of ambient seawater), rendering the medium under-saturated even under ambient conditions. The growth of both embryos and juveniles was unaffected by pH, whereas 45Ca incorporation in cuttlebone increased significantly with decreasing pH at both temperatures. This phenomenon of hypercalcification is limited to only a number of animals but does not guarantee functional performance and calls for better mechanistic understanding of calcification processes.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>OA-ICC</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent /><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title>seacarb: seawater carbonate chemistry with R. R package version 2.4</md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title><date>2012-03-19T05:36:09</date></data>