<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.865231</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Directional wave measurements using the Offshore Sensing Sailbuoy, link to MATLAB file</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Directional wave measurements using an autonomous vessel</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>An autonomous vessel, the Offshore Sensing Sailbuoy, was used for wave measurements near the Ekofisk oil platform complex in the North Sea (56.5 N, 3.2 E, operated by ConocoPhilllips) from 6 to 20 November 2015. Being 100% wind propelled, the Sailbuoy has two-way communication via the Iridium network and has the capability for missions of six months or more. It has previously been deployed in the Arctic, Norwegian Sea and the Gulf of Mexico, but this was the first real test for wave measurements. During the campaign it held position about 20km northeast of Ekofisk (on the lee side) during rough conditions. Mean wind speed measured at Ekofisk during the campaign was near 9.8m/s, with a maximum of 20.4m/s, with wind mostly from south and south west. A Datawell MOSE G1000 GPS based 2Hz wave sensor was mounted on the Sailbuoy. Mean significant wave height (Hs 1hr) measured was 3m, whereas maximum Hs was 6m. Mean wave period was 7.7s, while maximum wave height, Hmax, was 12.6m.  These measurements have been compared with non-directional Waverider observations at the Ekofisk complex. Mean Hs at Ekofisk was 3.1m, while maximum Hs was 6.5m. Nevertheless, the correlation between the two measurements was high (97%). Spectra comparison was also good, except for low Hs (~1m), where the motion of the vessel seemed to influence the measurements. Nevertheless, the Sailbuoy performed well during this campaign, and results suggests that it is a suitable platform for wave measurements in rather rough sea conditions.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>NorthSea_Ekofisk</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent /><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>2016-10-05T08:52:23</date></data>