<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.854343</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Dissolved nitrogen in soil solution of the Jena Experiment (Main Experiment, year 2003)</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title /><md:MetaData/md:abstract>This data set contains measurements of dissolved nitrogen (total dissolved nitrogen: TDN, dissolved organic nitrogen: DON, dissolved ammonium: NH4+, and dissolved nitrate: NO3-) in samples of soil water collected from the main experiment plots of a large grassland biodiversity experiment (the Jena Experiment, see further details below). In the main experiment, 82 grassland plots of 20 x 20 m were established from a pool of 60 species belonging to four functional groups (grasses, legumes, tall and small herbs). In May 2002, varying numbers of plant species from this species pool were sown into the plots to create a gradient of plant species richness (1, 2, 4, 8, 16 and 60 species) and functional richness (1, 2, 3, 4 functional groups). Plots were maintained by bi-annual weeding and mowing. In April 2002 glass suction plates with a diameter of 12 cm, 1 cm thickness and a pore size of 1&#8211;1.6 &#181;m (UMS GmbH, Munich, Germany) were installed in depths of 10, 20, 30 and 60 cm to collect soil solution. The sampling bottles were continuously evacuated to a negative pressure between 50 and 350 mbar, such that the suction pressure was about 50 mbar above the actual soil water tension. Thus, only the soil leachate was collected. Cumulative soil solution was sampled biweekly and analyzed for nitrate (NO3-) and ammonium (NH4+) concentrations with a continuous flow analyzer (CFA, Skalar, Breda, The Netherlands). Nitrate was analyzed photometrically after reduction to NO2- and reaction with sulfanilamide and naphthylethylenediamine-dihydrochloride to an azo-dye. Our NO3- concentrations contained an unknown contribution of NO2- that is expected to be small. Simultaneously to the NO3- analysis, NH4+ was determined photometrically as 5-aminosalicylate after a modified Berthelot reaction. The detection limits of NO3- and NH4+ were 0.02 and 0.03 mg N L-1, respectively. Total dissolved N in soil solution was analyzed by oxidation with K2S2O8 followed by reduction to NO2- as described above for NO3-. Dissolved organic N (DON) concentrations in soil solution were calculated as the difference between TDN and the sum of mineral N (NO3- + NH4+). In 5% of the samples, TDN was equal to or smaller than mineral N. In these cases, DON was assumed to be zero.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>JenExp</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>JenExp_2003</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent /><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title>Nitrogen and Phosphorus Budgets in Experimental Grasslands of Variable Diversity</md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title><date>2015-10-26T10:25:33</date></data>