<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.810131</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>qPCR counts of mRNA for hepatic reference gene selection in juvenile and adult female Atlantic salmon from perturbation experiments under artificial temperature conditions</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Hepatic reference gene selection in adult and juvenile female Atlantic salmon at normal and elevated temperatures</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>The use of quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction (qPCR) has become widespread due to its specificity, sensitivity and apparent ease of use. However, experimental error can be introduced at many stages during sample processing and analysis, and for this reason qPCR data are often normalised to an internal reference gene. The present study used three freely available algorithms (GeNorm, NormFinder and BestKeeper) to assess the stability of hepatically expressed candidate reference genes (Hprt1, Tbp, Ef1a and b-tubulin) in two experiments. In the first, female Atlantic salmon (Salmo salar) broodstock of different ages were reared at either 14 or 22&#176;C for an entire reproductive season, therefore a reference gene that does not respond to thermal challenge or reproductive condition was sought. In the second, estrogen treated juvenile salmon were maintained at the same temperatures for 14 days and a reference gene that does not respond to temperature or estrogen was required. Additionally, we performed independent statistic analysis to validate the outputs obtained from the program based analysis.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Temperature used as treatment | Treatment: temperature | Treat temp | State of the Life cycle | Life Cycle: state | LC:state | of mRNA [vernacular: mRNA abundance] expressing gene Tbp [GenBank: BT059217] in liver of Salmo salar [WoRMS ID: 127186, vernacular: Atantic salmon] | qPCR counts, mean | Cq | Fluorescence-based quantitative real-time PCR (qPCR) | qPCR counts, standard error of mean | Cq, SEM | of mRNA [vernacular: mRNA abundance] expressing gene Hprt1 [GenBank: BT043501] in liver of Salmo salar [WoRMS ID: 127186, vernacular: Atantic salmon] | of mRNA [vernacular: mRNA abundance] expressing gene Efla [GenBank: AF321836] in liver of Salmo salar [WoRMS ID: 127186, vernacular: Atantic salmon] | of mRNA [vernacular: mRNA abundance] expressing gene &#223;-tubulin [GenBank: DQ367888] in liver of Salmo salar [WoRMS ID: 127186, vernacular: Atantic salmon] | of mRNA [vernacular: mRNA abundance] expressing gene Vtg [GenBank: DQ834857] relative to mRNA expressing Tbp [GenBank: BT059217] in liver of Salmo salar [WoRMS ID: 127186, vernacular: Atantic salmon] | qPCR counts, ratio | Cq/Cq | qPCR counts, ratio, standard error of mean | Cq/Cq, SEM | of mRNA [vernacular: mRNA abundance] expressing gene Vtg [GenBank: DQ834857] relative to mRNA expressing &#223;-tubulin [GenBank: DQ367888] in liver of Salmo salar [WoRMS ID: 127186, vernacular: Atantic salmon] | Duration of the treatment | Treatment: duration | T:duration | Hormones used as treatment | Treatment: hormones | T:hormones</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>2013-04-11T10:25:50</date></data>