<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.753802</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Accumulation rates and composition of organic matter in sediments off Peru</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Accumulation rates and composition of organic matter in late Cenozoic sediments underlying the active upwelling area off Peru</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Deep-sea sediment samples from three Ocean Drilling Program (ODP) Leg 112 sites on the Peru continental margin were investigated, using a number of organic geochemical and organic petrographic techniques, for amounts and compositions of the organic matter preserved. Preliminary results include mass accumulation rates of organic carbon at Site 679 and characteristics of the organic facies for sediments from Sites 679, 681, and 684.Organic-carbon contents are high, with few exceptions. Particularly high values were determined in the Pliocene interval at Site 684 (4%-7.5%) and in the early Pliocene to Quaternary section of Hole 679D (2%-9%). Older sediments at this site have distinctively lower organic-carbon contents (0.2%-2.5%). Mass accumulation rates of organic matter at Site 679 are 0.02 to 0.07 g carbon/cm**2/k.y. for late Miocene to early Pliocene sediments and higher by a factor of 5 to 10 in the Quaternary sediments. The organic matter in all samples has a predominantly marine planktonic and bacterial origin, with minor terrigenous contribution. Organic particle sizes are strikingly small, so that only a minor portion is covered by visual maceral analysis.Molecular organic-geochemical data were obtained for nonaromatic hydrocarbons, aromatic hydrocarbons (including sulfur compounds), alcohols, ketones, esters, and carboxylic acids. Among the total extractable lipids, long-chain unsaturated ketones from Prymnesiophyte algae strongly predominate among the gas chromatography (GC) amenable components. Steroids are major constituents of the ketone and free- and bound-alcohol fractions. Perylene is the most abundant aromatic hydrocarbon, whereas in the nonaromatic hydrocarbon fractions, long-chain n-alkanes from higher land plants predominate, although the total terrigenous organic matter proportion in the sediments is small.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>ODP</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>112-679C</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment>8 cores, 75.5 m cored, 0 m drilled, 92.4 % recovery</md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Sample code/label | Sample label | ODP sample designation | Lithologic unit/sequence | Unit | Epoch | Calcium carbonate | CaCO3 | Carbon, organic, total | TOC | Hydrogen index, mass HC per unit mass total organic carbon | HI, HC/TOC | Carbon, total | TC | Kerogen concentrates | Carbon | C | Hydrogen | H | Hydrogen/Carbon ratio | H/C | Sample code/label 2 | Sample label 2 | Depth, top/min | Depth top | Depth, bottom/max | Depth bot | Sedimentation rate | Sed rate | Density, wet bulk | WBD | Porosity | Poros | Carbon, organic, total, minimum | TOC min | Carbon, organic, total, maximum | TOC max | range, minimum | Accumulation rate, total organic carbon | Acc rate TOC | range, maximum | mean | Vitrinite | Vitr | Inertinite | Alginite | Liptodetrinite | unstructured | Liptinite | Sporinite | Comment | Total extract from total organic carbon | Extract TOC | Nonaromatic hydrocarbon fraction | nonaro fraction | Aromatic hydrocarbon fraction | Arom HC | heterocompounds | Hydrocarbons | HC | Ketone | Alcohols | Alco | acid | Lipids | base | highly | Lipids, polar | Lipids pol</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>1990-11-17T16:00:03</date></data>