<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.896337</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Phytoplankton, Microzooplankton and Fatty Acid Composition in the KOSMOS Experiment Bergen 2015</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Ocean acidification impacts on biomass and fatty acid composition of a post-bloom marine plankton community</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Quantifying effects of Ocean Acidification (OA) on marine primary and secondary producers is of acute interest, as they could translate up to higher trophic levels and ultimately may alter ecosystem services including fishery yields. A mesocosm approach was used to investigate the effects of OA on a natural plankton community in coastal waters off Norway by manipulating CO2 partial pressure (pCO2). Eight enclosures were deployed in the Raunefjord near Bergen. Treatment levels were ambient and elevated pCO2 of ~ 2000 &#181;atm each in four replicate enclosures. The experiment lasted for 53 days in early summer of 2015. To assess impacts of OA on the plankton community, we measured phytoplankton and protozooplankton biomass and total seston fatty acid (FA) content. In both the control and the elevated pCO2 treatment, the plankton community was dominated by the dinoflagellate Ceratium longipes. In the elevated pCO2 treatment, however, this species as well as other dinoflagellates were strongly negatively impacted: At the end of the experiment, total dinoflagellate biomass was fourfold higher in the control group than under elevated pCO2 treatment. In a size comparison of C. longipes, individuals in the high pCO2 treatment were significantly larger. Fatty acid analysis revealed a decreased ratio of polyunsaturated fatty acids (PUFA) to saturated fatty acids (SFA) at elevated pCO2. Further, docosahexaenoic acid (DHA, C 22:6n3c), essential for development and reproduction of copepods and higher trophic levels, was lower in the high pCO2 treatment. Both in quality and quantity of their food, higher trophic levels thus experienced worse conditions in a community exposed to elevated pCO2, with potentially severe consequences for higher trophic levels.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>BIOACID</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Date/time start | Date/time end | Phase | Sample code/label | Sample label | Experimental treatment | Exp treat | pico | Phytoplankton, biomass | Phytopl | nano-i | synechococcus | cryptos | ehux | diatoms | dinophyta | ciliates | 14:0 | Fatty acids | 15:0 | 16:0 | 16:01 | 17:0 | 18:0 | 18:1n9c | 18:1n7 | 18:2n6c | 3-OH-14:0 | 18:3n3 | 18:4n3 | 20:5n3c | 22:1n9c | 22:6n3c | Day of experiment | DOE | Treatment | Treat | Fatty acids of water | FAME water | Totals</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>2018-11-29T10:38:45</date></data>