<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.884312</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Portable Monitoring Station measurements of trace gases relevant to air quality in Western Sydney, Australia from 23 May 2017 to 18 September 2017</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title /><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Location: Roof of 2-storey building at 2 Percy St, Auburn NSW 2144,Australia, -33.85469 151.0374 20.6 m rooftop above sea level, height rooftop above street level = 6.72 m, height air intake above rooftop=  3.3 m Operating dates: 28-October-2016 13:00 to 18-September-2017 13:00Original measurement time resolution: 1 minuteAveraging time: 1 hourThe portable air quality monitoring site was maintained in accordance with Climate and Atmospheric Science Standard of Operation Procedures which includes scheduled site visit and instruments calibration.Interruptions or issues: Replaced the faulty (cooler failure) SO2 instrument T100 S.No 1013 with T100 S.No 276 on 28/06/16 and performed multipoint calibration (MPC). Replaced pump diaphragm of T300 CO and performed MPC. Replaced T204 NOx and Ozone instrument S.No 51 with T204 S.No 71 on 02/08/2017 due to noisy trace of Ozone and performed MPC.Issues:  There was difficulty in determining the orientation of the 3D-sonic due to the surrounding infrastructure and nearby high tension electrical power lines. Final orientation was verified by comparison with wind direction data from the Australian Bureau of Meteorology,  Sydney Olympic Park AWS site (station number  066212,  GPS 33.8338,  151.0718). The average difference in measured wind direction to Olympic Park AWS was -27 23 (1 s.d., N=1036, Wind speed &gt; 1m/s), and 27 degrees has been added to the recorded wind directions</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>Auburn_PercySt</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-NC-SA-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent /><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>2017-12-20T11:19:26</date></data>