<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.807629</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Part of the global DOC versus AOU (dissolved organic carbon/apparent oxygen utilization) data compilation, Bransfield and Gerlache Straits</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Dissolved organic carbon distributions in the Bransfield and Gerlache Straits, Antarctica</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>During FRUELA'95 cruise, seawater samples were collected at the Bransfield and Gerlache Straits for the analysis of dissolved organic carbon (DOC) profiles throughout the water column. An excess of DOC probably derived from phytogenic material was observed in the upper mixed layer (UML, average: +22&#177;13 &#181;mol C/l), compared to the constant concentration of refractory DOC below 400 m (44&#177;4 &#181;mol C/l). The average excess DOC concentration was higher than the particulate organic carbon concentration indicating the major contribution of DOC to carbon export in this area. However, large spatial variability of DOC in the upper mixed layer (52-102 &#181;mol C/l) was observed: excess DOC contributed from 15% to 57% to the actual DOC concentration. Maximum average DOC concentrations in the UML were recorded in the Gerlache Strait (71 &#181;mol C/l) and in the Gerlache-Bransfield confluence (80 &#181;mol C/l), whereas minimum values were recorded in the Bransfield Strait (61 &#181;mol C/l).Several shelf and slope stations showed a slight increase of DOC (5-10 &#181;mol C/l) in the deep layer which might be related to organic matter release from the underlying sediments. Considering the net DOC release from phytoplankton, the low bacterial biomass and the reduced vertical DOC export, the DOC excess could build up in about 6 days for most of the sampling stations. The probable fate of the DOC excess is the eastwards horizontal transport by the Bransfield Current out of the study area.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>JGOFS</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Particulate organic carbon flux | POC flux | Dissolved organic carbon flux | DOC flux | Extracellular release | Extrac rel | Temperature, water | Temp | Oxygen, apparent utilization | AOU | Carbon, organic, dissolved | DOC | Bottle number | Bottle</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title>Dissolved organic carbon support of respiration in the dark ocean</md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title><date>2002-02-20T09:36:31</date></data>