<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.849508</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Biomass of mesozooplankton in the western part of the Black Sea in 1992 during the Cooperative Marine Science Program for the Black Sea (CoMSBlack)</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title /><md:MetaData/md:abstract>The &#8220;CoMSBlack92&#8221; dataset is based on samples collected in the summer of 1992 along the Bulgarian coast including coastal and open sea areas. The whole dataset is composed of 79 samples (28 stations) with data of zooplankton species composition, abundance and biomass. Sampling for zooplankton was performed from bottom up to the surface at standard depths depending on water column stratification and the thermocline depth. Zooplankton samples were collected with vertical closing Juday net,diameter - 36cm, mesh size 150 &#956;m. Tows were performed from surface down to bottom meters depths in discrete layers. Samples were preserved by a 4% formaldehyde sea water buffered solution. Sampling volume was estimated by multiplying the mouth area with the wire length. Sampling volume was estimated by multiplying the mouth area with the wire length.The collected material was analysed using the method of Domov (1959). Samples were brought to volume of 25-30 ml depending upon zooplankton density and mixed intensively until all organisms were distributed randomly in the sample volume. After that 5 ml of sample was taken and poured in the counting chamber which is a rectangle form  for taxomomic identification and count.  Large (&gt; 1 mm body length) and not abundant species were calculated in whole sample. Counting and measuring of organisms were made in the Dimov chamber under the stereomicroscope to the lowest taxon possible. Taxonomic identification was done at the Institute of Oceanology by Asen Konsulov using the relevant taxonomic literature (Mordukhay-Boltovskoy, F.D. (Ed.). 1968, 1969,1972 ). The biomass was estimated as wet weight by Petipa, 1959  (based on species specific wet weight). Wet weight values were transformed to dry weight using the equation DW=0.16*WW as suggested by Vinogradov &amp; Shushkina, 1987. Copepods and Cladoceras were identified and enumerated, the other mesozooplankters were identified and enumerated at higher taxonomic level (commonly named as mesozooplankton groups). Large (&gt; 1 mm body length) and not abundant species were calculated in whole sample. The biomass was estimated as wet weight by Petipa, 1959 ussing standard average weight of each species in mg/m**3.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>SESAME</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>15AK1992075-Zoo_1</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment>Juday closing net: Vertical tows of a Juday net, with mouth area 0.102 m**2, mesh size 150&#181;m. Tows were performed at 0-10, 0-20, 0-50, 10-25, 25-50, 50-100 m (depending on the thermocline or halocline position). Towing speed: 1m/s. Samples were preserved by a 4% formaldehyde sea water buffered solution. Sampling volume was estimated by multiplying the mouth area with the wire length. The net was checked after every tow for any damage. All nets opened properly.</md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent /><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>2015-09-16T13:43:22</date></data>