<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.775274</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Massic magnetic susceptibility and CaCO3 content at the P. ohmi and T. hugii zones from the Rio Argos X.Ag-1 section, southeastern Spain</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>An orbital floating time scale of the Hauterivian/Barremian GSSP from a mangetic susceptibility signal (Rio Argos, Spain)</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>An orbital floating time scale of the Hauterivian-Barremian transition (Early Cretaceous) is proposed using high-resolution magnetic susceptibility measurements. Orbital tuning was performed on the R&#237;o Argos section (southeast Spain), the candidate for a Global boundary Stratotype Section and Point (GSSP) for the Hauterivian-Barremian transition. Spectral analyses of MS variations, coupled with the frequency ratio method, allow the recognition of precession, obliquity and eccentricity frequency bands. Orbitally-tuned magnetic susceptibility provides minimum durations for ammonite biozones. The durations of well-constrained ammonite zones are assessed at 0.78 myr for Pseudothurmannia ohmi (Late Hauterivian) and 0.57 myr for Taveraidiscus hugii (Early Barremian). These results are consistent with previous estimates from the other reference section (Angles, southeast France) and tend to show that the R&#237;o Argos section displays a complete succession for this time interval. They differ significantly from those proposed in the Geologic Time Scale 2008 and may help to improve the next compilation. The Faraoni Oceanic Anoxic Event, a key Early Cretaceous oceanographic perturbation occurring at the P. ohmi/P. catulloi subzone boundary has a duration estimated at 0.10-0.15 myr, which is similar to previous assessments.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>Rio_Argos_X.Ag1</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent /><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>2012-02-02T16:05:00</date></data>