<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.809472</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Fossil plant remains in DSDP Leg 80 holes</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Fossil plants and other organic debris in Cretaceous sediments from Deep Sea Drilling Project Leg 80: Their paleoenvironmental significance and source potential</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>The lower part of the syn-rift Barremian-?Hauterivian section at Site 549 contains a large amount of acid-resistant land-derived organic matter that, as elsewhere in the Cretaceous sediments of the IPOD Leg 80 sites, is thermally immature. This plant debris was derived from a vegetation made up of many species of pteridophytes and gymnosperms. The palynofacies indicate that the sediments were deposited in shallow marginal and nonmarine environments and that the climate was probably warm temperate and fairly moist at the time. Source potential for gas is suggested at some horizons. Most of the younger Lower Cretaceous sediments at this and the other sites were deposited in more open marine conditions. Although they generally contain less organic matter, land plant remains continue to comprise a major part of the palynofacies. The Upper Cretaceous sediments were mainly deposited in well oxygenated conditions and are organically lean. However, stratigraphically restricted dark-colored shales at Sites 549 to 551 contain relatively large quantities of amorphous detritus of at least partly marine origin. These characteristics are suggestive of deposition during periods of restricted circulation and also of source potential for oil and gas if maturation levels had been higher.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>DSDP</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Sample ID | Sample code/label | Sample label | ODP sample designation | amount, VS = very small, S = small, M = moderate, VL = very large | Organic matter | OM | Miospores | cysts and acritarchs | Dinoflagellate abundance | Dinofl abund | and tasminitids | Leiospheres | Foraminifera, linings | Foram lin | Megaspores | others | Microfossil abundance | Mircofos abund | others, miscellaneous phytoclasts | Cuticles | Tissues | brown wood huminite and vitrinite | Vitrinite | Vitr | black wood huminite and inertinite | black wood, reworked vitrinite and inertinite only | Wood remains | Wood | finely disseminated particles | Biogenic particles | Biog | amorphous vascular plant material | Plant debris | Plant deb | of algal origin, marine/nonmarine | Organic matter, amorphous | AOM | G = good, M = fair, P = poor | Preservation | Preserv | Lithologic unit/sequence | Unit | Stage</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>1985-04-02T08:37:28</date></data>