<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.760173</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Late Neogene sediment composition and accumulation rates of ODP Hole 120-751A</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Sediment microfabric and physical properties record of late Neogene Polar Front migration, Site 751</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Through scanning electron microscope analysis of sediment microfabric, we have evaluated variations in high-resolution shipboard physical properties (index properties and shear strength), sediment components (smear slide determinations), and shore-based calcium carbonate and biogenic silica data from Site 751 (Kerguelen Plateau). The stratigraphic section at this site records a change in biogenic ooze composition from predominantly calcareous (nannofossil) to siliceous (diatom) ooze from ~23 Ma to the present, reflecting expansion of Antarctic water masses during the late Neogene. The profound change in physical properties and sediment character at 40.1 mbsf (~5-6 Ma) evidently records the northward movement of the Polar Front and a change in absolute accumulation rates of sediment at this site.Trends in geotechnical properties with depth at Site 751 allowed us to subdivide the sedimentary column into a number of geotechnical units that reflect changes in depositional and postdepositional processes with time. Geotechnical properties are sensitive to changing sedimentary inputs of primarily siliceous and calcareous microfossils. This allows us to study the physical nature of biostratigraphically-identified hiatuses and variations in environmental conditions linked to the migration of the Polar Front across this region. The analysis of geotechnical properties permits a more detailed division of the sedimentary column than is possible from shipboard lithologic descriptions alone.Our study of the sedimentary microfabric indicates that randomly oriented, elongate pennate diatom valves compose the sediments with highest porosity and water content values, and the lowest density values (wet bulk, dry bulk, and grain density). Conversely, sediments composed of nannofossils and disassociated nannofossil crystallites and little or no siliceous remains have the lowest porosity and water content values, and the highest density values. Samples of mixed siliceous/calcareous composition have intermediate physical property values, but these vary according to the nature of the sedimentary matrix and the state of preservation of individual skeletal elements.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>ODP</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>120-751A</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment>18 cores, 166.2 m cored, 0 m drilled, 98 % recovery</md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>subunit | Lithologic unit/sequence | Unit | Depth, top/min | Depth top | Depth, bottom/max | Depth bot | maximum | Water content, wet mass | Water wm | minimum | Porosity | Poros | Density, wet bulk | WBD | Density, dry bulk | DBD | Density, grain | Density grain | Carbonates | Carb | Sample code/label | Sample label | ODP sample designation | Epoch | Diatoms | Radiolarians | Rad | Nannofossils | Nannos | Silicoflagellates | Silicoflag | including foraminifera fragments | Foraminifera | Foram | Calcium carbonate | CaCO3 | Silicon dioxide | SiO2 | shore | ship | Sedimentation rate | Sed rate | Accumulation rate, sediment, mean | MAR | Accumulation rate, calcium carbonate | Acc rate CaCO3 | Accumulation rate, opal | Acc rate opal | Accumulation rate, non carbonate | Acc rate non CaCO3</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>1992-05-10T10:53:37</date></data>