<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.855333</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Analysis of Mn-deposits from Lake Eningi-Lampi</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Geochemical studies on the formation of iron-manganese nodules and crusts in recent basins, I. Eningi-Lampi Lake, Central Karelia</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>The processes of formation of iron-manganese nodules and crusts have been studied on an example of the Eningi-Lampi lake, Central Karelia, where the relationships between the source of the ore, sedimentary materials and areas of their accumulation prove relatively simple and apparent. Nodules and crusts are composed mostly by birnessite, amorphous hydrous ferric oxides and hydro-goethite. They occur, as a rule, on the surface of relatively coarse-grained sediments, at the ground-water interface. Considerably in a lesser extent are found the nodules in the upper part (0&#243;5 cm) of the red-brown flooded watery mud covering dark-green, black muds. The nucleus of nodules, or the basis of crusts of iron-manganese hydroxides are various, frequently altered, fragments of rocks, sometimes pieces of wood. Distribution of Mn and Fe in sediments and waters of the lake is considered. It is shown that the Mn/Fe ratio decreases considerably in waters, sediments and nodules of the lake while moving off a distance from the source. The main role in the process of formation of iron-manganese nodules belongs to the selective chemosorption interaction (with auto-catalytic oxidation) of component-bearing solutions with active surfaces.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>NOAA-MMS</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Identification | ID | Silicon | Si | Spectrophotometric | Aluminium | Al | Titanium | Ti | Iron | Fe | Calcium | Ca | Magnesium | Mg | Sodium | Na | Potassium | K | Phosphorus | P | Manganese | Mn | Carbon, organic, total | TOC | Carbon dioxide | CO2 | Barium | Ba | Cobalt | Co | Chromium | Cr | Copper | Cu | Nickel | Ni | Lead | Pb | Vanadium | V | Zinc | Zn | Description | Barium oxide | BaO</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title>The NOAA and MMS Marine Minerals Geochemical Database</md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title><date>1972-11-26T15:07:45</date></data>