<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.897147</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>RAFOS Float Trajectories from the MOVE Project in the Tropical Atlantic in 2000 and 2001</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title /><md:MetaData/md:abstract>In early 2000 and again in 2001, RAFOS floats were deployed in the western tropical Atlantic near latitude 16N. These floats drift at pre-determined depths for durations of typically one year or more, and they are geo-located by triangulation using sound signals from moored underwater sound sources. The float trajectories then show the currents of the water they drift in. The first batch of floats drifted in the layer of the Antarctic Intermediate Water near 800m depth, the second in the upper North Atlantic Deep Water near 1400m depth. Here, the trajectory data from the floats (position and lateral velocity) are presented, together with temperature and pressure records. Two versions of the data are included: one that leaves gaps in the trajectories untreated (see "Download data"), and another one that is smoothed with a low-pass filter and has gaps filled or removed (see "Other version"). The floats were part of the Meridional Overturning Variability Experiment (MOVE), a project to investigate the meridional overturning circulation of the Atlantic. MOVE was funded by the German agencies BMBF (awards 03F0246A and 03F0377B) as well as DFG (award SE815/21).</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>KN161-02_RAFOS-80</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment>ID ARGOS: 5493/55D61</md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-4.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent /><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title>The mid-depth circulation of the northwestern tropical Atlantic observed by floats</md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title><date>2019-01-08T14:56:54</date></data>