<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.774172</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Age determination and stable carbon isotope ratios of Cassidulina laevigata of sediment core Svanic90_9004</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Variations in organic carbon flux and stagnation periods during the last 2400 years in a Skagerrak fjord basin, inferred from benthic foraminiferal d13C</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>A well-dated high-resolution d13C record of the last 2400 a, based on the benthic foraminifera Cassidulina laevigata, is presented for Gullmar Fjord, Sweden. The time interval covers die Roman Warm Period (RWP), the Viking Age/Medieval Warm Period (VA/MWP), the little Ice Age (LIA) and the most recent warming. There is little variation in the d13C record until the early Viking Age (AD 800), when the d13C signal becomes significantly more negative and continues to decrease throughout the VA/MWP, The d13C signal increases both at the beginning and at the end of the LIA but is marked by more negative values during the larger part of the period. Since about 1970, the d13C values are more negative than the long-term average. This general negativity of the record may result from a higher flux of organic matter, possibly of terrestrial origin due to land-use changes together with moderate changes in stagnation periods since the VA/MWP. In most recent times, the oceanic Suess effect together with increased number of extended stagnation periods are probably the main causes of the shift towards more negative d13C values.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>Skagerrak01_GA113-2Aa</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Cassidulina laevigata, &#948;13C | C. laevigata &#948;13C | Isotope ratio mass spectrometry | # = outlier | Sample code/label | Sample label | Age, dated material | Dated material | Age, dated | Age dated | Age, 14C AMS | Age, dated standard deviation | Age dated std dev | Age, 14C calibrated | Age</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>2010-01-17T10:07:34</date></data>