<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.737473</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Seawater carbonate chemistry and biological processes during experiments with common cuttlefish Sepia officinalis, 2008</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Growth and calcification in the cephalopod Sepia officinalis under elevated seawater pCO2</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Ocean acidification and associated changes in seawater carbonate chemistry negatively influence calcification processes and depress metabolism in many calcifying marine invertebrates. We present data on the cephalopod mollusc Sepia officinalis, an invertebrate that is capable of not only maintaining calcification, but also growth rates and metabolism when exposed to elevated partial pressures of carbon dioxide (pCO2). During a 6 wk period, juvenile S. officinalis maintained calcification under ~4000 and ~6000 ppm CO2, and grew at the same rate with the same gross growth efficiency as did control animals. They gained approximately 4% body mass daily and increased the mass of their calcified cuttlebone by over 500%. We conclude that active cephalopods possess a certain level of pre-adaptation to long-term increments in carbon dioxide levels. Our general understanding of the mechanistic processes that limit calcification must improve before we can begin to predict what effects future ocean acidification will have on calcifying marine invertebrates.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>EPOCA</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Group | Identification | ID | Experimental treatment | Exp treat | Experiment day | Exp day | Salinity | Sal | Temperature, water | Temp | Temperature, standard deviation | T std dev | NBS scale | pH | WTW Oxi 340i probe | pH, standard deviation | pH std dev | Carbon, inorganic, dissolved | DIC | Gas chromatography | Carbon, inorganic, dissolved, standard deviation | DIC std dev | Partial pressure of carbon dioxide (water) at sea surface temperature (wet air) | pCO2water_SST_wet | Calculated using CO2SYS | Carbon dioxide, partial pressure, standard deviation | pCO2 std dev | Aragonite saturation state | Omega Arg | Carbonate system computation flag | CSC flag | Calculated using seacarb after Nisumaa et al. (2010) | Total scale | Carbon dioxide | CO2 | Fugacity of carbon dioxide (water) at sea surface temperature (wet air) | fCO2water_SST_wet | Bicarbonate ion | [HCO3]- | Carbonate ion | [CO3]2- | Alkalinity, total | AT | Calcite saturation state | Omega Cal | Animal | Initial | Sepia officinalis, mass, wet | S. officinalis wm | Measured | Sepia officinalis, length, mantle | S. officinalis l | Final | Time, incubation | T incubation | Sepia officinalis, cuttlebone, CaCO3, mass | S. officinalis cb CaCO3 | Metabolic rate of oxygen, standard | Met rate O2</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>2008-04-29T15:06:25</date></data>