<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.761025</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Geochemistry of basalts of the Indian Ocean</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>The geochemistry of oceanic crust at the onset of rifting in the Indian Ocean</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Indian Ocean crust formed at Sites 765 and 766 is geochemically comparable to that presently forming in the Red Sea. In both cases, we interpret the crust as reflecting high degrees of mantle melting that are associated with an enhanced thermal gradient below recently rifted continental lithosphere. Asthenospheric melts formed in this environment are rich in CaO and FeO, poor in Na2O and Al2O3, and characterized by depleted rare earth element (REE) profiles ([La/Sm]n approximately 0.5-0.6). Both the Red Sea basalts and the basalts at Sites 765 and 766 are distinct from those erupted at the present Mid-Indian Ocean Ridge.The isotope characteristics of the Site 765 basalts define a geochemical signature similar to that of the present-day Mid-Indian Ocean Ridge basalts (MIORB). The Indian Ocean mantle domain is distinct from that of the Atlantic and Pacific oceans, and this distinction has persisted since Jurassic time, when the Site 765 oceanic crust was formed.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>ODP</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>123-765C</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment>65 cores, 613.7 m cored, 0 m drilled, 60.8 % recovery</md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>Sample code/label | Sample label | ODP sample designation | Lanthanum | La | Instrumental neutron activation analysis (INAA) (Reimann et al., 1998) | Cerium | Ce | Neodymium | Nd | Samarium | Sm | Europium | Eu | Terbium | Tb | Holmium | Ho | Thulium | Tm | Ytterbium | Yb | Lutetium | Lu | Scandium | Sc | Hafnium | Hf | Tantalum | Ta | Thorium | Th | Uranium | U | Sample comment | Strontium 87/Strontium 86 | 87Sr/86Sr | Strontium 87/Strontium 86, error | 87Sr/86Sr e | Neodymium 143/Neodymium 144 | 143Nd/144Nd | Neodymium 143/Neodymium 144, error | 143Nd/144Nd e | Lead 206/Lead 204 ratio | 206Pb/204Pb | Lead 207/Lead 204 ratio | 207Pb/204Pb | Lead 208/Lead 204 ratio | 208Pb/204Pb</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>1992-05-23T16:51:09</date></data>