<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.854371</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Mineral nitrogen from KCl extractions of soil from the Jena Experiment (Main Experiment up to 15cm depth, year 2008)</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title /><md:MetaData/md:abstract>As an estimate of plant&#8208;available N, this data set contains measurements of inorganic nitrogen (NO3&#8208;N and NH4&#8208;N, the sum of which is termed mineral N or Nmin) determined by extraction with 1 M KCl solution of soil samples from the main experiment plots of a large grassland biodiversity experiment (the Jena Experiment, see further details below). In the main experiment, 82 grassland plots of 20 x 20 m were established from a pool of 60 species belonging to four functional groups (grasses, legumes, tall and small herbs). In May 2002, varying numbers of plant species from this species pool were sown into the plots to create a gradient of plant species richness (1, 2, 4, 8, 16 and 60 species) and functional richness (1, 2, 3, 4 functional groups). Plots were maintained by bi-annual weeding and mowing. Soil sampling and analysis: Five soil cores (diameter 0.01 m) were taken at a depth of 0 to 0.15 m of the mineral soil from each of the experimental plots in March and October 2008. In October 2008, also the plots of the management experiment, that altered mowing frequency and fertilized subplots (see further details below) were sampled. Samples of the soil cores per plot (subplots in case of the management experiment) were pooled during each sampling campaign. NO3&#8208;N and NH4&#8208;N concentrations were determined by extraction of soil samples with 1 M KCl solution and were measured in the soil extract with a Continuous Flow Analyzer (CFA, AutoAnalyzer, Seal, Burgess Hill, United Kingdom).</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>JenExp</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label>JenExp_2008</md:MetaData/md:event/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent /><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title>Plant diversity effects on aboveground and belowground N pools in temperate grassland ecosystems: Development in the first 5 years after establishment</md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title><date>2015-10-26T14:57:59</date></data>