<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.824829</id><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title>Variability of the Brazil Current during the late Holocene analysed on two marine sediment cores</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:title><md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title>Variability of the Brazil Current during the late Holocene</md:MetaData/md:citation/md:supplementTo/md:title><md:MetaData/md:abstract>Our understanding of the centennial-scale variability of the Brazil Current (BC) during the late Holocene is elusive because of the lack of appropriate records. Here we used the Mg/Ca and oxygen isotopic composition of planktonic foraminifera from two marine sediment cores collected at 27&#176; S and 33&#176; S off southeastern South America to assess the late Holocene variability in the upper water column of the BC. Our results show in phase fluctuations of up to 3 &#176;C in sea surface temperatures (SST), and 0.8 per mil in oxygen isotopic composition of surface sea water, a proxy for relative sea surface salinity (SSS). Time-series analyses of our records indicate a cyclicity with a period of ca. 730 yr. We suggest that the observed cyclicity reflects variability in the strength of the BC associated to changes in the Atlantic meridional overturning circulation (AMOC). Positive (negative) SST and SSS anomalies are related to a strong (weak) BC and a weak (strong) AMOC. Moreover, periods of peak strength in the BC occur synchronously to a weak North Brazil Current, negative SST anomalies in the high latitudes of the North Atlantic, and positive (negative) precipitation anomalies over southeastern South America (equatorial Africa), further corroborating our hypothesis. This study shows a tight coupling between the variability of the BC and the high latitudes of the North Atlantic mediated by the AMOC even under late Holocene boundary conditions.</md:MetaData/md:abstract><md:MetaData/md:project/md:label>MARUM</md:MetaData/md:project/md:label><md:MetaData/md:event/md:label /><md:MetaData/md:event/md:comment /><md:MetaData/md:license/md:label>CC-BY-3.0</md:MetaData/md:license/md:label><md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent>sensu stricto 250-350 microm (per mil, VPDB) | Globigerinoides ruber white, &#948;18O | G. ruber w &#948;18O | Mass spectrometer Finnigan MAT 251 | sp2 500-650 microm (per mil, VPDB) | Globorotalia truncatulinoides dextral, &#948;18O | G. truncatulinoides d &#948;18O | Depth, composite | Depth comp | Intercore correlation | sensu stricto 250-350 microm | Globigerinoides ruber white, Magnesium/Calcium ratio | G. ruber w Mg/Ca | Mg/Ca temperature Globigerinoides ruber white sensu stricto 250-350 microm based on Anand et al. (2003) | Sea surface temperature, annual mean | SST (1-12) | Calculated from Mg/Ca ratios (Anand et al., 2003) | d18O continental-ice-volume-corrected surface sea water based on Mulitza et al. (2003) (per mil, VSMOW) | &#948;18O, water | &#948;18O H2O | Ice volume corrected | 3 chambers in final whorl 315-400 microm (per mil, VPDB) | Globorotalia inflata, &#948;18O | G. inflata &#948;18O | d18O permanent thermocline from Globorotalia spp (per mil, VPDB) (from 1 until 45 cm composite core depth the data comes from Globorotalia truncatulinoides dextral sp2 500-650 microm from GeoB6211-1, and from 46 until 84 cm composite core depth the data comes from Globorotalia inflata 3 chambers in final whorl 315-400 microm from GeoB6211-2) | Globorotalia spp., &#948;18O | Globorotalia spp. &#948;18O | Refer to the depth of the composite core GeoB6211-1/2 | Sample code/label | Sample label | Species | Age, dated material | Dated material | BP | Age, dated | Age dated | Age, 14C AMS | +/- 1Sigma error (BP) | Age, dated standard deviation | Age dated std dev | 2Sigma calibrated age range (BP) | Age, minimum/young | Age min | Age, 14C calibrated, CALIB 6.0 (Stuiver et al., 2013) | Age, maximum/old | Age max | Calibrated age, interpolated from 2Sigma range | interpolated | Reference/source | Reference</md:MetaData/md:additionalSearchableContent><md:MetaData/md:reference/md:title /><date>2013-12-19T10:26:59</date></data>