<data><id>21afc06a-f097-47bd-b85e-ff2301436101</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Crustacea, diversity, Echinodermata, Porifera, symbiosis, Cnidaria, parasitism, reefs|Observation</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>&lt;p&gt;The data review presented in Korzhavina et al. (2019) formed the basis of this data set.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of June 27, 2019, dataset includes 1,363 records of 115 species of symbiotic copepods (47 genera, 17 families, 3 orders), inhabiting 80 species of invertebrates (58 genera, 39 families, 22 orders, 7 classes). Marine invertebrates with copepods reported in these review represent only 47% of scleractinians, 9% of octocorals, 3% of echinoderms and 1% of sponges from the entire diversity of potential hosts in the Caribbean.The dataset comprises information on host and symbiont taxonomy, references to unique records in the World of Copepods, the number of associates per host, the nature of the symbiosis, the names and coordinates of collection sites, the depths and dates of collections, as well as publication sources.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The dataset covers 154 locations in the Greater Caribbean, belonging to eight of the ten Caribbean ecoregions. All records are georeferenced. Please note that the precision of the coordinates depends on the detail of the geographic data marked in the articles, and the accuracy of the coordinates is indicated as a radius (uncertainty in meters) around the point.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The record date is noted in 992 occurrences.&lt;/p&gt;|An analysis of all published data on copepods inhabiting anthozoans, echinoderms and sponges of the Caribbean has made it possible to determine the least studied groups of hosts and ecoregions. This information is necessary to identify the direction of further research. In addition, this is the first dataset on copepods published on the Internet. These dataset providing open access to data for a wide range of people.|1,360 occurrences</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><date
>2019-10-15</date
></data>