<data><id>25d73670-8b5c-4813-aadb-37b65022602b</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject /><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Biopsy samples (small amounts of skin and blubber) were collected from humpback and blue whales during the Antarctic blue whale voyage 2013. For more information please see: http://www.marinemammals.gov.au/sorp/antarctic-blue-whale-projectThis dataset consists of an access database summarising biopsy events containing the fields:Pod: a combination of date and where the biopsy was taken from (small boat - Remora, or main vessel - Amaltal Explorer)Ship reference: sighting numberNumber of individuals sightedAge class and sexSatellite tag numberBiopsy sample numberBiopsy collection location (longitude and latitude)Biopsy collection time (UTC)Reaction to biopsyNumber of biopsy attemptsPhoto ID imagesBiopsy collection photoCommentsAn excel spreadsheet (Biopsy_info_ ABWV2013.xlsx) details the biopsy processing that occurred upon collection of a sample. Where possible, each blue whale sample was split and preserved in 2 x All Protect, 1 x EtOH and 1 x Nitrogen. Each humpback sample was additionally preserved in RNA later and stored at -20 degrees Celsius and individually detailed in spreadsheet Biopsy_info _ABWV2013(hbw).xlsx. Biopsy samples were processed to determine sex and relatedness using DLOOP analysis and the results are held in: 240513 BW Sexing Results.xlsPurposes: Genetic tagging from biopsy samples is a well established method that enables the identification of individuals from genetic markers such as microsatellite or SNPs. This individual identification allows the production of sightings histories required for a mark-recapture approach to estimating abundance. Genetic data can also be used assess population structureQuality: Australian Antarctic Data Centre Note 2018-07-04:Original datasheet was reformatted to fit GBIF/IPT Biodiversity.AQ standard. The new datasheet "blueWhales2013.csv" provides the dataset ID, organism Quantity, organism Quantity type, record number, material sample ID, preparation, water body, event day, verbatim latitude and longitude, decimal latitude and longitude, sex, occurrence, and basis of record. The taxonomical organisation is provided to the lowest taxonomical rank that could be determined, after matched in WoRMS (World Register of Marine Species). Data contains information from report.DATA LICENCEThis dataset has been collected under the International Whaling Commission&#8217;s (IWC) Southern Ocean Research Partnership (SORP). The IWC-SORP ethos is one of open collaboration, communication and data sharing. The Data User will acknowledge the use of the IWC SORP dataset by the following statement:Data provided by the International Whaling Commission&#8217;s Southern Ocean Research Partnership were all based upon non-lethal samples collected under a protocol approved by the Australian Antarctic Program Animal Ethics Committee (AAPAEC). These data were provided by the Partnership for the purpose of collaborative investigation.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><date
>2018-10-16T02:58:01Z_header</date
></data>