<data><id>2c12acd9-1600-487d-a809-2c2743381112</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Specimen, Observation, Occurrence</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>A BioBlitz brings together taxonomic experts, citizen scientists and the general public to inventory all species (plants, animals, fungi and more) in a particular area over a  24 hour period.  Participants record all the organisms they find, then experts verify their identity. As the Blitz proceeds and after it is done, the species records are compiled into a single data set- our species list. This resource represents all species sighted or collected from each of the flagship Ontario BioBlitz events hosted under the Ontario BioBlitz program. Records include observations or collections from the following BioBlitz events: Rouge Watershed BioBlitz 2012, Rouge Watershed BioBlitz 2013, Humber Watershed BioBlitz 2014, Don Watershed BioBlitz 2015, Credit Watershed BioBlitz 2016, and Rouge Watershed BioBlitz 2017. Species records may be modified as further information becomes available. Visit our website at www.ontariobioblitz.ca to learn more about the Ontario BioBlitz program!|A BioBlitz brings together taxonomic experts, citizen scientists and the general public to inventory all species (plants, animals, fungi and more) in a particular area over a  24 hour period.  Participants record all the organisms they find, then experts verify their identity. As the Blitz proceeds and after it is done, the species records are compiled into a single data set: the species list, which provides a snapshot of the biodiversity in that location on that date.  The Ontario BioBlitz program is led by a partnership of some of the province's leading conservation, education and research organizations. Our collective goal is to connect scientists with the public, promote citizen science, and to work together to increase awareness of Ontario's biodiversity and encourage local surveys of familiar and little known organisms.|5,414 occurrences</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><date
>2017-10-17</date
></data>