<data><id>2e102194-f384-4712-89a4-5db7a3fc409a</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>tree related microhabitat occurrences, tree species, saproxylic, Forest ecosystem, taxonomic biodiversity, permanent plots, spatially explicit|Occurrence|Observation</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>&#8216;Tree &#8211; tree&#8217; interactions are important structuring mechanisms for forest community dynamics. Forest management takes advantage of competition effects on tree growth by removing or retaining trees to achieve management goals. Both competition and silviculture have thus a strong effect on density and distribution of Tree related Microhabitats (TreMs) which are key features for forest taxa at the stand scale (e.g. Bouget et al. 2013, 2014). In particular, spatially explicit data to understand patterns and mechanisms of TreM formation in forest stands are rare. To train and eventually improve decision making capacities related to the integration of biodiversity aspects into forest management 39 usually 1 ha (100 m x 100m) permanent plots were established in dominant forest communities of Europe. Due to their demonstration character the selection of plots was non-systematic. They do, however, cover a broad range of forest types (e.g. beech-oak, beech-fir (-spruce), oak-hornbeam, pine-spruce, etc.), altitudinal gradient (from 25 m &#8211; 1850 m) and site conditions (e.g. oligotrophic Luzulo-Fagetum or Vaccinio-Pinetum to mesotrophic Galio-Fagetum or Milio-Fagetum). For each plot the following data is collected: (1) tree location as polar coordinates (stem base map), (2) tree species, (3) forest mensuration data (dbh in [cm], tree height in [m]), (4) tree related microhabitats (TreMs) and (5) tree status (living or standing dead). In addition to the spatial dendrometric data we provide information on plot establishment, management history (year of last intervention), forest type, plot location (state, region, country), elevation, means for annual precipitation and temperature, and the natural forest community.|Initially the permanent plots established within the Integrate+ project had the focus on showing good practice examples of integrative forest management concepts. The plots were designed following the Marteloscope approach to allow practitioners to perform virtual tree selection exercises in the demonstration sites based on different scenarios and forest management strategies. Immediate feedback on their decisions is given in terms of ecological and economic impacts. Particular attention was given to tree related microhabitats as these structures are home to many, also endangered species. Retaining and restoring such habitats in managed forests can be well integrated into the work portfolio of forest managers and thus be a direct contribution to biodiversity conservation in managed forests. The TreM recording and the development of the field catalogue was primarily aimed at providing individual habitat values for each tree to make harvesting impacts visible to practitioners in Marteloscope exercises. In the course of the project the plots themselves proved valuable as exploratory forests for other research questions as well. In particular, the database with the spatially explicit information on trees and TreMs looked promising to increase understanding of TreM formation and development, and also spatial distribution.|15,191 occurrences</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><date
>2017-07-25</date
></data>