<data><id>3c9e2297-bf20-4827-928e-7c7eefd9432c</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Occurrence|French Guiana|Neotropics|Opiliones|Specimen</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>This dataset provides information on specimens of harvestmen (Arthropoda, Arachnida, Opiliones) collected in French Guiana. Field collections have been initiated in 2012 within the framework of the CEnter for the Study of Biodiversity in Amazonia (CEBA: www.labex-ceba.fr/en/). This dataset is a work in progress.  Occurrences are recorded in an online database stored at the EDB laboratory after each collecting trip and the dataset is updated on a monthly basis. Voucher specimens and associated DNA are also stored at the EDB laboratory until deposition in natural history Museums. The latest version of the dataset is publicly and freely accessible through our Integrated Publication Toolkit at http://130.120.204.55:8080/ipt/resource.do?r=harvestmen_of_french_guiana or through the Global Biodiversity Information Facility data portal at http://www.gbif.org/dataset/3c9e2297-bf20-4827-928e-7c7eefd9432c.|French Guiana is a French overseas department covered at 97% by primary forest (Gond et al. 2011). As such, it represents the only Outermost Region of Europe covering a large fraction of mainland in tropical South America. The territory is part of the Guianan moist forests ecoregion and has strong biogeographic affinities with the rest of the Amazonia bioregion (Olson et al. 2001). The biological diversity of French Guiana is now one of the best known in South America, yet some gaps in knowledge still exist, especially in arthropods.With more than 6500 species, harvestmen (Opiliones) is the third most diverse order of arachnid after Acari and Araneae (Kury 2013). They occur in superficial soil layers, leaf litter, under bark, and on vegetation from ground to canopy (Pinto-da-Rocha and Bonaldo 2006). The maximum richness of harvestmen species is found in the Neotropical region, however, diversity patterns within this region are still poorly known, both on regional and local scales. Because of their relatively high abundance and diversity in the Neotropical forests, they are useful candidates for studying community ecology (e.g. Proud et al. 2012), phylogeography, and biogeography (e.g. Sharma and Giribet 2012).By providing a database on harvestmen of French Guiana, regularly updated and publicly available, our goal is to provide a fast and efficient tool for sharing and tracking information on collected specimens. This database will be used for disseminating biodiversity information related to ongoing work on ecology and evolution of harvestmen in French Guiana. We also aim to promote best practices for recording and sharing biodiversity data within our research community. We believe this will make a valuable contribution to the global effort of sharing harvestmen database information (e.g. Merino-S&#225;inz et al. 2013).|3,405 occurrences</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><date
>2019-02-21</date
></data>