<data><id>3d6c8883-c29b-48f6-9fbf-9a5ad6ecbee4</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject /><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>The Bird Conservation Targeting Project (BCTP) produces breeding distribution maps for a suite of rare and declining farmland and/or woodland birds. The maps can be used to guide the prescription of land management advice based on the species already breeding in an area, or for allocating funding towards sites known to be important for birds. The data cover a 5-year period, and are up-dated annually. Data are collated from a wide range of sources to produce the most comprehensive maps possible. The data are displayed as presence-only records. Absence of a record does not necessarily indicate a true absence record, as there may be no data available. BCTP outputs were first produced in England in 2004, in Wales and Northern Ireland in 2008, and in Scotland in 2009. This dataset contains the non-sensitive records for England, Scotland and Northern Ireland, compiled in 2012, covering the 2006 - 2010 breeding seasons (plus any 2011 data available). The sensitive records are in a separate dataset on the NBN. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; The species selection varies in each country. There are non-sensitive records for 30 species in England, 26 species in Scotland, and 19 species in Northern Ireland. Welsh data are not included in this dataset, and will be added when they become available.  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; English data were not updated in 2012. Date ranges for the current English data are 2004-2009 for woodland birds, and 2005-2010 for other species.  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; The BCTP is a partnership between the British Trust for Ornithology (BTO), the Centre for Environmental Data and Recording (CEDaR), the Countryside Council for Wales (CCW), the Department of Agriculture and Rural Development (DARD), Forestry Commission England (FCE), Forestry Commission Wales (FCW), Forest Service (FS), Natural England (NE), Northern Ireland Environment Agency, the RSPB and Scottish Natural Heritage (SNH). The BCTP partners are grateful to the contributions of the data providers listed at &lt;a href="http://www.rspb.org.uk/targeting"http://www.rspb.org.uk/targeting&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.|135,656 occurrences</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><date
>2017-06-16</date
></data>