<data><id>3e95aa8e-a40c-4d34-ad11-7560484f1ff9</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>species richness, understory light availability, Brazilian Atlantic Forest, tropical forests, Keywords: Seasonal Semideciduous Forests, forest inventory|Occurrence</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>AbstractTo understand future changes in community composition due to global changes, the knowledge about community dynamics is of crucial importance. To improve our understanding about processes and patterns involved in maintaining species rich neotropical ecosystems, we provide here a dataset from the one hectare Forest of Seu Nico (FSN) Dynamics Plot from Southeastern Brazil. We report diameter at breast height, basal area and height measurements of 2868 trees and treelets identified during two census spanning over a nine-year period. Furthermore, soil properties and understory light availability of all 100 10 x 10m subplots from the one hectare FSN Dynamics Plot during the second census are given.|Global changes such as habitat destruction, fragmentation and climate change threaten species richness and diversity of tropical forests (Wright 2010, Gastauer &amp; Meira-Neto 2013, Magnago et al. 2014). To outline and understand their influences on tropical forest communities, long term monitoring studies, so-called community dynamics, are necessary (Losos &amp; Leigh Jr. 2004, Wright 2005, Ernst et al. 2009, Pan et al. 2011, Laurance et al. 2014).Among tropical forests, the Brazilian Atlantic Forest is one of the most diverse ecosystems (Stehmann et al. 2009). Due to its high degree of endemism and endangered status it is considered a biodiversity hotspot (Myers et al. 2000). Once covering up to 1,500,000 km2 (C&#226;mara 2005), only about 11 % of the original Atlantic Rainforest remains, most of it as small secondary forest patches (Ribeiro et al. 2009a). Species rich old-growth forests like the Forest of Seu Nico (FSN) in Vi&#231;osa municipality, Minas Gerais, Brazil are extremely rare and little studied (Campos et al. 2006, Ribeiro et al. 2009, Gastauer &amp; Meira-Neto 2013, 2014). The aim of this data paper is the distribution of dynamics data from the FSN Dynamics Plot in order to increase knowledge about community composition and maintenance in the Brazilian Atlantic Forest.|2,868 occurrences</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><date
>2015-06-05</date
></data>