<data><id>4359b08c-37a2-4ec9-98a5-ce4887fc3a80</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Occurrence|Specimen</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>This dataset includes specimens originating from India in the natural history collections at the University Museum of the Norwegian University of Science and Technology (NTNU). &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Animals&lt;/b&gt;: The zoological collection includes 1 cnidarian, 122 molluscs (mostly marine), 24 birds, 4 mammals and three reptiles. These are all old specimens, presumably from the end of the 19th century or the first half of the 20th century, without collecting date. In addition, the collecting site is poorly documented, often restricted to &#8220;India&#8221; or &#8220;Indian Ocean&#8221;. There is no easy way to obtain more precise data. Data from Indian specimens in Trondheim are not previously available in the GBIF portal. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Plants&lt;/b&gt;: The vascular plant collection has not been digitised, but random sampling suggests that it contains no specimens from India. The most interesting Indian material in Trondheim is found in the bryophyte collection, which houses the legacy of the botanist Ingebrigt Hagen (1852-1917). In the course of 2013 the bryophyte herbarium with its circa 30.000 specimens will be digitised. A random sample suggests that the number of specimens from India will be around 200. These are mostly from the Himalaya, and include relatively many type specimens (not labelled as such) which the Finnish botanist V.F. Brotherus (1849-1929) has worked on. These specimens have relatively complete collecting data. Moreover, the digitisation project in Trondheim includes the addition of the currently valid nomenclature. As an illustration of the data that become available after digitisation, an initial sample is included in this dataset.|An international project in India to support capacity building in biodiversity informatics under the UN- program &#8220;Intergovernmental Platform for Biodiversity and Ecosystem Services (IPBES)&#8221;. The project aims to enhance decision making and improve nature management in India.|154 occurrences</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><date
>2018-07-09</date
></data>