<data><id>484ba7d4-531e-4dc4-bc52-99a8c363fdcd</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Occurrence|Observation|Algae, Intertidal environment, Intertidal zonation, Benthos, Data, Marine Genomics</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>&lt;p&gt;Biodiversity data collected twice a year by schools along a fixed transect in the intertidal area, Portugal 2005-2010.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Along the transect the different ecological zones were identified and quadrants different quadrants of (50 by 50 cm) were deployed in each zone. In each quadrant the abundance of all species were either counted or the percentage coverage was estimated. &lt;/br&gt;Other data recorded include omoung others the length of the zone and the slope. More information (in Portugese) can be found in the protocol : &lt;a href="http://www.ciimar.up.pt/mobidic/documentos/MoBiDIC_descriProtocolo.pdf"&gt; http://www.ciimar.up.pt/mobidic/documentos/MoBiDIC_descriProtocolo.pdf &lt;/a&gt;Most of the population in Portugal lives along its coast. Consequently, there are schools across the country with easy access to beaches. The ecosystems of the intertidal zone are living laboratories and scientific and educational opportunities they offer are numerous. &lt;/br&gt;The program MoBiDiC seeks to reconcile the scientific needs, with the popularization of science and education of young students. The objective of this project is therefore beyond the awareness of the issue of biodiversity. Students will have the opportunity to interact with members of the national and international scientific community, know the flora and fauna of the Portuguese coast and contact with marine ecosystems.&lt;/br&gt;Simultaneously, we believe that these activities with the school community also ensure a good impact on the rest of the community. Data collected by students from different parts of the country will be placed online in a database created for this purpose. They will thus be available for the entire school community, to be used in the classroom as well as for the general public and scientific community.&lt;/br&gt;Download the leaflet of this project here: &lt;a href="http://www.ciimar.up.pt/mobidic/documentos/desdobravelMobidic.pdf"/&gt; http://www.ciimar.up.pt/mobidic/documentos/ desdobravelMobidic.pdf &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;|6,873 occurrences</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><date
>2019-09-19</date
></data>