<data><id>6fd6f172-5877-4ebb-857f-2a7da6201d3e</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Checklist, flora, organic fields, monitoring, agricultural biodiversity, Mascarenes|Derivedfromoccurrence</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>This dataset is the checklist of the biannual qualitative surveys for the presence of the non-crop flora in and around pilot organic fields set in 2017 on the island of Mauritius. Plants were identified in-situ or collected for identification at The Mauritius Herbarium. The monitoring of eleven fields or greenhouses scattered around the island and having different crops, is part of an effort from Mauritius NGO Le Velo Vert (LVV) to mainstream organic agriculture. LVV wants to highlight the importance of correct plant identification and the uses of non-crop species to improve and support organic farming. LVV believes sharing data will increase transparency and help cooperation of local, regional and global stakeholders of different fields to improve perspectives and multidisciplinarity, much needed to face the increasing problems of declining biodiversity and resources, and a growing human population.This databasing effort has been funded by BID Africa Call 2017, grant BID-AF2017-SMA_0316 (https://www.gbif.org/project/aRCxBBF1BYU2C0us62ea4/getting-the-plants-to-all-dissemination-of-information-from-the-collection-of-the-mauritius-herbarium.) "|This checklist consists of biannual qualitative surveys for the presence of the non-crop flora in and around pilot organic fields set in 2017 on the island of Mauritius. Plants were identified in-situ or collected for identification at The Mauritius Herbarium. The monitoring of ten fields or greenhouses scattered around the island and having different crops, is part of an effort from Mauritius NGO Le Velo Vert (LVV) to mainstream organic agriculture. LVV wants to highlight the importance of correct plant identification and the uses of non-crop species to improve and support organic farming. LVV believes sharing data will increase transparency and help cooperation of local, regional and global stakeholders of different fields to improve perspectives and multidisciplinarity, much needed to face the increasing problems of declining biodiversity and resources, and a growing human population.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><date
>2018-10-19</date
></data>