<data><id>7ac0504d-0230-4029-afbe-04657ae47c48</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Occurrence|nomenclature|type material|herbarium colletion|image colletion|western Mediterranean|Fungi|Mycology|GDA|GDAC</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>This dataset contains the specimen records from the catalogue of the nomenclature types of fungi and lichens in the Herbarium of the University of Granada, Spain. These herbarium specimens are included in the GDA and GDAC collections, acronyms from Index Herbariorum (Thiers 2014). A catalogue of types from the Herbarium of the University of Granada has not previously been compiled. As a result, a search of these collections to get digital images to preserve and publish them yielded a large number of previously unrecognized types. At this time, the type collection of fungi and lichens at the Herbarium of the University of Granada contains 146 type material of 72 nominal taxa, most from Agaricales and the genus Cortinarius, described from the western Mediterranean, mainly Spain, by the following authors: V.Antonin, J.Ballar&#225;, A.Bidaud, G.F.Bills, M.Bon, C.Cano, M.Casares, G.Chevassut, M.Contu, F.Esteve.Ravent&#243;s, R.Gal&#225;n, L.Guzm&#225;n-D&#225;valos, R.Henry, E.Horak, R.Mahiques, G.Malen&#231;on, P.Mo&#235;nne-Loccoz, G.Moreno, A.Ortega, F.Palaz&#243;n, V.N.Su&#225;rez.-Santiago, A.V&#234;zda, J.Vila, and M.Villareal.For each specimen, the locality indication, species name, observation date, collector, type status, related information, associated sequences, other catalogue numbers related to each type, and image URL are recorded. The dataset is associated with an image collection named &#8220;Colecci&#243;n de im&#225;genes de los tipos nomenclaturales de hongos, l&#237;quenes, musgos y algas incluidos en el Herbario de la Universidad de Granada (GDA y GDAC)&#8221; (Vizoso and Quesada 2013) which is hosted and accessible at the GBIF.ES Hosting and Publishing Service &#8220;Biodiversity Image Portal of Spanish collections&#8221; and is also available at the Herbarium of University of Granada institutional web (Vizoso 2014a) (http://herbarium.ugr.es/pages/imagenes/tipos-nomenclaturales/tipos_hongos). That image collection contains 117 images of which 59 correspond to the nomenclature types of 52 taxa (50 fungi, 2 lichens), the rest of the images in this collection correspond to documents and specimens or microscopy photographs which are included in the herbarium specimens of fungi. These complement and document the process of the typification.|The Herbarium of the University of Granada combines two general collections: GDA and GDAC (Thiers 2014). The GDA used to be the herbarium of the Pharmacy Faculty, which was created in 1852. In 1970, GDAC was created in the Science Faculty. In 2000, both herbaria were moved to the same place, forming the current Herbarium of the University of Granada. The GDAC collection was closed in 2000 with a total of 45,000 records. New materials are continuously added to the collection and registered with the GDA acronym. Currently, the GDA Herbarium has become an essential reference for studies of the flora of southeastern Spain. Both collections, the GDA and GDAC, include specimens of vascular plants and cryptogams. Vascular plants amount to 87% of the whole collection (including a 3% of pteridophytes) and cryptogams 13% (9% in the GDAC and 4% in the GDA). Over 50% of all vascular-plant specimens are in the GDA collection, which continues to grow, and the rest belongs to the GDAC. Conversely, over 69% of all cryptogams come from the GDAC. Within this group, the fungus (51%), lichen (25%, completely within the GDA) and moss (18%) collections have special significance. The remaining specimens correspond to algae and liverworts. Geographically, the country with the most specimens is Spain (94%), followed by Morocco (3.5%) and Portugal (1.5%). Within Spain, the largest portion is from Andalusia (82%) which in turn includes samples from Granada (68%), Almer&#237;a (11%), Ja&#233;n (7%), M&#225;laga (6%), and other Andalusian provinces, confirming the value of our Herbarium as a reference for studying the flora from eastern Andalusia.Since the unification of the GDA and GDAC collections, many tasks have been accomplished. These include a complete review of all materials, recovery and incorporation of unregistered materials, updating curatorial methods and, even more important, the computerization of the entire collection. More recently, the Herbarium of the University of Granada has developed several projects to digitalize images of high-priority specimens in order to preserve them and make them available on Internet. As a result of the reviewing process, many types that had not previously been compiled were detected. In addition, the catalogues of type specimens of different groups of the Herbarium of the University of Granada have been compiled, published, and made accessible on Internet through the &#8220;Biodiversity Image Portal of Spanish collections&#8221; at the GBIF.ES Hosting and Publishing Service and at the Herbarium of the University of Granada institutional web. The catalogue of type specimens of fungi and lichens has been one of the first published on the GBIF.es Integrated Publishing Toolkit (IPT). This dataset is the most important part of the image collection &#8220;Colecci&#243;n de im&#225;genes de los tipos nomenclaturales de hongos, l&#237;quenes, musgos y algas incluidos en el Herbario de la Universidad de Granada (GDA y GDAC)&#8221; (Vizoso and Quesada 2013) published in GBIF.ES and &#8220;Tipos nomenclaturales de hongos&#8221; (Vizoso 2014a) and &#8220;Tipos nomenclaturales de l&#237;quenes&#8221; (Vizoso 2014b) available on the Herbarium of University of Granada institutional web site.|146 occurrences</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><date
>2018-11-30</date
></data>