<data><id>7f24aff6-f762-11e1-a439-00145eb45e9a</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Occurrence</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>&lt;p&gt;Recopilaci&#243;n de las citas sobre flora vascular de la Comunidad Foral de Navarra y su entorno, realizada por la Sociedad de Ciencias Aranzadi para el Gobierno de Navarra y que dio origen al Cat&#225;logo de Flora de Navarra publicado en el a&#241;o 1992. Se compone de 1/3 de citas bibliogr&#225;ficas, 1/3 de ejemplares de distintos herbarios y 1/3 de observaciones. Su valor es hist&#243;rico y de referencia por su volumen y amplitud (105.566 citas de 3.143 taxones). En el proceso de recopilaci&#243;n se han perdido los datos de observadores e identificadores y muchas citas carecen de fecha, por lo que su uso queda limitado por estas causas. En 2011 la nomenclatura taxon&#243;mica se ha normalizado y actualizado, principalmente con la ayuda de Species2000, versi&#243;n 2010 y Anthos (www.anthos.es). Compilation of quotes about vascular flora of Navarra and the environment, conducted by Aranzadi Science Society for the Government of Navarra. It gave rise to the Flora of Navarra catalogue published in 1992. It consists of 1 / 3 of quotations, 1 / 3 of different herbarium copies and 1 / 3 of observations. It has an historical value as well as a reference value for its volume and extent (105,566 citations from 3,143 taxa). The use of the information is limited due to the lost of the data observers and data identifiers during the process of collecting data, as well as the lost of the date for many quotes. The taxonomic nomenclature has been standardized and updated in 2011, supported mainly by Species2000 &#8211; version 2010 database, and Project Anthos services (www.anthos.es).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note: this dataset was previously orphaned. It has been rescued by &#9312; extracting it from the GBIF.org index (see GBIF Download in External Data) and &#9313; republishing it on this IPT data hosting centre as version 1.0.&lt;/p&gt;|105,523 occurrences</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><date
>2018-11-30</date
></data>