<data><id>83598aa6-f762-11e1-a439-00145eb45e9a</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Dothideales, gilled boletales, Balearic Islands, Myxomycetes, Helotiales, Tremelales, Spain, Fungi, Cantharellaceae, Ustilaginales, fungi and lichens, Laboulbeniales, mitosporic fungi, Gomphales, Gasteromycetes, Aphyllophorales, Agaricales|Occurrence|Observation</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>&lt;p&gt;The database contains detailed distribution information on several fungus groups species. The information has been revised, and in many time compiled, by expert mycologist(s) working on the monographs for the Flora Mycologica Iberica Project (FMI). Records comprise both collection and observational data, obtained from a variety of sources including field work, herbaria, and literature.  The database contains 54,138 records, of which 20,813 are georeferenced. These correspond to 2445 species, grouped in 18 classes. The geographical scope of the dataset is Iberian Peninsula (Continental Portugal and Spain) and Balearic Islands. The complete dataset is provided in Darwin Core Archive format.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The " Flora Mycologica Iberica Project database"  is one of the main results produce by the "Flora Mycologica, a research project that stood from 1996 to 2008 and involved over 30 researchers . It provides information on 2,445 fungus species recorded from The Iberian Peninsula and Balearic Islands. As an online resource, it is a valuable service, with a high reuse  potential, based on its coverage, taxonomic scrutiny --carried out by taxonomic experts in the different groups-- and validation processes of the associate information (location, habitat).   The other major outcome of the project were the monographs of the covered groups: Aphyllophorales [p.p.](Telleria Melo, 1995), Myxomycetes [p.p.] (Lado &amp; Pando, 1997), Gasteromycetes [p.p.] (Calonge, 1998), Laboulbeniales (Santamaria, 1998, 2003) and Dictiosporic Dothideales (Checa, 2004).These provides description, illustrations, identification keys and additional infomation on the species and taxa included in this database.&lt;/p&gt;|This dataset was conceived within the Flora Mycologica Iberica Project (FMI) to serve two purposes:						1.  To gather the available information on Iberian fungi as published on the scientific literature, to establish a baseline knowledge for the project and provide basic information upon which to elaborate the project's monographs, among other purposes.						2. To incorporate the primary data produced and compiled during the project to the previously available information, and thus providing updated and validated data on Iberian fungi. These data were gathered or verified by professional researches, many of whom also authored the project's monographs (see under References).  Primary data added in this way mostly came from studied herbarium specimens and field campaigns. Targeted field surveys on sites poorly known and of ecological or conservation relevance were carried out within the framework of the project. The primary data were also made available as publication in the "Cuadernos de Trabajo de Flora Micologica" series (see References).|59,235 occurrences</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><date
>2018-11-30</date
></data>