<data><id>8d88898d-a2c4-4616-a1fe-431b9c06b671</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Occurrence|Specimen</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>University of Texas at Arlington Amphibian and Reptile Diversity Research Center: During the 1980s the herpetological collection witnessed an explosive session of growth.  Prior to the 1980s the collection contained approximately 8,000 herpetological specimens.  By the end of the decade more than 30,000 specimens were housed in the collection.  During the 1990s the size of the collection increased at an almost exponential rate.  During this time, the collection grew to contain more than 80,000 specimens.  This combined with efforts from  faculty and students helped to establish national and international recognition for the collection.  Since the turn of the century the herpetology collection at the University of Texas at Arlington has experienced more growth and the collection now houses some 115,000 specimens and is among the top herpetological collections in the United States.  In 2004 the entire herpetological collection was moved from the basement of the Life Sciences building to the newly constructed Amphibian and Reptile Diversity Research Center.     Asides from housing a major herpetological collection, the Department of Biology at the  University of Texas at Arlington has hosted and facilitated the academic pursuits of a diverse student body.  This has also provided inherent benefits to the museum collection as well.  The collection currently holds the worlds largest assemblage of reptiles and amphibians from Guatemala as well as significant holdings from Texas, Bolivia, Cameroon, Colombia, Costa Rica, Guyana, Honduras, and Mexico.  Along with several thousand fluid preserved specimens, the collection maintains several type specimens, a sizeable osteological collection, cleared and stained specimens, audio recordings of frog calls, one of the largest collections of herpetological photographs in the United States, as well as a comprehensive herpetological library.  These resources can be made available for use by qualified individuals.  For questions regarding the use of the collection resources please call 817-272-2406.|114,203 occurrences</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><date
>2016-12-22</date
></data>