<data><id>98442b0b-9f7b-4924-9289-5b793946ca01</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Echinoids, Hauterivian, Early Cretaceous, Calcaires &#224; Spatangues Formation, Paris Basin, France</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>This dataset compiles occurrence data (all data are referenced by locality names and georeferenced WGS1984) of fossil echinoids collated from the literature published over a century and a half, from 1857 to 2012, by Cotteau (1857&#8212;1878, 1862&#8212;1867), Valette (1908), Corroy (1925), Rat et al. (1987), and Sauc&#232;de et al. (2012). The dataset was completed by data from collection specimens housed at the department of Geology of Universit&#233; de Bourgogne (Dijon, France), specimens sampled in the field by J Houdard, A Valette, B David, and P Robert, at the Mus&#233;um national d'Histoire naturelle (Paris, France), specimens sampled by J Lambert, and at the department of Geosciences of Universit&#233; de Rennes 1 (Rennes, France), specimens sampled by P Courville. The dataset also gives information on taxonomy (from species to order and higher taxonomic levels). Systematics was reviewed and homogeneized by T Sauc&#232;de for taxonomic relevance (Sauc&#232;de et al. 2012).|This dataset inventories occurrence records of fossil echinoid specimens collected in the Calcaires &#224; Spatangues Formation (CSF) that crops out in the southeast of the Paris Basin (France), and is dated from the Acanthodiscus radiatus chronozone (ca. 132 Ma, early Hauterivian, Early Cretaceous). Fossil richness and abundance of the CSF has attracted the attention of palaeontologists since the middle of the nineteenth century. This dataset compiles occurrence data (referenced by locality names and geographic coordinates with decimal numbers) of fossil echinoids both collated from the literature published over a century and a half, and completed by data from collection specimens. The dataset also gives information on taxonomy (from species to order and higher taxonomic levels), which has been checked for reliability and consistency. It compiles a total of 628 georeferenced occurrence data of 26 echinoid species represented by 22 genera, 14 families, and 9 orders.|628 occurrences</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><date
>2013-08-10</date
></data>