<data><id>b043c480-dd36-4f4f-aa82-e188753ff09d</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Checklist|Inventorythematic|Uredinales, rust fungi, rusts, Belgium, TrIAS, checklist, plant pathogens, inventory, host plants</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>&lt;p&gt;The catalogue of rust fungi in Belgium is a species checklist dataset published by the Botanic Garden Meise. It contains information on 237 native and non-native species of rust fungi occurring in Belgium. The catalogue is the result of literature review and herbarium inspection of the main public Belgian herbaria, complemented with specimens from private herbaria. The checklist  has been published as three separate volumes by Vanderweyen &amp; Fraiture (2006, 2008 and 2011). Here it is published as a standardized Darwin Core Archive and includes for each rust fungus: the scientific name, higher classification, full bibliographic reference and stable taxon ID (in the taxon core), the occurrence status, whether the species is native or introduced (establishment) and date of first and last recorded observation  in Belgium (given as a date range in the event date in the distribution extension). In the taxon core, we also provide the taxonomic information (scientific name and higher classification) of all 518 recorded host plant species and link those to their pathogenic rust fungus/fungi in the resource relationship extension. Issues with the dataset can be reported at: https://github.com/trias-project/uredinales-belgium-checklist&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have released this dataset to the public domain under a Creative Commons Zero waiver. We would appreciate it if you follow the GBIF citation guidelines (https://www.gbif.org/citation-guidelines) when using the data. If you have any questions regarding this dataset, don't hesitate to contact us via the contact information provided in the metadata or via https://twitter.com/trias_project.&lt;/p&gt;|This dataset was published as open data for the TrIAS project (Tracking Invasive Alien Species http://trias-project.be, Vanderhoeven et al. 2017), with technical support provided by the Research Institute for Nature and Forest (INBO). It is selected as one of the authoritative sources for the compilation of a unified and standardized checklist of alien species in Belgium.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><date
>2019-03-19</date
></data>