<data><id>b2906713-07c4-41b1-887f-adfc0a24b3ab</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Samplingevent|ecosystem functioning, fish-based index of biotic integrity, River Yser, fish distribution, LifeWatch, freshwater, River Meuse, open data, River Scheldt</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>&lt;p&gt;VIS - 'Reference Freshwater Monitoring&#8217; in Flanders, Belgium is a sample based dataset published by the Research Institute for Nature and Forest (INBO). The database is described in Brosens et al. 2015 (https://doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.475.8556). The dataset contains over 25,000 fish occurrences sampled between 2013 and 2015 from 246 in inland rivers, streams and canals in Flanders, Belgium. The dataset includes 42 fish species, as well as a number of non-target species (mainly crustaceans). The data are retrieved from the Fish Information System (VIS), a database set up to monitor the status of fishes and their habitats in Flanders and are collected in support of the Water Framework Directive, the Habitat Directive, certain red lists, and biodiversity research. Additional information, such as measurements, absence information and abiotic data are available upon request. Issues with the dataset can be reported at https://github.com/inbo/data-publication/tree/master/datasets/vis-freshwater-monitoring-events&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Length and weight measurement data of the individual fishes, absence information, occurrence data since 2013, as well as abiotic data of the sampling points (pH, temperature, etc.) are not included in the Darwin Core Archive and are available upon request.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To allow anyone to use this dataset, we have released the data to the public domain under a Creative Commons Zero waiver (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). We would appreciate however, if you read and follow these norms for data use (http://www.inbo.be/en/norms-for-data-use) and provide a link to the original dataset (https://doi.org/10.15468/klsy8u) whenever possible. If you use these data for a scientific paper, please cite the dataset following the applicable citation norms and/or consider us for co-authorship. We are always interested to know how you have used or visualized the data, or to provide more information, so please contact us via the contact information provided in the metadata, opendata@inbo.be or https://twitter.com/LifeWatchINBO.&lt;/p&gt;|The Fish Information System or VIS (http://vis.milieuinfo.be) is a database created by the Research Institute for Nature and Forest (INBO) which is used to monitor the status of fishes and their habitats in Flanders, Belgium and to calculate the biotic integrity (Karr 1981, Belpaire et al. 2000, Breine et al. 2004, 2007, 2010) of fish assemblages. It contains data regarding occurrences, individual morphometrics, stocks, pollutants, indices, and non-native fish species. Sampling has been going on since 1992, the database model was designed in 1994 (Verbiest et al. 1994), the first database developed in 1996 (Verbiest et al. 1996), and the consolidated database set up in 2001. VIS is used for supporting NATURA 2000, an ecological network of protected areas in Europe and to calculate the EQR (Ecological Quality Ratio) in the framework of the EU Water Directive (Directive 2000/60/EC). Further, the database provides updated information for Flemish Red Lists of fishes and lampreys (Verreycken et al. 2014) and on the distribution status of non-native and invasive fish species. The data are also crucial in fish stock management and for reporting on the status of the European eel stock as required by the Eel Regulation (Council Regulation (EC) N&#176; 1100/2007). This dataset is a standardized extraction of all inland water species occurrences from VIS.|55,086 occurrences</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><date
>2019-03-25</date
></data>