<data><id>bcabcfcc-b613-43b6-b0bd-4c79ecc396da</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Occurrence|nomenclature|type material|herbarium collection|western Mediterranean|GDA|GDAC|vascular plants|Morocco|Spain|Iter maroccanum|Plantes d'Espagne</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>This dataset contains the specimen records from the catalogue of the nomenclature types of vascular plants in the Herbarium of the University of Granada, Spain. These herbarium specimens are included in the GDA and GDAC collections, acronyms registered  in the Index Herbariorum (Thiers 2014). A catalogue of vascular plants types from the Herbarium of the University of Granada has not previously been compiled. As a result of developing a doctoral thesis on the nomenclatural types included in their collections, and a project to get digital images to preserve and publish them, a large number of previously unrecognized types were identified. At this time, the type collection of vascular plants at the Herbarium of the University of Granada contains 547 type material of 438 nominal taxa. Most of the types provide from Morocco and Spain (eastern Andalusia). Almost half of them come from the following exsiccatae: Iter Maroccanum (1927-1930) of Font Quer, Plantes D&#8217;Espagne of Sennen, Flora Iberica Selecta, Flora Selecta Canariensis of Sventenius, and Pteridophyta Iberica. The rest of this catalogue has been generated through researches conducted by Botany Department of the University of Granada, mostly from eastern Andalusia. For each specimen, the locality indication, species name, observation date, collector, type status, related information, associated sequences, and other catalogue numbers related to each type are recorded. The dataset is associated with an image collection available at the Herbarium of University of Granada institutional web site (http://herbarium.ugr.es/pages/imagenes/tipos-nomenclaturales/tvascular) or by request images to the data provider while loading the image collection on the server is completed.|The Herbarium of the University of Granada combines two general collections: GDA and GDAC (Thiers 2014). Both sections have different origin, dates, taxonomic groups and curatorial treatment. Since 2000, both herbaria were moved to the same place, forming the current Herbarium of the University of Granada. A complete review of all materials, recovery and incorporation of unregistered materials, updating curatorial methods and, even more important, the computerization of the entire collection were the main tasks accomplished since then.Late years, the Herbarium of the University of Granada has developed a project to digitalize images of high-priority specimens in order to preserve them and make them available on Internet. As a result of the reviewing process, several types that had not previously been compiled were detected. In order to reveal the existence of nomenclatural types whose deposit in the herbarium was unknown and to catalogue, analyze and validate the types of the different taxonomic groups and its historical collections, a doctoral thesis was conceived and the associated research conducted.   This lead to an in-depth analysis of both sections and their historical collections. As a result, the catalogues of type specimens of different taxonomic groups of the Herbarium of the University of Granada have been compiled, published, and made accessible on Internet at the Herbarium of the University of Granada institutional web.During the verification process of this information, errors in the database have been revealed, and corrected, thereby contributing to the databases cleaning and their validation. In this validation process, types corresponding to a bryophytes taxon and eight to a vascular plants whose names had not been published in an effective and valid way (according to Art. 29-30 and 32 of the ICN) have been removed from the catalogue.  Other four types have been validated by publishing a valid typification of their names. The disappearance of 10 types corresponding to six taxa of vascular plants has also been detected.In total, 533 nomenclatural types of vascular plants, four of macroscopic algae, 142 of fungi and four of lichens have been catalogued. From these, 293 types of vascular plants and 42 of fungi have been detected after the study of the historical collections included in the GDA Herbarium and the exhaustive review of the Fungi collection. In addition, 32 new types have been incorporated into the vascular collection and 54 types of fungi in GDA-Fungi corresponding to the publication of new taxa.The catalogue of type specimens of fungi and lichens was the first published on the GBIF.ES Integrated Publishing Toolkit (IPT) (http://ipt.gbif.es/resource?r=gda-fungi-tipos), updated in 2018, indexed on the GBIF.ORG Data Portal (https://www.gbif.org/dataset/7ac0504d-0230-4029-afbe-04657ae47c48) and published as data paper (Vizoso &amp; Quesada, 2015). In order to complete the main goals of this work we intend to publish the catalogue of type specimens of vascular plants in the same way. However, so far, aside form the fungi and lichen specimen catalogues, only the catalogue of types of macroscopic algae has been published, but at the Herbarium of the University of Granada institutional web.|547 occurrences</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><date
>2018-11-30</date
></data>