<data><id>f885d3e2-0310-43f5-a902-50dda62e6a68</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Occurrence</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>These spreadsheets provide the proportions of prey DNA sequences in the scats of Adelie penguins at Bechervaise Island and Whitney Point in East Antarctica. Samples were collected during two stages of the breeding season: mid brood guard (Bechervaise Island-January 4-6th 2013, Whitney Point 23- 28th December 2012) and mid creche (23-26th January 2013). Scat samples were collected from breeding birds, chicks and non-breeders at Bechervaise Island and breeding birds and chicks at Whitney Point. 'Breeders' were identified as individuals brooding or provisioning a chick, whereas 'non-breeders' were usually pairs that had reoccupied the colony and were building new practice nests with no chick present. Non-breeders in the colony include immature birds that have not yet bred and mature birds of breeding age that did not breed in a particular season (e.g. no partner or insufficient body condition)DNA from each sample was extracted and sequenced as per the protocols in the following paper:Jarman, S.N., McInnes, J.C., Faux, C., Polanowski, A.M., Marthick, J., Deagle, B.E., Southwell, C. and Emmerson, L. 2013 Adelie penguin population diet monitoring by analysis of food DNA in scats. PLoS One 8, e82227. (doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0082227).The Raw Data spreadsheet contains the proportion of each prey group of each individual sample, plus the total sequence count of prey items. Only samples with greater than 100 prey sequences are included in the dataset. The summary datasheet contains only prey taxa which contained greater than 2% of the proportion of sequences.Analysis of these data have been published in: McInnes JC, Emmerson L, Southwell C, Faux C, Jarman SN. (2016) Simultaneous DNA-based diet analysis of breeding, non-breeding and chick Adelie Penguins http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rsos.150443Quality: 2018-09-24 - The original datasheet was reformatted to fit OBIS/GBFI/IPT Biodiversity.AQ standardS. The new datasheet 'AdeliePenguinDiet2012_2013.csv" provides datasetID, recordNumber, resourceID, relatedResourceID, relationshipOfResource, relationshipAccordingTo, eventRemarks, eventDate, year, month, day, locality, locationID, verbatimLatitude, verbatimLongitude, decimalLatitude, decimalLongitude, continent, countryCode, preparation, identificationQualifier, occurrenceStatus, organismQuantity, organismQuantityType, basisOfRecord, behaviour, and institutionCode. The lowest taxonomical rank of the species identified that could be determined is provided, after matched in WoRMS (World Register of Marine Species).|2,436 occurrences</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><date
>2018-10-16</date
></data>