<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.97151</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Fibronectin_Modulation_Dataset</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>The associated .csv files constitute quantitative datasets underpinning the manuscript "Heterogeneity in mesenchymal motility reflects adaptive switching between two distinct migration modes", by Shafqat-Abbasi et al. Three datasets are presented with equivalent structures, reflecting data derived from multiscale, high resolution imaging of randomly migrating H1299-PL cells. These datasets focus on comparison of cells: attached on different concentrations of fibronectin (extracellular-matrix ligand, Fibronectin_Modulation_Dataset), following inhibition of Rho-associated kinase (ROCK, Y27632 inhibitor) or a control treatment (DMSO, ROCK_Modulation_Dataset), or following siRNA-mediated depletion of talin 1 protein levels compared to control siRNA treatment (Talin_Modulation_Dataset). Accordingly, each data set is divided into two conditions (denoted &#8220;1&#8221; or &#8220;2&#8221;), between which feature values are quantitatively compared throughout the manuscript. In each case, the values 1 and 2 in the &#8220;condition&#8221; column refer to: Fibronectin_Modulation_Dataset: 1 = 2.5 &#181;g/ml FN (2580 observations), 2 = 10 &#181;g/ml FN (7000 observations), ROCK_Modulation_Dataset: 1 = DMSO (2666 observations), 2 = 6 &#181;M ROCK Inh (985 observations), Talin_Modulation_Dataset: 1 = Control siRNA (3154 observations), 2 = talin 1 siRNA (6263 observations). Column structure within the files is as follows. The first 6 columns are indexing columns, wherein the: experimental condition is defined (1 vs 2, as above), experimental date is define, individual cell identities are defined, the mesenchymal cell migration mode is defined (0 = undetermined, e.g. dead cells or cells in contact, 1 = Discontinuous migration mode, 2 = Continuous migration mode), cell centre of area (row), and, cell centre of area (column) are defined. The following 60 columns define quantitative features extracted based on image analyses. These include 5 Behavioral features and 55 Organizational features, as defined in Figure 3 &#8211; figure supplement 1.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Cell Migration|Cell Adhesion|Cell Plasticity|Cell Adaptation|Cell Heterogeneity|Systems Microscopy</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2016-02-11T17:15:48Z</date
></data>