<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.24397</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Functional aspects of protist diversity and abundance in soils.</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>In this study we address the following questions with a natural environment (watershed 13): 1- what are the protist colonisers in disturbed soil? Whichare the late succession species? 2- what kinds of interactions are there between the rhizosphere community and soil protists? 3- to what extent does the litter and derived organic matter affect species composition? 4- what is the time scale of recovery after disturbance? We hope to be able to address the following issues also from the data collected. Do certain groups of species become active together, under similar habitat changes, or is the community dynamics more stochastic? One would predict that at low species biodiversity the community structure is more predictable, and at high diversity more stochastic. In this study, organic-free plots, litter exclusion and root exclusion plots are prepared to reduce species diversity. Soil protist activity consists of successions of groups of species becoming active then inactive in succession.The experimental plots consist of nine holes (75cm diameter) dug to about 30-50 cm. There are three treatments. First series of three: soil dug out and returned. Second series, soil dug out, sterilised in lab by autoclave,and returned. In third series, soil dug out and replaced by organic-matter-free sand. One of each plot type are covered with mesh to exclude litter deposit. One of each plot type are lined by mesh to exclude roots as well as mesh to exclude litter. One set of plots are left without exclusion. The plot containing sand as well as root and litter exclusion, will contain wheat grass debris as litter.Study_Sampling_Frequency: monthly</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Coweeta|LTER|protozoa|fungi|microbial|biodiversity|Coweeta|soil disturbance</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2011-04-26T22:02:00Z</date
></data>