<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.20601</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Biodiversity - Fauna - Soil Fauna - Cub Hill Forest Earthworms BES ID 547-</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Cub Hill forest EW metadataIntroductionThe Baltimore Ecosystem Study (BES) has established a network of long-term permanent forest plots. These plots will provide long-term data on vegetation, soil and hydrologic processes in the key ecosystem types within the urban ecosystem. The current network of study plots includes eight forest plots, chosen to represent the range of forest conditions in the area. The goal of the soil invertebrate survey was to compare community composition and abundance of soil macrofauna, primarily earthworms (Oligochatea), terrestrial isopods (Isopoda: Oniscidea), and millipedes (Diplopoda).  Plot Locations and CharacterizationsIn November of 1998 four rural, forested plots were established at Oregon Ridge Park in Baltimore County northeast of the Gwynns Falls Watershed. Oregon Ridge Park contains Pond Branch, the forested reference watershed for BES. Two of these four plots are located on the top of a slope, the other two are located midway up the slope.Four urban, forested plots were established in November 1998, two at Leakin Park and two adjacent to Hillsdale Park in west Baltimore City in the Gwynns Falls. One of the plots in Hillsdale Park was abandoned in 2004 due to continued vandalism.Plot locations:Hillsdale 1: 39&#65533;19'28.14"N, 76&#65533;42'16.49"WHillsdale 2: 39&#65533;19'31.24"N, 76&#65533;42'28.62"WLeakin 1: 39&#65533;18'1.32"N, 76&#65533;41'37.08"WLeakin 2: 39&#65533;18'5.42"N, 76&#65533;41'34.15"WOregon top-slope - 1: 39&#65533;28'51.11"N, 76&#65533;41'22.50"WOregon mid-slope - 1: 39&#65533;28'51.32"N, 76&#65533;41'18.24"WOregon top-slope - 2: 39&#65533;29'12.74"N, 76&#65533;41'22.88"WOregon mid-slope - 2: 39&#65533;29'12.68"N, 76&#65533;41'18.62"WSoil arthropods were sampled between November 1999 and 2000 using pitfall traps. At each plot a total of ten traps were placed which were emptied monthly. Earthworms were sampled using a combination of formalin solution (Raw 1954) and mustard suspension. 50cm x 50cm quadrats were used. Earthworms samples were taken is spring, summer and fall 1999, 2000, and 2002. In addition several qualitative samples were taken from residential and commercial areas in the city. Cub Hill forest EW metadataSamples were taken spring 2004, along two 100 m transects. 25 cm x 25 cm quadrats were used at every 10 m point along each transect. Animals were counted and weighed, later identified.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Baltimore|MD|Washington|D.C|Chesapeake Bay|Baltimore-Washington|Maryland</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2010-07-10</date
></data>