<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.20154</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>IPCC Climate Change Data: GFDL99 A2a Model: 2050 Mean Temperature</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>The experiments with the GFDL model used here were performed        using the coupled ocean-atmosphere model described in Manabe et        al. (1991) and Stouffer et al., (1994) and references therein.        The model has interactive clouds and seasonally varying solar        insolation. The atmospheric component has nine finite difference        (sigma) levels in the vertical. This version of the model was        run at a rhomboidal resolution of 15 waves (R15) yielding an        equivalent resolution of about 4.5 degrees  latitude by 7.5        degrees  longitude. The model has global geography consistent        with its computational resolution and seasonal (but not diurnal)        variation of insolation.  The ocean model is based on that of        Byan and Lewis (1979) with a spacing between gridpoints of 4.5        degrees  latitude and 3.7 degrees  longitude. It has 12 unevenly        spaced levels in the vertical dimension. To reduce model drift,        the fluxes of heat and water are adjusted by amounts which vary        seasonally and geographically, but do not change from one year        to another. The model also includes a dynamic sea-ice model        (Bryan, 1969) which allows the system additional degrees of        freedom.  The 1000-year unforced simulation used here is        described in Manabe and Stouffer (1996). The drift in        global-mean temperature during this unforced simulation is very        small at about -0.023 degrees C per century.  The two GFDL-R15        climate change experiments used here use the IS92a scenario of        estimated past and future greenhouse gas (GGa1) and combined        greenhouse gas and sulphate aerosol (GSa1) forcing for the        period 1765-2065 (Haywood et al., 1997). For the GGa1 experiment        only the 100-year segment from 1958-2057 are available through        the IPCC DDC. The radiative effects of all greenhouse gases is        represented in terms of an equivalent CO2 concentration, and the        direct radiative sulphate aerosol forcing is parameterised in        terms of specified spatially dependent surface albedo changes        (following Mitchell et al., 1995). Results from these climate        change experiments are discussed in Haywood et al. (1997).  The        model's climate sensitivity is about 3.7 degrees C.The A2 world consolidates into a series of roughly        continental economic regions, emphasizing local cultural roots.        In some regions, increased religious participation leads many to        reject a materialist path and to focus attention on contributing        to the local community. Elsewhere, the trend is towards ncreased        investment in education and science and growth in economic        productivity. Social and political structures diversify with        some regions moving towards stronger welfare systems and reduced        income inequality, while others move towards &amp;quot,lean&amp;quot,        government. Environmental concerns are relatively weak, although        some attention is paid to bringing local pollution under control        and maintaining local environmental amenities.The A2 world sees more international tensions and less        cooperation than in A1 or B1. People, ideas and capital are less        mobile so that technology diffuses slowly. International        disparities in productivity, and hence income per capita, are        maintained or increased. With the emphasis on family and        community life, fertility rates decline only slowly, although        they vary among regions. Hence, this scenario family has high        population growth (to 15 billion by 2100) with comparatively low        incomes per capita relative to the A1 and B1 worlds, at US$7,200        in 2050 and US$16,000 in 2100.Technological change is rapid in        some regions and slow in others as industry adjusts to local        resource endowments, culture, and education levels. Regions with        abundant energy and mineral resources evolve more resource        intensive economies, while those poor in resources place very        high priority on minimizing import dependence through        technological innovation to improve resource efficiency and make        use of substitute inputs. The fuel mix in different regions is        determined primarily by resource availability. And divisions        among regions persist in terms of their mix of technologies,        with high-income but resource-poor regions shifting toward        advanced post fossil technologies (renewables in regions of        large land availability, nuclear in densely populated, resource        poor regions) and low-income resource-rich regions generally        relying on older fossil technologies.With substantial food        requirements, agricultural productivity is one of the main focus        areas for innovation and RD efforts in this future. Initially        high levels of soil erosion and water pollution are eventually        eased through the local development of more sustainable        high-yield agriculture.Although attention is given to potential        local and regional environmental damage, it is not uniform        across regions. For example, sulfur and particulate emissions        are reduced in Asia due to impacts on human health and        agricultural production but increase in Africa as a result of        the intensified exploitation of coal and other mineral        resources. The A2 world sees high energy and carbon intensity,        and correspondingly high GHG emissions. Its CO2 emissions are        the highest of all four scenario families.  Data are available        for the following periods:  1961-1990, 2010-2039, 2040-2069, and        2090-2099 Mean monthly and change fields.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>climate|global climate change|temperature</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2011-04-26T19:12:01Z</date
></data>