<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.32508</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Characterization of human disturbance regimes in southern Appalachia.</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Human disturbance is being characterized in the Blue Ridge District to determine its contribution to past and present landscape-level ecological processes in Southern Appalachia. Patterns of disturbance combined with observed social and economic changes in the region serve to forecast the likely future impact on terrestrial and aquatic resources. This is a unique opportunity to establish how the localized activities of individuals directed at the satisfaction of various kinds of needs and desires are guided by the knowledge, beliefs, and values shared with members of a social system and lead to particular outcomes in ecological processes. This overcomes the limitations associated with the driving forces commonly used to explain the human dimensions of global change: technology, socioeconomic organization, level of economic development, and culture. In so doing, it becomes possible to provide policy- makers with the time-and-place information needed for developing targeted, rather than generalized, instruments to respond to projected future conditions.Mail survey of Chambers of Commerce from 65 counties in Georgia, North Carolina, South Carolina, Tennessee, and Virginia. | Compilation of social and economic information for 65 counties in Georgia, North Carolina, South Carolina, Tennessee, and Virginia from National Census records. | Compiling GIS coverages of vegetation cover, elevation, potential trout-bearingstreams, ownership, and cultural features (roads, trails, etc.) for 65 counties in Georgia, North Carolina, South Carolina, Tennessee, and Virginia. | Personal interviews with long term and recent migrant residents of the region.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Coweeta|LTER|human disturbance|socioeconomic drivers|beliefs|values|development</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2011-04-27T04:10:33Z</date
></data>