<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.15053</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Distribution of barrier island overwash disturbance</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Fahrig, L., B. Hayden and R. Dolan 1993. Distribution of barrier island plants in relation to overwash disturbance: A test of life history theory. J. Coastal Research. 9(2):403-412. From lfahrig@ccs.carleton.ca Thu Jun 11 10:22:56 1992I am sending a file that is actually a SAS program for reading in the dataset that I used in the calculations. The columns are:map: base map number (i.e., the map number that Dolan/Hayden used for their rectangular blocks of coastline)trans: transect number from south to north for that mapThe remaining columns refer to a point on the transect at which there is a transition between vegetation communities (as defined by McCaffrey and digitized by LTER):utm1: first utm co-ord for transition pointutm2: second utm co-ord for transition pointunit: unit number for the vegetation community type that we are moving INTO. We are moving along the transect from the sea side to the mainland side of the island. The unit numbers are the numbers that you used when digitizing the map. For example, note that the first observation for every transect has unit number 7 since this is the number for sand.Editors note: Vegetation unit number refers to the mapping units used by McCaffrey, C.A. and R.D. Dueser. 1990. Plant associations on the Virginia Barrier Islands. Virginia Journal of Science 41(4A):282-299. The digital versions of the vegetation maps are also available on the VCR LTER information server.Unit numbers are listed below along with the corresponding vegetation class.GRID-CODE VEG_CODE VEG_CLASS      0        w        Water/background      1        A        Foredune Grassland      2        G        Dense Grassland      3        AG       Beachgrass Dunes/ Dense Grassland Dunes      4        g        Sparse Grassland      5        Ag       Foredune - Sparse Grassland Complex      6        At       Open Dunes - Thicket Complex      7        B        Beach      8        T        Tall Thicket      9        AT       Open Dunes - Thicket Complex     10        t        Low Thicket     11        J        Juniper Thicket     12        P        Pine Forest     13        H        Hardwood Forest     14        PH       Pine-Hardwood Forest Complex     15        m        Low Salt Marsh     16        Mm       Upper Low Salt Marsh     17        M        Brackish Marsh     18        s        Salt Flat     19        F        Fresh Marsh     20        w        Open Water     21        dr       Drift     22        b        Submerged Sand     23        uw       Underwater Flora (or Fauna)     24        peat     "Peat" Outcrops     25        wf       Wash Flat     26        mf       Mud Flat dist: distance along the transect (from the sea) in m for that transition pointprob: index of disturbance probability at that point (method of calculation in the ms)</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Disturbance|Biodiversity|Disturbance|Erosion</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>1997-12-31</date
></data>