<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.20690</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Streamflow and Stream Chemistry - Longitudinal Sites Along The Gwynns Falls - Location, Photographs, Equipment - Boundary Station 4. Gwynns Falls at Route 1/Carroll Park. BES ID 533-</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Participants Gary Fisher, U.S. Geological Survey (oversees stream flow monitoring) Ed Doheny, U.S. Geological Survey (oversees stream flow monitoring) Ken Belt, U.S. Forest Service (oversees weekly station checks) I. Collection of Flow Data at USGS Stream Gage Stations BES stream chemistry samples are collected at gaging stations built and maintained by the U.S Geological Survey and which are funded mainly by LTER funds. However a number of the stations are funded by other sources, including the USGS, Maryland Department of the Environment, Baltimore County DEPRM, and Baltimore City DPW. Stage at each gage site is measured to about 0.01 ft accuracy and is recorded at 15 minute (or shorter) intervals using either a float gage or pressure transducer. These stage records are converted to flow records using stage-discharge relationships (see below). Crest-stage recorders (floating cork gages) indicate high water marks and provide a backup source of high water in case recording gages are compromised in flooding conditions. Stilling wells are installed at each site, either in the channel or via piping to the channel, to provide quiescent locations for sensing of stage. General Approach to Discharge Measurement and Flow Ratings In a measurement of discharge (volumetric flow per unit time), a number of velocity measurements are taken across a transect located near the gage using a wading rod and propeller current meter (usually a mini (pygmy) velocity meter). Velocities (ft/sec) for each sub section are multiplied by their respective sub section areas (sq. ft.) and these discharges (cubic feet per second) are then summed to get a total discharge measurement for the section. Generally, an attempt is made to include enough velocity measurements across the transect such that no more than 10 % of the total discharge is contained in each sub section, although this may not be achievable for higher flows. Each total discharge measurement, along with the concurrent stage reading constitutes a point on a stage-discharge rating curve. Over time, discharge measurements are obtained for a range of stages so that a complete, accurate and current stage-discharge rating curve (graph) can be constructed. USGS field crews visit all sites about every six weeks to download data, check and calibrate equipment, and to do a low flow discharge measurements to check the stage-discharge rating for shifts, and to observe the channel section for potential changes in the high flow rating. A single USGS hydrologist is assigned to the BES stations to provide continuity and to maximize familiarity with the stations. These USGS visits are augmented by weekly visits by BES field crews who do a number of checks under the guidance of a Forest Service Hydrologist (see below, II. Stream Gage calibration &amp; Flow Rating QAQC: Weekly Checks). High flow velocities cannot be measured in-stream, and are metered by USGS crews from bridges near the gaging station. Discharge measurements during runoff events are repeatedly conducted until the high flow portion of the rating is defined. Extremely high flow discharges that cannot be measured are estimated by a slope area curve method using cross section geometry, channel roughness and surveyed elevations of high points of the hydraulic grade line indicated by debris left by the receding limb of the hydrograph. Data are recorded at 15 minute intervals at the larger watersheds and at 5 minute intervals at small watersheds. Records are downloaded electronically and processed at the USGS office where adjustments are made for calibration problems, backwater corrections (due to debris and ice buildup), missing records, shifts in the rating, etc. Small changes in the low flow portion of the stage-discharge rating are handled using</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Baltimore|MD|Washington|D.C|Chesapeake Bay|Baltimore-Washington|Maryland</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2003-01-01</date
></data>