<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.18356</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>IPCC Climate Change Data:  NIES99 B2a Model: 2080 Radiation</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>The model used here is a coupled ocean-atmosphere model that        consists of the CCSR/NIES atmospheric GCM, the CCSR ocean GCM, a        thermodynamic sea-ice model, and a river routing model        (Abe-Ouchi et al., 1996). The spatial resolution is T21 spectral        truncation (roughly 5.6 degrees  latitude/longitude) and 20        vertical levels for the atmospheric part, and roughly 2.8        degrees  horizontal grid and 17 vertical levels for the oceanic        part. Flux adjustment for atmosphere-ocean heat and water        exchange is applied to prevent a drift of the modelled climate.        The atmospheric model adopts a radiation scheme based on the        k-distribution, two-stream discrete ordinate method (DOM)        (Nakajima and Tanaka, 1986). This scheme can deal with        absorption, emission and scattering by gases, clouds and aerosol        particles in a consistent manner. In the calculation of sulphate        aerosol optical properties, the volumetric mode radius of the        sulphate particle in dry environment is assumed to be 0.2        micron. The hygroscopic growth of the sulphate is considered by        an empirical fit of d'Almeida et al. (1991). The vertical        distribution of the sulphate aerosol is assumed to be constant        in the lowest 2 km of the atmosphere. The concentrations of        greenhouse gases are represented by equivalent-CO2.  Three        integrations are made for 200 model years (1890-2090). In the        control experiment (CTL), the globally uniform concentration of        greenhouse gases is kept constant at 345 ppmv CO2-equivalent and        the concentration of sulphate is set to zero. In the experiment        GG, the concentration of greenhouse gases is gradually        increased, while that of sulphate is set to zero. In the        experiments GS, the increase in anthropogenic sulphate as well        as that in greenhouse gases is given and the aerosol scattering        (the direct effect of aerosol) is explicitly represented in the        way described above. The indirect effect of aerosol is not        included in any experiment.  The scenario of atmospheric        concentrations of greenhouse gases and sulphate aerosols is        given in accordance with Mitchell and Johns (1997). The increase        in greenhouse gases is based on the historical record from 1890        to 1990 and is increased by 1 percent / yr (compound) after        1990. For sulphate aerosols, geographical distributions of        sulphate loading for 1986 and 2050, which are estimated by a        sulphur cycle model (Langer and Rodhe, 1991), are used as basic        patterns. Based on global and annual mean sulphur emission        rates, the 1986 pattern is scaled for years before 1990, the        2050 pattern is scaled for years after 2050, and the pattern is        interpolated from the two basic ones for intermediate years to        give the time series of the distribution. The sulphur emission        rate in the future is based on the IPCC IS92a scenario. The        sulphate concentration is offset in our run so that it starts        from zero at 1890. The seasonal variation of sulphate        concentration is ignored.  Discussion on the results of the        experiments will be found in Emori et al. (1999). Climate        sensitivity of the CCSR/NIES model derived by equilibrium runs        is estimated to be 3.5 degrees Celsius. Global-Mean Temperature,        Precipitation and CO2 Changes (w.r.t. 1961-90) for the CCSR/NIES model.Like B1, the B2 world is one of increased concern for        environmental and social sustainability, but the character of        this world differs substantially.  Education and welfare        programs are widely pursued leading to reductions in mortality        and, to a lesser extent, fertility. The population reaches about        10 billion people by 2100, consistent with both the United        Nations and IIASA median projections. Income per capita grows at        an intermediary rate to reach about US$12,000 by 2050. By 2100        the global economy might expand to reach some US$250 trillion.        International income differences decrease, although not as        rapidly as in scenarios of higher global convergence (A1, B1).        Local inequity is reduced considerably through the development        of stronger community support networks.  Generally high        educational levels promote both development and environmental        protection. Indeed, environmental protection is one of the few        remaining truly international priorities. However, strategies to        address global environmental challenges are less successful than        in B1, as governments have difficulty designing and implementing        agreements that combine environmental protection with mutual        economic benefits.  The B2 storyline presents a particularly        favorable climate for community initiative and social        innovation, especially in view of high educational levels.        Technological frontiers are pushed less than in A1 and B1 and        innovations are also regionally more heterogeneous. Globally,        investment in R and D continues its current declining trend, and        mechanisms for international diffusion of technology and        know-how remain weaker than in scenarios A1 and B1 (but higher        than in scenario A2). Some regions with rapid economic        development and limited natural resources place particular        emphasis on technology development and bilateral co-operation.        Technical change is therefore uneven. The energy intensity of        GDP declines at about one percent per year, in line with the        average historical experience of the last two centuries.        Land-use management becomes better integrated at the local level        in the B2 world. Urban and transport infrastructure is a        particular focus of community innovation, contributing to a low        level of car dependence and less urban sprawl. An emphasis on        food self-reliance contributes to a shift in dietary patterns        towards local products, with reduced meat consumption in        countries with high population densities.  Energy systems differ        from region to region, depending on the availability of natural        resources. The need to use energy and other resources more        efficiently spurs the development of less carbon-intensive        technology in some regions. Environment policy cooperation at        the regional level leads to success in the management of some        transboundary environmental problems, such as acidification due        to SO2, especially to sustain regional self-reliance in        agricultural production. Regional cooperation also results in        lower emissions of NOx and VOCs, reducing the incidence of        elevated tropospheric ozone levels. Although globally the energy        system remains predominantly hydrocarbon-based to 2100, there is        a gradual transition away from the current share of fossil        resources in world energy supply, with a corresponding reduction        in carbon intensity.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>climate|global climate change|radiation</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2011-04-26T18:01:11Z</date
></data>