<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.28773</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Sevilleta LTER Meteorology Data, 1994</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge LTER Weather Data:    1 January 1994 - 31 Dec. 1994 This file contains the weather data for a network of 9 permanent weather stations on the Sevilleta Wildlife area, Langmuir Labs, and Bosque Del ApacheWildlife area for the year 1994. Station 40 has been in operation since the middle of 1987,  Stations 41-44  were installed in the early part of 1989, Station 45 was put into operation on 26 Jan 1990 (hour 15), Station 46 was put into operation on 31 Aug 1990 (hour 17), Station 47 was put into operationon 08 Jan 1991 (hour 16), and Station 1 was put into test operation on29 Dec 1991 (hr 12) and official data recording started on 01 Jan 93 (hr 01).The geographic locations of the various weather stations are as follows:                             40 = Deep Well Site: Lat 34.3556, Long -106.6914                             41 = South Gate Site:    34.2177,      -106.7958                             42 = Cerro Montosa Site: 34.3692,      -106.5341                             43 = Watersheds Site:    34.3892,      -107.0398                             44 = Rio Salado Site:    34.3489,      -106.8802                             45 = Bronco Well Site:   34.4068,      -106.9328                             46 = Langmuir Site:      33.97472      -107.1808                             47 = Bosque Del Apache:  **.****,      ****.****                             01 = Headquarters:       34.3550       -106.8847Note that Stations 40, 45, 46, and 1 are the only stations that collect data onsolar radiation.  Station 1 is the only station collecting evaporation, evappan water temperature, and barometric pressure data.  Also note that Station 47 is situated in a small clearing containing Salt Cedar within aCottonwood canopy.  The data were recorded and stored by a Campbell Scientific CR10 Datalogger.Samples were taken every "n" seconds and values averaged for the hour (where n = 3 seconds for wind speed, wind direction, and solar radiationvariables,  n = 30 seconds for rh, air temperature, soil temperature, andmixing ratio variables,  n = 300 seconds for soil moisture variables).Numbers were stored and processed in the datalogger in binary format with23 bit precision. Final output was rounded to a maximum of 3 decimal digits.The following variable description section provides detailed information on variables collected, units of measurement, and the format of the data section.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>meteorology|precipitation|temperature|SEV|LTER|weather</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>1994</date
></data>