<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.28509</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Long-Term Nitrogen Deposition: Effects on Succession Following Major Disturbances. Year 1984 Percent light penetration</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>The purpose of this experiment is to measure how initially disturbing an area and adding nitrogen over a long time will affect the number of species, the type of species present, the amount of annual growth, and the change from year to year in the growth of each species in a plant community which is also relieved of grazing by large and small mammals. This experiment is conducted within fields (A, B, and C) which were initially low in soil nutrients. The ground was disturbed by thoroughly disking the area prior to establishment of the experiment. There are 8 different levels of nitrogen addition with other nutrients added to ensure that nitrogen remains the limiting nutrient, and a control which receives no nutrients. Nitrogen fertilizer (NH4NO3) is applied twice per year, once in early May and once in late June. There are six replicates of each treatment per field. The treatments were randomly assigned to plots of size 4 by 4 meters. The plots are in 6 plot by 9 plot grids with 1 meter aisles between plots. The plot grids are enclosed by a fence to keep out mammalian herbivores. Gophers are trapped and removed as they appear. In the spring of 1992, subexperiments E097 and E098 were established. E097 is in fields A and C where randomly selected plots within each treatment no longer receive fertilizer. E098 is in field B where randomly selected plots within each treatment are burned. Note that the design of E002 is similar to E001 except E002 was thoroughly disked prior to establishment.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Cedar Creek Natural History Area|Long Term|Ecology|Successional dynamics|Primary Productivity|Disturbance Patterns|Nutrient Budgets|Nutrient Cycles|Climatic Variation|Biodiversity|Ecosystem functioning|Nitrogen limitation|Fire Frequency|Plant Competition</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>1986</date
></data>