<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.26686</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Carpinteria Salt Marsh Reserve Annual Report</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>The following are descriptions of some of the research projects that are being conducted by the users of Carpinteria Salt Marsh Reserve:               BIVALVE MOLLUSKS          Dr. Mark Page     MSI/Biological Sciences     UC Santa Barbara          Bivalve mollusks constitute one of the important marine zoological resources of Carpinteria Salt Marsh Reserve. Dr. Page's study is aimed at (1) determining the life histories of the most abundant species, (2) elucidating relationships between bivalve distribution and abundance and the physical and biological characteristics of the environment, and (3) determining whether bivalve populations may be used to monitor the environmental quality of the salt marsh habitat. Differential rates of recruitment and mortality have contributed to temporal fluctuations in the population densities of Macoma nasuta and Protothaca staminea, while the population density of Tagelus californianu8 has remained relatively constant. The rates of recruitment of M. nasuta and P. staminea indicate that populations of these species would recover more quickly than those of T. californianus, following major disturbance. Participants in this study include Jenifer Dugan, who is a Ph.D. candidate of UCSB, undergraduate UCSB students Jens Sorensen, Mitch Byrd, and Jeanne McAdara, as well as David Hubbard, who graduated from UCSB with a B.A. This project has been funded by the Giles W. and Elise G. Mead Foundation and the Reserve Manager's Fund and mitigation funds from local developers.          Dr. Page is also conducting a water quality study at the marsh which has identified pollutants in the sediments of two tidal creeks. These pollutants could contaminate and affect the abundance of invertebrate species eaten by resident and migrating bird species. This study has been funded by the Reserve Manager's Fund.          *		*          Ms. Teresa Stevens     (Dr. A. Kuris)     Department of Biological Sciences     UC Santa Barbara          Ms. Stevens conducted graduate studies regarding the distribution, abundance and food web significance of two species of gastropod, Cerithidea californica and Melampus olivaceus, located at the Reserve. Populations of these two gastropod species may be threatened by a number of factors including loss of habitat due to flood control plans in Franklin Creek and the Apple Road areas, local development and land filling around the Reserve, and chemical contamination as a result of runoff from surrounding agricultural areas. Displacement or local extinction by steepening of creek channels or by contamination of these populations could have a significant impact on the other organisms in the marsh. Funding for this project was provided by the Reserve Manager's Fund.     Mr. Jack D. Linn     California Department of Fish</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>bivalve molluscs|gastropods|light footed clapper rail|belding&#213;s savannah sparrows</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2007-09-11</date
></data>