<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.73873</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Force Field Parameters</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>These are MD trajectories to accompany the paper: "Lipid Binding and Force Transduction in MscL: A Continuum-Molecular Approach" by Juan M. Vanegas and Marino Arroyo. PLoS ONE 2014. All trajectories were generated with GROMACS version 4.5.5 (www.gromacs.org). All trajectoories can be read and analyzed by the standard GROMACS utilities. Trajectories (.xtc) can also be visualized by common molecular graphics programs such as UCSF Chimera (http://www.cgl.ucsf.edu/chimera/) or VMD (http://www.ks.uiuc.edu/Research/vmd/). Topology files in text (.top) and binary (.tpr) form are included, as well as simulation parameters (.mdp). In some cases text files (.xvg) including coordinate information are also included. The file MscL_Equilibration.tar.gz contains the trajectory corresponding to the 500 ns equilibration period of the MscL Channel embedded in the POPE bilayer. The file Local_Stress_and_Traction.tar.gz contains the trajectories for the tensionless and tensioned simulations, as well as the files needed to visualize the traction on the surface of the protein. The stress tensor was calculated with a custom version of GROMACS (http://www.lacan.upc.edu/LocalStressFromMD) and the files can be visualized with the program ParaView. The file Arrhenius_Bell_unbinding.tar.gz contains the steered MD simulation trajectories used to estimate the strength of lipid binding to the MscL protein. The file Channel_Actuation.tar.gz contains the steered MD simulation trajectories used to actuate the MscL channel by pulling on protein-bound lipids. Finally, the file force_field_parameters.tar.gz contains the parameters used in all of the simulations. We used the G43A1-S3 lipid parameters in combination with the G54A7 protein parameters.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>MscL|mechanosensitive channel of large conductance|mechanosensation|force transduction|stress tensor|lateral pressure profiles|lipid binding|central force decomposition|traction</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2014-12-03T20:58:05Z</date
></data>