<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.68866</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Data from: Early treatment response in non-small cell lung cancer patients using diffusion-weighted imaging and functional diffusion maps - a feasibility study</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Objective: The aim of this study was to prospectively evaluate the feasibility of monitoring treatment response to chemotherapy in patients with non-small cell lung carcinoma using functional diffusion maps (fDMs). Materials and Methods: This study was approved by the Cantonal Research Ethics Committee and informed written consent was obtained from all patients. Nine patients (mean age = 66 years, range = 53&#8211;76 years, 5 females, 4 males) with overall 13 lesions were included. Imaging was performed within two weeks before initiation of chemotherapy and at one, two, and six weeks after initiation of chemotherapy. Imaging included a respiratory-triggered diffusion-weighted sequence including three b-factors (100, 600, and 800 s/mm2). Treatment response was defined by change in tumor diameter on computed tomography (CT) after two cycles of chemotherapy. Changes in the apparent diffusion coefficient (ADC) on a per-lesion basis and the percentages of voxel with significantly increased or decreased ADCs on fDMs were analyzed using repeated measures analysis of variance (ANOVA). Changes in tumor size were used as covariate to examine the ability of ADCs and fDM parameters to predict treatment response. Results: Repeated measures ANOVA revealed that the percentage of voxels with increased ADCs on fDMs (p = 0.002) as well as the mean ADC increase (p = 0.011) were significantly higher in good responders with a large reduction in tumor size on CT. Conclusion: Our results indicate that the percentage of voxels with significantly increased ADCs on fDMs seems to be a promising biomarker for early prediction of treatment response in patients with non-small cell lung carcinoma. Contrary to averaged values, this approach allows the spatial heterogeneity of treatment response to be resolved.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Diffusion-weighted imaging|Quantitative MRI|Biomarkers|Functional diffusion map|Non-small cell cancer|Lung cancer|Treatment response</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2014-10-17T19:00:05Z</date
></data>