<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.25237</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Urban Historical Boundaries, 1900 BES ID 204-</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Urban area boundaries for 1900, part of the Baltimore-Washington Spatial Dynamics and Human Impacts dataset. The Baltimore-Washington Spatial Dynamics and Human Impacts dataset is an integrated and flexible temporal urban land characteristics database for the Baltimore-Washington metropolitan area.  The compilation of this data is a collaborative effort led by the U.S. Geological Survey and the University of Maryland Baltimore County.  The database provides visual and historical perspective of the urban growth experienced in the area between 1792 and 1992.  Data on built-up areas exists as separate geographic layers for the dates: 1792, 1801, 1822, 1850, 1878, 1900, 1925, 1938, 1953, 1966, 1972, 1982, and 1992.  Temporal urban mapping reconstructs past landscapes by incorporating historic maps, census statistics, and commerce records to generate a progressive geo-referenced picture of the past changes in a region.  Contemporary mapping focuses on the use of remotely sensed data, existing digital land use data, digital census information, and a variety of earth science infrastructure data, such as Digital Line Graphs, Digital Elevation Models, and key ancillary demographic information. Different procedures were used for different time periods, more fully described for each file in the Process Step Section 2.5.2.  The resulting database of temporal urban land use/land cover and demographic changes provides an ideal source of test data and information for both urban geographers and global change research scientists. While this dataset was developed by the University of Maryland Baltimore County final quality control and metadata generation was performed by the University of Vermont's Spatial Analysis Lab.  Two significant problems were noted regarding this dataset.  The first anomoly is that the 1801, 1822, and 1878 layers have a much smaller extent, and contain data only for Baltimore City.  The second discrepancy is that there are also some very obvious positional errors causing misalignments between layers of different dates (i.e. urban areas become non-urban in a very short time period, an unlikely occurance).</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Baltimore|MD|Washington|D.C|Chesapeake Bay|Baltimore-Washington|Regional</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2009-12-31</date
></data>