<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.115785</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Interception data for "Corruption, development and governance indicators predict invasive species risk from trade"</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>This data file contains three sheets - "Vegetable Pathway", "Timber Pathway" and "Vehicle Pathway". 	Details on pathways are described in the ESM of the main manuscript.  		Governance indicator scores were obtained from the World Bank World Governance Indicators (WGI) database (www.govindicators.org)	Development indicator scores were obtained from the World Bank Development Indicators database (http://data.worldbank.org/indicator)	The meanings of the columns within each sheet are as follows:		Country:	Country of commodity originYear: 	Year in which interception of non-native species occurred Total trade:	Total trade in the selected pathway. Pathways are described in the ESM of the main manuscript.  Total detections:	Total detections in the defined pathway each yearG_voice:	Governance indicator of Voice and AccountabilityG_stability:	Governance indicator of Political Stability and Freedom from ViolenceG_effective:	Governance indicator of Government EffectivenssG_regulator:	Governance indicator of Regulatory QualityG_law:	Governance indicator of Rule of LawG_corruption:	Governance indicator of Control of CorruptionD_agri:	Development indicator of Agricultural land (% of land area)D_export:	Development indicator of Exports of goods and services (% of GDP)D_forest:	Development indicator of Forest area (% of forest area)D_GDP:	Development indicator of Gross domestic product	These Governance and Development indicator scores are further described in Table 1 of the main manuscript. 		Ministry for Primary Industries 	New Zealand's Ministry for Primary Industries provided  access to the data on an &#8216;as is&#8217; basis.  MPI does not warrant as to the quality, accuracy or completeness of the data.  MPI or any original data creator does not accept liability for any damages, whether direct or indirect, resulting from the use of the data. The data were obtained from the Data Analysis Team's (Analysis and Profiling Group, Border Standards Directorate, MAFBNZ) "Interception Database" and the MAF Quantum Database. Data includes only border interceptions.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Biological invasions|free trade|interception rates|governance|quarantine regulations</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2016-05-19T14:44:31Z</date
></data>