<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.89224</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Data from: Development of chloroplast genomic resources for Cynara</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>In this study, new chloroplast (cp) resources were developed for the genus Cynara, using whole cp genomes from 20 genotypes, by means of high-throughput sequencing technologies. Our target species included seven globe artichokes, two cultivated cardoons, eight wild artichokes, and three other wild Cynara species (C. baetica, C. cornigera, and C. syriaca). One complete cp genome was isolated using short reads from a whole genome sequencing project, while the others were obtained by means of long-range PCR, for which primer pairs are provided here. A de novo assembly strategy, combined with a reference based assembly allowed us to reconstruct each cp genome. Comparative analyses among the newly sequenced genotypes and two additional Cynara cp genomes (&#8220;Brindisino&#8221; artichoke and C. humilis) retrieved from public databases revealed 126 parsimony informative characters and 258 singletons in Cynara, for a total of 384 variable characters. Thirty-nine SSR loci and 34 other INDEL events were detected. After data analysis, 37 primer pairs for SSR amplification were designed, and these molecular markers were subsequently validated in our Cynara genotypes. Phylogenetic analysis based on all cp variable characters provided the best resolution when compared to what was observed using only parsimony informative characters, or only short &#8220;variable&#8221; cp regions. The evaluation of the molecular resources obtained from this study led us to support the &#8220;super-barcode&#8221; theory and consider the total cp sequence of Cynara as a reliable and valuable molecular marker for exploring species diversity and examining variation below the species level.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Agriculture|Angiosperms|DNA Barcoding|Genomics/Proteomics</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2015-08-18T14:01:40Z</date
></data>