<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.26633</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Coal Oil Point Natural Reserve Annual Report</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Applicant(s):	Richard F. Ambrose     Project Title:	Inventory of Rocky Intertidal Resources in Santa Barbara, Ventura, and Orange Counties     Institution(s): UC Los Angeles     Department(s): Department of Environmental Health Sciences     Project Dates: 1/98-6/00     Grant Info: Funding Agency: Minerals Management Service-Southern California Education Initiative     PI: Richard F. Ambrose     Award amount: $139,730     Award number: 4-445951-AB-57769     Award date: 1/1/98     Grant duration dates: 1/98-6/00     Grant title: Inventory of rocky intertidal resources in Santa Barbara, Ventura and Orange Counties          Applicant(s):	Jonathan Appelbaum     Project Title:	Preliminary Assessment of Anniella pulchra in Campus Lagoon Area     Institution(s): UC Santa Barbara     Department(s): Department of Ecology, Evolution, and Marine Biology     Project Dates: 3/01     Funding: Self-funded          Applicant(s):	Michael Arntz     Project Title: Landscape Images of the UCSB Natural Reserve System     Institution(s): UC Santa Barbara     Department(s): Art Studio     Project Dates: 1999-2001     Grant Info: Funding: Self-funded.     PI: Michael Arntz     Affiliation: Art Studio Department, UC Santa Barbara     Title: Landscape images of the Natural Reserve System          Applicant(s):	Jim Baldwin, Steve Nadler, Dan Bumbarger     Project Title: Systematics and diversity of free-living nematodes in the family Cephalobidae     Institution(s): UC Riverside     Department(s): Department of Nematology     Project Dates: 11/00 - 11/01     PI: Jim Baldwin, Department of Nematology, UC Riverside     Funding agency: National Science Foundation     Award amount: $740,000     Project duration dates: 9/97- 10/02     Grant number: 9712355     Grant title: FEET: Clasical and molecular-based monographic revision of Cephalobina: integrating databases and training in microbivore, plant and animal nematology          Applicant(s):	Jonathan Blythe     Project Title:	Variable Parasitism in Mytilus californianus as a Bioindicator     Institution(s): UC Santa Barbara     Department(s): Department of Ecology. Evolution, and Marine Biology     Project Dates: 2/01 -4/01     Funding: Grant proposal has been submitted          Applicant(s):	Cheryl J. Briggs     Project Title: The Influence of Seasonality on Parisitoid Coexistence and Host Abundance     Institution(s): UC Berkeley     Department(s): Integrative Biology     Project Dates: 8/00-8/01     Funding agency: United States Department of Agriculture     PI: Cheryl J. Briggs     Award amount: 165,000     Award number: NRICGP 98-35302-6880     Award date: 12/98     Grant duration dates: 12/98- 12/00     Grant title: Parasitoid diversity: effects of competition and seasonality in host suppression     Funding agency: National Science Foundation     PI: Cheryl J. Briggs     Award amount: 294,878     Award number: DEB-9806635     Award date: 9/98     Grant duration dates: 9/98 - 3/01     Grant title: The effects of dispersal on the population dynamics and parasitoid diversity of a multiparasitoid-host system          Applicant(s):	Shelly Cole     Project Title:	Relating Structure to Function: The Physiological and Ecological Role of Plant     Structure in Coastal Species     Institution(s): UC Santa Barbara     Department(s): Department of Ecology, Evolution, and Marine Biology     Project Dates: 11/99-5/01     Funding agency: Self-Funded          Applicant(s):	Jenifer Dugan     Project Title: Factors Affecting Sandy Beach Use by Shorebirds     Institution(s): UC Santa Barbara     Department(s): Marine Science Institute and Department of Ecology, Evolution, and Marine Biology     Project Dates: 10/98 - 12/01     Funding agency: Minerals Management Service     PI: J. E. Dugan, A. M. Wenner     Award amount: $210,000     Award date: 10/98     Grant duration dates: 10/98-12/01     Grant title: Factors Affecting Sandy Beach Use by Shorebirds in the Santa Maria Basin and Vicinity          Applicant(s):	Jenifer Dugan     Project Title:	Deveraux Slough Pilot Water Quality Study     Institution(s): UC Santa Barbara     Department(s): Marine Science Institute and Department of Ecology, Evolution, and Marine Biology     Project Dates: 10/99 - 10/00     Grant Info: Funding agency: Office of Budget and Planning, UC Santa Barbara     PI: Jenifer Dugan and Henry Page     Award amount: $5,600     Award number:     Award date: 10/99     Grant duration dates: 10/99-10/00     Grant title: Deveraux Slough Pilot Water Quality Study          Applicant(s):	John E. Estes     Project Title:	Extent and Nature of Oil Seeps at Coal Oil Point     Institution(s): UC Santa Barbara     Department(s): Department of Geography     Project Dates: 1/70-6/01     PI: John Estes     Affiliation: Department of Geography, UCSB     Funding agency: Self-funded     Title: Extent and Nature of Oil Seeps at Coal Oil Point     Project duration dates: 1/70-12/00          Applicant(s):	John Galetzka, Kenneth Hudnut, Yehudna Bock, Frank Webb, William Young     Project Title:	The Southern California Integrated GPS Network: Coal OH Point Continuous GPS Station     Institution(s):	US Geological Survey     Project Dates: 4/00-4/05     Funding agency: Self-funded          Applicant(s):	Jeffrey Goddard, Carol Blanchette, Carol Thornber     Project Title:	Safeguarding Intertidal Biodiversity: Removal of an Invasive Seaweed at Coal Oil Point Natural Reserve and Alegria Beach     Institution(s): UC Santa Barbara     Department(s): Marine Science Institute     Project Dates: 6/01 -6/03     Funding Agency: Self-funded          Applicant(s):	Robert Hansen     Project Title:	Monitoring Birds on Coal Oil Point Reserve     Funding: Self-funded          Applicant(s):	Mark Holmgren     Project Title: Vertebrate Monitoring     Institution(s): UC Santa Barbara     Department(s): Department Ecology, Evolution, and Marine Biology     Project Dates: 7/97 - ongoing     Funding: Self-funded          Applicant(s):	Karl S. Kellogg, Richard Stanley, Scott Minor     Project Title: Southern California aerial mapping project     Institution(s): U. S. Geological Survey (U.S.G.S.)     Department(s): Geologic Division     Project Dates: 6/01 -9/03     PI: Dr. Karl S. Kellogg, U.S. Geological Survey, Denver, Colorado     PI: Richard Stanley, U.S. Geological Survey, Menlo Park, California     PI: Mr. Scott Minor, U.S. Geological Survey, Denver, Colorado     Funding Agency: U.S. Geological Survey     Award Amount: $4,000,000 (overall project, this is a subportion of the overall project)     Award Date: 10/99     Grant Duration Dates: 10/99 - 9/03     Grant Title: Southern California aerial mapping project          Applicant(s):	Kevin Lafferty     Project Title:	Disturbance of Wintering Snowy Plovers at Coal Oil Point and Other Pacific Coast Populations     Institution(s): UC Santa Barbara</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Anniella pulchra|Near-Surface Currents|Snowy Plover|Mytilus californianus</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2007-09-11</date
></data>