<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.135507</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Data from: Hepatitis B vaccination coverage, knowledge and sociodemographic determinants of uptake in high risk public safety workers in Kaduna State, Nigeria: a cross sectional survey</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Objectives: To estimate hepatitis B vaccination (HBVc) coverage, and knowledge and socio-demographic determinants of full-dose uptake in Federal Road Safety Corps (FRSC) members, Kaduna State, Nigeria in order to inform relevant targeted vaccination policies. Design: A cross-sectional survey of FRSC members, Kaduna Sector Command. Settings: Six randomly-selected Unit Commands under Kaduna Sector Command, Kaduna State, Nigeria. Participants: Pilot-tested structured self-administered questionnaire was administered to 341 participants aged 18 years and above with &#8805;6 months of service between 17th June and 22nd July, 2015. Excluded were FRSC members in Road Safety (RS) 1 Zonal Command headquarters as the Zonal Command includes other States beyond the study scope. Primary Outcome: HBVc status of participants categorized as &#8216;not vaccinated&#8217; for uptake of &lt;3 doses and &#8216;vaccinated&#8217; for uptake of &#8805;3 doses. Analysis: Descriptive analysis estimated HBVc coverage while logistic regression ascertained associations. Results: Most participants were males, aged 30-39 years, with 3-10 years of service, and of Marshal cadre. HBVc coverage was 60.9% for &#8805;1 dose and 30.5% for &#8805;3 doses. Less than 47% of participants scored above the mean knowledge score for hepatitis B virus (HBV) and HBVc. Female sex (AOR 2.28, 95% CI 1.15-4.52, p&lt;0.05), perceiving there to be an occupational risk of exposure to HBV (AOR 2.86, 95% CI 1.06-7.70, p&lt;0.001), and increasing HBVc knowledge (AOR 2.68, 95% CI 1.83-3.92, p&lt;0.001) were independent predictors of full-dose HBVc in FRSC members, Kaduna Sector Command. Conclusions: HBVc coverage and knowledge are poor among FRSC members, Kaduna Sector Command. Educational intervention, geared towards improving FRSC members&#8217; knowledge of HBVc and perception of risk of occupational exposure to HBV, is recommended for these vulnerable public safety workers. Such enlightenment could be a cheap and easy way of improving HBVc coverage in the study population.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Infection control|Hepatitis B virus|Vaccination coverage|Public safety workers</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2017-04-07T14:08:53Z</date
></data>