<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.10989</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Bird predation, grasshopper dynamics, and plant structure. Year 1990 Aboveground biomass data</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>This experiment was set up in the same macroplots at Field B E004 that were used in E060.  Pairs of 9 m x 9 m plotswere demarcated.  Oneplot in each pair was randomly assigned to exclude birds (BEX) and the otherto allow birds to forage for grasshoppers in the vegetation (BAL).  A framewas built around BEX plots with wooden posts at each corner and heavy aluminumwire stretched between posts 1m above the ground.  Bird netting (2.5 cm mesh)was then stretched over this framework and attached to the ground withnumerous wire stakes. In 1989, these plots were set up 15 July, but were setup 15 May in 1990 to examine the effects of predation in the early summer.Between 15-25 August, netting was removed and grasshoppers were sampled withinboth BEX and BAL plots and stored in 70% ethanol for later identification tospecies or genus, counting and weighing. Grasshoppers were sampled by twopeople with butterfly nets. After the grasshoppers were sampled, thevegetation was sampled. Within each 9 m x 9 m plot, three 0.1 m x 3 m stripswere clipped, sorted to species, dried and weighed.  In 1990, the exclosureswere set up 15 May, but all vegetation and grasshopper sampling was similar tothat in 1989.  For a list of treatments, see the treatment layouts in file&lt;A HREF="http://www.cedarcreek.umn.edu/research/exper/e061/treatment.html"&gt;trmte61&lt;/A&gt;. On May 5,1995, a wildfire burned all of the plots in experiment 61 in fieldB.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Cedar Creek Natural History Area|Long Term|Ecology|Successional dynamics|Primary Productivity|Disturbance Patterns|Nutrient Budgets|Nutrient Cycles|Climatic Variation|Biodiversity|Ecosystem functioning|Nitrogen limitation|Fire Frequency|Plant Competition|SCHIZACHYRIUM SCOPARIUM|POA PRATENSIS|CYPERUS SP.|AGROPYRON REPENS|SETARIA LUTESCENS (GLAUCA)|CAREX SP.|PANICUM CAPILLARE|PANICUM OLIGOSANTHES|AMBROSIA ARTEMISIIFOLIA ELATIO|SOLIDAGO NEMORALIS|SOLIDAGO RIGIDA|LESPEDEZA CAPITATA|POLYGALA POLYGAMA|POLYGONUM CONVOLVULUS|ANTENNARIA NEGLECTA|ARISTIDA BASIRAMEA|POLYGONUM TENUE|VICIA VILLOSA|PANICUM PRAECOCIOUS|VIOLA PEDATIFIDA|MOLLUGO VERTICILLATA|CHENOPODIUM ALBUM|HIERACIUM LONGIPILUM|ACHILLEA MILLEFOLIUM(LANULOSA)|EUPHORBIA COROLLATA|PANICUM PERLONGUM|ERAGROSTIS SPECTABILIS|ANEMONE CYLINDRICA</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>1992</date
></data>