<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.37640</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Aubret 53172</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Excel file contains 4 sheets. First sheet titled Adult Tiger snakes contains field data collected on Adult Tiger snakes (sex, body mass and snout-vent length). Sheet titled Mothers litters and neonates contains laboratory and museum data about reproductive output in female tiger snakes for several populations. For each female is given birth date, mean litter body mass (calculated average body mass for all neonates in a given litter), mean litter svl (calculated average snout vent length for all neonates in a given litter), and mean litter jaw (calculated average jaw length for all neonates in a given litter). Sheet titled Prey contains data collected in Museum collection for prey available at each study site. Latin names are given with body mass and maximum circumference of each prey item. Sheet titled Growth experiment contains experimental data on growth rate and food consumption in neonate Tiger snakes from several populations. Headings indicate for each mother its population of origin, neonate identification number, birth date and morphometrics at birth. Body mass and snout vent length are recorded every two months until the end of the experiment. Column titled Total growth in body mass indicates the difference in body mass between the start and the end of the experiment. The two last columns are Total food (total amount of food consumed by each neonate over the course of the experiment) and Length of experiment (total duration of the experiment). Conversion rates were calculated (column titled Increase in body mass per g of food) and daily growth rates in body mass (increase in body mass in mg per day).  Similar calculation were made for snout vent length (increase in svl per g of food, increase in svl in mm per day).</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Body size|island|snake|biogeography</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2012-02-01T17:40:24Z</date
></data>