<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.19117</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>IPCC Climate Change Data: HADCM3 B2a Model: 2020 Maximum Temperature</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>The recent experiments performed at the Hadley Centre have        used the new Unified Model (Cullen, 1993). These experiments        represent a large step forward in the way climate change is        modelled by GCMs and raises new possibilities for scenario        construction. This experiment has overcome some of the major        difficulties that were associated with the previous generations        of equilibrium (circa IPCC 1990) and cold-start transient (circa        IPCC 1992) climate change experiments.  HadCM2 has a spatial        resolution of 2.5 degrees x 3.75 degrees (latitude by longitude)        and the representation produces a grid box resolution of 96 x 73        grid cells. This produces a surface spatial resolution of about        417km x 278 km reducing to 295 x 278km at 45 degrees North and        South (comparable to a spectral resolution of T42).  The        equilibrium climate sensitivity (DT2x) of HadCM2, that is the        global-mean temperature response to a doubling of effective CO2        concentration, is approximately 2.5 degrees C, although, this        quantity varies with the time-scale considered. This is somewhat        lower than most other GCMs (IPCC, 1992). In order to undertake a        'warm-start' experiment it is necessary to perturb the model        with a forcing from an early historical era, when the radiative        forcing was relatively small compared to the present. The Hadley        Centre started their experiments performed with HadCM2 with        forcing from the middle industrial era, about 1860 Mitchell et        al., 1995 and Johns et al., 1995.  The greenhouse gas only        integrations, HadCM2GG, used the combined forcing of all the        greenhouse gases as an equivalent CO2 concentration. A further        series of integrations, HadCM2GS, used the combined equivalent        CO2 concentration plus the negative forcing from sulphate        aerosols. The HadCM2GG integrations simulated the change in        forcing of the climate system by greenhouse gases since the        early industrial period (taken by HadCM2 to be 1860). The        addition of the negative forcing effects of sulphate aerosols        represents the direct radiative forcing due to anthropogenic        sulphate aerosols by means of an increase in clear-sky surface        albedo proportional to the local sulphate loading (refer to        Mitchell et al., 1995 for details of this method). The indirect        effects of aerosols were not simulated.  The modelled control        climate shows a negligible long term trend in surface air        temperature over the first 400 years. The trend is about +0.04        degrees C per century, which is comparable to other such        experiments.  HadCM2CON represents an improvement over previous        generations of GCMs that have been used at the Hadley Centre        (Johns et al., 1995 and Airey et al., 1995).  The experiments        performed have simulated the observed climate system using        estimated forcing perturbations since 1860. Johns et al., (1995)        and Mitchell et al., (1995) have established that HadCM2's        sensitivity is consistent with the real climate system. The        agreement between the observed global-mean temperature record        and that produced in these experiments is better for HadCM2GS        than for HadCM2GG. This implies that HadCM2Gs has captured the        observed signal of global-mean temperature changes better than        HadCM2GG for the recent 100-year record.  The climate        sensitivity of HadCM2 is about 2.5 degrees CLike B1, the B2 world is one of increased concern for        environmental and social sustainability, but the character of        this world differs substantially.  Education and welfare        programs are widely pursued leading to reductions in mortality        and, to a lesser extent, fertility. The population reaches about        10 billion people by 2100, consistent with both the United        Nations and IIASA median projections. Income per capita grows at        an intermediary rate to reach about US$12,000 by 2050. By 2100        the global economy might expand to reach some US$250 trillion.        International income differences decrease, although not as        rapidly as in scenarios of higher global convergence (A1, B1).        Local inequity is reduced considerably through the development        of stronger community support networks.  Generally high        educational levels promote both development and environmental        protection. Indeed, environmental protection is one of the few        remaining truly international priorities. However, strategies to        address global environmental challenges are less successful than        in B1, as governments have difficulty designing and implementing        agreements that combine environmental protection with mutual        economic benefits.  The B2 storyline presents a particularly        favorable climate for community initiative and social        innovation, especially in view of high educational levels.        Technological frontiers are pushed less than in A1 and B1 and        innovations are also regionally more heterogeneous. Globally,        investment in R and D continues its current declining trend, and        mechanisms for international diffusion of technology and        know-how remain weaker than in scenarios A1 and B1 (but higher        than in scenario A2). Some regions with rapid economic        development and limited natural resources place particular        emphasis on technology development and bilateral co-operation.        Technical change is therefore uneven. The energy intensity of        GDP declines at about one percent per year, in line with the        average historical experience of the last two centuries.        Land-use management becomes better integrated at the local level        in the B2 world. Urban and transport infrastructure is a        particular focus of community innovation, contributing to a low        level of car dependence and less urban sprawl. An emphasis on        food self-reliance contributes to a shift in dietary patterns        towards local products, with reduced meat consumption in        countries with high population densities.  Energy systems differ        from region to region, depending on the availability of natural        resources. The need to use energy and other resources more        efficiently spurs the development of less carbon-intensive        technology in some regions. Environment policy cooperation at        the regional level leads to success in the management of some        transboundary environmental problems, such as acidification due        to SO2, especially to sustain regional self-reliance in        agricultural production. Regional cooperation also results in        lower emissions of NOx and VOCs, reducing the incidence of        elevated tropospheric ozone levels. Although globally the energy        system remains predominantly hydrocarbon-based to 2100, there is        a gradual transition away from the current share of fossil        resources in world energy supply, with a corresponding reduction        in carbon intensity.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>climate|global climate change|temperature</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2011-04-26T18:30:02Z</date
></data>