<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.24380</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Coweeta climate.</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>This dataset contains base-line climatic information for the main climate station (CS01) at Coweeta Hydrologic Laboratory in Macon County, North Carolina, USA. The station is operated by the Southern Research Station, Forest Service, USDA. CS01 is also a cooperative station with the National Weather Service. Since May 1963 it has been located in a grassy field NW of the junction of Ball Creek and Shope Fork of Coweeta Creek. Previously CS01 was located about 100m SW of its current location. The current elevation is 685.5m (2249ft) at latitude 35-3-37.21N and longitude 83-25-49.02W. During the 1940s forest regrowth was tolerated up to 150 feet from the station. In August 1949 the larger opening was reestablished. The high elevation precipitation gage is located in a forest opening on Mooney Gap at elevation 1362.6m (4475ft).Observations were made twice a day at 0800 and 1700 through 1957. Beginning in 1958 observations were made at 0900 eastern standard time only. Since March 1968 observations have been made at 0800 EST. All observations of air temperature are made with Hg thermometers and are currently backed up by both replicating chart recorders and electronic data logger observations. Daily maximum temperature observations are recorded as the previous days maximum temperature. When direct observations are not made on holidays and weekends, values are extracted from the chart recorder. Precipitation at CS01 is observed daily whereas precipitation at the high elevation site is observed weekly. Week long totals and weekend/holiday totals are separated into daily amounts using adjacent weighing/recording raingages. Global solarradiation began in July 1960. Radiation is sensed by an Eppley Pyrheliometer and recorded on a Campbell data logger. Some evaporation measurements at CS01 have been made using National Weather Service class A type pans. However, data reported here are derived from a buried pan 36 inches in diameter and 18 inches deep, providing a more representative climatic norm for evaporation.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Coweeta|LTER|Climate|air temperature|max air temperature|minimum air temperature|low elevation precipitation|global solar radiation|high elevation precipitation|evaporation</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2011-04-26T22:01:16Z</date
></data>