<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.24468</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Habitat suitability and the distribution of species.</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Metapopulation theory posits that suitable habitat may recently beunoccupied because it is isolated and has never been colonized or has beenbeen colonized followed by local extinction and has not yet beenrecolonized. This research addresses the question of how to identifysuitable, unoccupied habitat and distinguish it from unsuitable habitat. Weare studying a group of six species of forest understory herbs chosen torepresent a broad range of habitat distribution and dispersalcharacteristics. Our aim is to quantify the fundamental niche of thesespecies (sensu Hutchinson 1957), in terms of variables such as soilmoisture and temperature, by developing a set of habitat specificdemographic stage transition models (i.e. conditional on such environmentalvariables) for these species. These models, in combination with data fromfield surveys of the local distribution of the species, will be used todevelop testable predictive maps of the distribution of suitable habitatwhich can be compared to the observed distribution of the plants. Wehypothesize that both dispersal ability and the distribution of suitablehabitat are important determinants of the actual distribution of species.The goal of this research is both to further our conceptual understanding ofthe relationships between habitat requirements and species distributions,and to provide a practical approach to operationalizing the concept of"suitable habitat." In order to quantify the niche requirements of our study species, we are simultaneously tracking their year-to-year demography and the environmental conditions to which they are subject. Environmental variables of interest include soil moisture, soil temperature, light levels, and soil chemistry.Soil moisture will be measured biweekly during the growing season andapproximately monthly during the winters to depths of 10 and 30cm at fourlocations within each study plot, using Coweetas Tektronix TDR unit. Soiltemperature will be monitored contimually using a Hobo data logger. Soilchemistry variables we anticipate measuring include pH, N, and C. Subcanopylight levels will be derived using hemispherical photography. The studyplots are subdivided into grids of 2x2m cells, marked with orange stakeflags. Within these all ramets of our study species are marked with stakeflags of various colors and given unique identifying numbers so that theirgrowth and survival can be foloowed from year to year. Variables of interestinclude plant size or leaf area, flower and fruit production, andrecruitment of new ramets. This information, along with the measures oflocal environmental conditions within study plots, will be used to constructcondition-specific demographic stage transition models, providing ameaningful quantitative definition of habitat suitability for our six studyspecies.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Coweeta|LTER|habitat suitability|seed dispersal|habitat-specific demography|Tipularia discolor|Hexastylis arifolia|Hepatica americanaa|Maianthemum racemosum</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2011-04-26T22:04:46Z</date
></data>