<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.29698</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>IPCC Climate Change Data: CSIRO A2a Model: 2080 Maximum Temperature</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>The CSIRO Atmospheric Research Mark 2b climate model (Hirst        et al., 1996, 1999) has recently been used for a number of more        sophisticated climate change simulations. These start from 1880        to avoid the &amp;quot,cold start problem&amp;quot,.  This version of        the CSIRO model includes the Gent-McWilliams mixing scheme in        the ocean and shows greatly reduced climate drift relative to        earlier versions (e.g. Dix and Hunt, 1998). The drift in global        mean surface temperature in the new control run is about -0.02        degrees C/century. Note that the model uses flux correction.        The model atmosphere has 9 levels in the vertical and horizontal        resolution of spectral R21 (approximately 5.6 by 3.2 degrees).        The ocean model has the same horizontal resolution with 21        levels.  The equilibrium sensitivity to doubled CO2 of a mixed        layer ocean version of the model is 4.3 degrees. This is at the        high end of the range of model sensitivities (e.g. IPCC 1995,        Table 6.3). In the basic greenhouse gas experiment the model        combines the effect of all radiatively active trace gases into        an &amp;quot,equivalent&amp;quot, CO2 concentration. Observed        concentrations are used from 1880 to 1990 and the IS92a        projections into the future. This gives close to a 1%/year        compounding increase of equivalent CO2.  Another model        experiment includes the negative radiative forcing from        atmospheric sulphate aerosol. The direct aerosol forcing is        included via a perturbation of the surface albedo, similarly to        the Hadley Centre experiments described by Mitchell et al (1995)        and Mitchell and Johns (1997) . The sulphate concentrations are        the same as used in the Hadley Centre experiments. However the        chosen aerosol optical properties are different, giving a        present day forcing due to anthropogenic sulphate of about -0.4        W/m^2. This can be compared to the 1880-1990 greenhouse gas        forcing of about 2 W/m^2.  The magnitude of the 20th century        warming in the model including aerosol matches the observed        reasonably well. However there are a number of forcings missing        from the model, including solar variability, sulphate indirect        effect and the effect of soot.  The climate sensitivity of        CSIRO-Mk2 is about 4.3 degrees C (Watterson et al.,1997).For the A2 emissions scenario the main emphasis is on a        strengthening of regional and local culture, with a return to        family values in many regions. The A2 world consolidates into a        series of roughly continental economic regions, emphasizing        local cultural roots. In some regions, increased religious        participation leads many to reject a materialist path and to        focus attention on contributing to the local community.        Elsewhere, the trend is towards increased investment in        education and science and growth in economic productivity.        Social and political structures diversify, with some regions        moving towards stronger welfare systems and reduced income        inequality, while others move towards &amp;quot,lean&amp;quot,        government. Environmental concerns are relatively weak, although        some attention is paid to bringing local pollution under control        and maintaining local environmental amenities. The A2 world sees        more international tensions and less cooperation than in A1 or        B1. People, ideas and capital are less mobile so that technology        diffuses slowly. International disparities in productivity, and        hence income per capita, are maintained or increased. With the        emphasis on family and community life, fertility rates decline        only slowly, although they vary among regions. Hence, this        scenario family has high population growth (to 15 billion by        2100) with comparatively low incomes per capita relative to the        A1 and B1 worlds, at US$7,200 in 2050 and US$16,000 in        2100.Technological change is rapid in some regions and slow in        others as industry adjusts to local resource endowments,        culture, and education levels. Regions with abundant energy and        mineral resources evolve more resource intensive economies,        while those poor in resources place very high priority on        minimizing import dependence through technological innovation to        improve resource efficiency and make use of substitute inputs.        The fuel mix in different regions is determined primarily by        resource availability. And divisions among regions persist in        terms of their mix of technologies, with high-income but        resource-poor regions shifting toward advanced post fossil        technologies (renewables in regions of large land availability,        nuclear in densely populated, resource poor regions) and        low-income resource-rich regions generally relying on older        fossil technologies.With substantial food requirements,        agricultural productivity is one of the main focus areas for        innovation and RD efforts in this future. Initially high levels        of soil erosion and water pollution are eventually eased through        the local development of more sustainable high-yield        agriculture.Although attention is given to potential local and        regional environmental damage, it is not uniform across regions.        For example, sulfur and particulate emissions are reduced in        Asia due to impacts on human health and agricultural production        but increase in Africa as a result of the intensified        exploitation of coal and other mineral resources. The A2 world        sees high energy and carbon intensity, and correspondingly high        GHG emissions. Its CO2 emissions are the highest of all four        scenario families.  Data are available for the following        periods:  1961-1990, 2010-2039, 2040-2069, and 2090-2099 Mean        monthly and change fields.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>climate|global climate change|temperature</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2011-04-27T01:56:31Z</date
></data>