<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.31850</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Saddle grid plant species composition (point quadrat measurements).</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Permanent 1-m^2 plots were established beside each of the 88 Saddle grid stakes in 1989. Each plot was located within 2 m of the grid  stake, but always in the same vegetation type as that associated with the  stake. The distance and direction from the were randomly selected, and  thus varied from plot to plot. Point quadrat measurements are to be made  every 5 years to quantify species composition, canopy structure, and  microtopography. Measurements were made in both 1989 and 1990 in order to  characterize the year-to-year variation inherent in the sampling method. The point-quadrat technique used was identical to that described by Auerbach (1992): The point-quadrat method was used for estimating canopy stratification and plant cover. Aluminum point-quadrat frames were 1-m^2 in size, with double-layer filament spaced 10 cm apart to make a 10 x 10 cm grid for a total of 100 sample points per plot. Before sampling, the point-quadrat frame was leveled and plots were permanently marked  in the following manner. Aluminum tags were nailed into the ground so that a frame could be repositioned in the same location from year to year, i.e., tags with a hole in the middle were used to define the locations for the point frame legs and four tags with a "X"  stamped on them (positioned somewhere inside each of the frame  corners) were used to define alignment of the frame by positioning the string crossings over these "X"s. Distances from the frame to a top canopy plant hit and to a surface layer plant hit were measured to the nearest 0.5 cm and recorded.  Plant genus and species were also recorded at both hits at each point.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>NWT|Niwot Ridge LTER Site|LTER|Colorado|canopy structure|community change|plant communities|species composition|vegetation</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>1994</date
></data>