<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.133555</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Data from: The fire ant social chromosome supergene variant Sb shows low diversity but high divergence from SB</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Variation in social behavior is common yet little is known about the genetic architectures underpinning its evolution. A rare exception is in the fire ant Solenopsis invicta: Alternative variants of a supergene region determine whether a colony will have exactly one or up to dozens of queens. The two variants of this region are carried by a pair of &#8220;social chromosomes&#8221;, SB and Sb, which resemble a pair of sex chromosomes. Recombination is suppressed between the two chromosomes in the supergene region. While the X-like SB can recombine with itself in SB/SB queens, recombination is effectively absent in the Y-like Sb because Sb/Sb queens die before reproducing.  Here, we analyze whole genome sequences of eight haploid SB males and eight haploid Sb males. We find extensive SB-Sb di&#8629;erentiation throughout the &gt;19Mb long supergene region. We find no evidence of &#8220;evolutionary strata&#8221; with different levels of divergence comparable to those reported in several sex chromosomes. A high proportion of substitutions between the SB and Sb haplotypes are nonsynonymous, suggesting inefficacy of purifying selection in Sb sequences, similar to that for Y-linked sequences in XY systems. Finally, we show that the Sb haplotype of the supergene region has 635-fold less nucleotide diversity than the rest of the genome. We discuss how this reduction could be due to a recent selective sweep affecting Sb specifically or associated with a population bottleneck during the invasion of North America by the sampled population.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Evolution of Sex|Genomics/Proteomics|Invasive Species|Molecular Evolution|Population Genetics - Empirical|Behavior/Social Evolution|Social chromosomes|Evolutionary strata|Social evolution|Diversity in supergene variants|Queen number in ants</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2017-02-08T16:42:36Z</date
></data>