<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.51248</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Data from: Contrasting insights provided by single and multispecies data in a regional comparative phylogeographic study</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Many single-species freshwater phylogeographic studies have been carried out in south-east Queensland, however comparative phylogeography requires multiple lines of evidence to infer deep, significant relationships between landscape and biota. The present study aimed to test conclusions resulting from single taxon studies in a multispecies comparative framework: (1) how influential are river basins in the genetic structure of freshwater species, (2) are there biogeographic frontiers between groups of basins, and (3) could deep intraspecific lineages be explained by a single event? New and existing data from 33 freshwater species (23 fishes and 10 crustaceans) were combined, and both standard single-species analyses (haplotype networks, genetic distances, &#934;ST) and multispecies methods (hierarchical ABC) were carried out for 1814 sequences from eight basins. More than half of the species displayed a high phylogeographic structure and contained at least two distinct lineages. Almost all of the lineage divergences displayed an element of north/south geographic breaks, with the most influential boundary being between the Mary and Brisbane rivers. Of the 11 basin-pair multispecies coalescent analyses, four implied a single divergence as being most likely. A regional analysis of deep lineages within 16 taxon-pairs resulted in a strongly supported inference of a single divergence, probably dating to the Pleistocene. Basin boundaries are a key determinant of phylogeographic patterns for most of these freshwater species, although the specific biogeographic relationship between basins often varies depending on the species. There are a number of influential biogeographic frontiers, with the Brisbane-Mary being the most important. The finding that a single event may be responsible for multiple deep lineages across the region implies that a highly influential climate change event may have been detected.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Crustaceans|Fish|Phylogeography|Comparative|hABC</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2014-03-04T16:45:47Z</date
></data>