<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.19820</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>IPCC Climate Change Data: ECHAM4 A2a Model: 2050 Wind Speed</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>The ECHAM climate model has been developed from the ECMWF        atmospheric model (therefore the first part of its name: EC) and        a comprehensive parameterisation package developed at Hamburg        therefore the abbreviation HAM) which allows the model to be        used for climate simulations. The model is a spectral transform        model with 19 atmospheric layers and the results used here        derive from experiments performed with spatial resolution T42        (which approximates to about 2.8 degrees  longitude/latitude        resolution). The model has also been used at resolutions in the        range T21 to T106.  ECHAM4 is the current generation in the line        of ECHAM models (Roeckner, et al., 1992). A summary of        developments regarding model physics in ECHAM4 and a description        of the simulated climate obtained with the uncoupled ECHAM4        model is given in Roeckner et al. (1996). The initial sea        surface temperature and sea-ice data is the COLA/CAC AMIP SST        and sea-ice data set. The mean terrain heights are computed from        high resolution US Navy data set. The fraction of grid area        covered by vegetation based on the Wilson and Henderson-Sellers        (1985) data set. The ocean albedo is a function of solar zenith        angle and the land albedo from the satellite data of Geleyn and        Preuss (1983). A diurnal cycle and gravity wave-drag is        included. The time-step of the model is 24 minutes, except for        radiation which uses two hours.  The ocean model is an updated        version of the isopycnal model (OPYC3) developed by Josef        Oberhuber (Oberhuber, 1993) at the Max-Planck-Institute for        Meteorology, Hamburg, Germany. The name OPYC is derived from        Ocean and isoPYCnal co-ordinates.  The concept to use isopycnals        as the vertical co-ordinate system for an OGCM is based on the        observation that the interior ocean behaves as a rather        conservative fluid. Even over long distances the origin of water        masses can be traced back by considering the distribution of        active or passive tracers. Treating the ocean as a conservative        fluid fails in areas of significant turbulence activity such as        the surface boundary layer. A surface mixed-layer is therefore        coupled to the interior ocean in order to represent near-surface        vertical mixing and to improve the response time-scales to        atmospheric forcing which is controlled by the mixed-layer        thickness. Since the model is designed for studies on large        scales, a sea ice model with rheology is included and serves the        purpose of de-coupling the ocean from extreme high-latitude        winter conditions and promotes a realistic treatment of the        salinity forcing due to melting or freezing sea ice.  The        experiments from which results are used here are the 1000-year        unforced control simulation using the coupled ECHAM4/OPYC3 model        and then two climate change simulations. The greenhouse gas only        forced experiment (referred to as GGa1) used historical        greenhouse gas forcing from 1860 to 1990 followed by a 1 per        cent annum increase in radiative forcing from 1990 to 2099. The        greenhouse gas and sulphate aerosol forced experiment (referred        to as GSa1) used the GGa1 forcing, plus the negative forcing due        to sulphate aerosols. This was represented by means of an        increase in clear-sky surface albedo proportional to the local        sulphate loading. The indirect effects of aerosols were not        simulated. For 1860 to 1990 the historic sulphate aerosol        forcing estimate was used and for 1990 to 2049 the aerosol        forcing estimated for the IS92a emissions scenario. The GSa1        experiment did not extend beyond 2049.  Fuller details of the        ECHAM4/OPYC3 coupled model can befound at the DDC Yellow Pages.Several papers describe results using this version of the model        - see Bacher et al. (1998), Oberhuber et al. (1998), Zhang et        al. (1998).  The climate sensitivity of ECHAM4 is about 2.6        degrees C.The A2 world consolidates into a series of roughly        continental economic regions, emphasizing local cultural roots.        In some regions, increased religious participation leads many to        reject a materialist path and to focus attention on contributing        to the local community. Elsewhere, the trend is towards ncreased        investment in education and science and growth in economic        productivity. Social and political structures diversify with        some regions moving towards stronger welfare systems and reduced        income inequality, while others move towards &amp;quot,lean&amp;quot,        government. Environmental concerns are relatively weak, although        some attention is paid to bringing local pollution under control        and maintaining local environmental amenities.The A2 world sees more international tensions and less        cooperation than in A1 or B1. People, ideas and capital are less        mobile so that technology diffuses slowly. International        disparities in productivity, and hence income per capita, are        maintained or increased. With the emphasis on family and        community life, fertility rates decline only slowly, although        they vary among regions. Hence, this scenario family has high        population growth (to 15 billion by 2100) with comparatively low        incomes per capita relative to the A1 andB1 worlds, at US$7,200        in 2050 and US$16,000 in 2100.Technological change is rapid in        some regions and slow in others as industry adjusts to local        resource endowments, culture, and education levels. Regions with        abundant energy and mineral resources evolve more resource        intensive economies, while those poor in resources place very        high priority on minimizing import dependence through        technological innovation to improve resource efficiency and make        use of substitute inputs. The fuel mix in different regions is        determined primarily by resource availability. And divisions        among regions persist in terms of their mix of technologies,        with high-income but resource-poor regions shifting toward        advanced post fossil technologies (renewables in regions of        large land availability, nuclear in densely populated, resource        poor regions) and low-income resource-rich regions generally        relying on older fossil technologies.With substantial food        requirements, agricultural productivity is one of the main focus        areas for innovation and RD efforts in this future. Initially        high levels of soil erosion and water pollution are eventually        eased through the local development of more sustainable        high-yield agriculture.Although attention is given to potential        local and regional environmental damage, it is not uniform        across regions. For example, sulfur and particulate emissions        are reduced in Asia due to impacts on human health and        agricultural production but increase in Africa as a result of        the intensified exploitation of coal and other mineral        resources. The A2 world sees high energy and carbon intensity,        and correspondingly high GHG emissions. Its CO2 emissions are        the highest of all four scenario families.  Data are available        for the following periods:  1961-1990, 2010-2039, 2040-2069, and        2090-2099, mean and monthly change fields.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>climate|global climate change|wind</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2011-04-26T18:58:13Z</date
></data>