<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.51615</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Supplemental Dataset 8: Traits used from other studies.</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Supplemental Dataset 8: Traits used from other studies. A list of traits meta-analyzed in this study. Traits are assigned to classes: &#8220;ENZ,&#8221; enzymatic activity measured from the fruit pericarp (Steinhauser et al., 2011), &#8220;MET,&#8221; metabolite levels from the fruit pericarp (Schauer et al., 2006, Schauer et al., 2008), &#8220;MOR,&#8221; yield, biomass, and morphological traits (Schauer et al., 2006, Schauer et al., 2008), &#8220;SEED,&#8221; seed metabolite levels (Toubiana et al., 2012). In addition to the trait abbreviation, for &#8220;MOR&#8221; traits a brief description is given, for all other traits, the abbreviation roughly corresponds to the metabolite or enzymatic activity measured, and precise definitions for all traits can be found from their publically-available source: phenome-networks.com. The &#8220;studies&#8221; for which the raw data is derived from phenome-networks.com is also given: A = akko 2001 II, B = akko 2001 met, C = akko 2001 metabolites A, D = akko 2001 metabolites B, M = akko 2003 metabolites A, N = akko 2003 metabolites B, O = akko 2003 enzymes, P = akko 2003, W = akko 2004 enzymes, X = akko 2004 morphology, Y = akko 2004 seed metabolites, Z = akko 2004 metabolites. Only homozygous IL traits were considered. For some traits there was a deficit in the ILs measured, and to not bias inter-trait analyses, only those traits for which &gt; 60 ILs (not including cv. M82) were measured were included (practically, the trait with the fewest ILs measured after this condition has 67 IL values). Whether the trait was &#8220;included&#8221; or &#8220;dropped&#8221; from analyses in this study is given in the &#8220;Included.Dropped&#8221; column.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>quantitative genetics|morphometrics|leaves|leaf|leaf development|development|stomata|tomato|evolution|adaptation|photosynthesis|fruit|sugar|leaf shape|morphology|QTL|desert|agriculture|plant biology|genomics|transcriptomics</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2013-07-22T19:27:51Z</date
></data>