<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.119020</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>poa_alpina_data</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>This file contains all raw data on the first sheet, with the site name, elevation of the site, site location (region in Switzerland),  individual number (genotype_replicate clone), population name, origin of the population, sympatric vs. allopatric criterion (sympatric, near-allopatric, far-allopatric), initial tiller number (initial tiller), height of inflorescences (height), number of tillers (ntiller), number of inflorescences (nrepro), incidence of reproduction (repro), vegetative biomass (vegbiom), survival, reproductive biomass (reprobiom), and specific leaf are (sla). On the second sheet, you willl find the data for the selection analysis of plasticity at the small spatial scale (sympatric - near-allpoatric : SA), with the standardized plasticity index (stand_index), the standardized specific leaf area (stand_sla),  and the relative fitness (relat-fit). Same for the third sheet, except with data calculted at the larger spatial scale (sympatric - far-allopatric: SF). IMPORTANT NOTE: The population codes between the data file and the manuscript were changed. Below you will find the population codes from the data file, the correspondant codes in the manuscript and the original home site (sympatric) of those populations: PAD1 --&gt; stays PAD1, home at FluelpassPAD2 --&gt; stays PAD2, home at Schwarzhorn (was removed from files and analysis)PAD7 --&gt; became PAD3, home at SchiahornPAZ1 --&gt; stays PAZ1, home at SchwarzseePAZ3 --&gt; became PAZ2, home at RothornPAZT4 --&gt; became PAZ3, home at FuriOne population was removed from analysis (as it did not amplify to microsatellite PCR, see results). However, we made a mistake in the manuscript in stating that this population was PAD3. Instead, it is population PAD2 that was removed from analysis (and the data file), as can be seen in Figure 2.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>reciprocal transplantation experiment|genetic differentiation|phenotypic plasticity|adaptive potential|sympatric vs. allopatric contrast</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2016-07-01T14:09:40Z</date
></data>