<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.20874</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Stream chemistry for watershed 263 (urban) sites BES ID 579-</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>In the Baltimore urban long-term ecological research (LTER) project, (Baltimore Ecosystem Study, BES) we use the watershed approach to evaluate integrated ecosystem function. The LTER research is centered on the Gwynns Falls watershed, a 17,150 ha catchment that traverses a gradient from the urban core of Baltimore, through older urban residential (1900 - 1950) and suburban (1950- 1980) zones, rapidly suburbanizing areas and a rural/suburban fringe. Our long-term sampling network includes four longitudinal sampling sites along the Gwynns Falls as well as several small (40 - 100 ha) watersheds located within or near to the Gwynns Falls. The longitudinal sites provide data on water and nutrient fluxes in the different land use zones of the watershed (rural/suburban, rapidly suburbanizing, old suburban, urban core) and the small watersheds provide more focused data on specific land use areas (forest, agriculture, rural/suburban, urban). Each of the gaging sites is continuously monitored for discharge and is sampled weekly for chemistry. Additional chemical sampling is carried out in a supplemental set of sites to provide a greater range of land use. Weekly analyses includes nitrate, phosphate, total nitrogen, total phosphorus, chloride and sulfate, total suspended solids, turbidity, fecal coliforms, temperature, dissolved oxygen and pH. Cations, dissolved organic carbon and nitrogen and  metals are measured on selected samples. This dataset is for Watershed 263, a 364 ha urban storm drain watershed (or sewershed), with 30,000 residents with mixed industrial, institutional, and residential land uses. In March 2004, we established long-term monitoring sites in two sub-watersheds within W283.  Both are approximately 17 ha, with 20% impervious surface and 4% vegetation cover.  Samples (weekly grab and flow-weighted composite) are taken in a stormwater drainage pipe.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Baltimore|MD|Washington|D.C|Chesapeake Bay|Baltimore-Washington|Maryland</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2007-03-02</date
></data>