<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.17676</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>MCR LTER: Coral Reef: Water Column: Zooplankton Composition and Abundance</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>This data package contains zooplankton abundance, dry mass, carbon content, 				and taxonomic composition measured 2 to 4 times per year at 5 stations on the 				north shore of Moorea, French Polynesia: Forereef, Backreef, Fringing Reef, 				Cooks Bay,  and Oceanic(5 km due north). Day time measurements were taken 				with a 30 cm, 200 um mesh plankton net equipped with a slow speed General 				Oceanics Model 2030 flow meter. Nets were swum horizontally by a diver 1 m 				above the bottom at Forereef, Backreef and Fringing Reef sites. Daytime 				sampling at the Oceanic and Cooks Bay sites consisted of 50 m and 30 m 				vertical tows respectively.  Nighttime sampling was done in duplicate or 				triplicate at the Forereef, Backreef and Fringing Reef sites only using 				automated plankton pumps equipped with flow meters and 200 um internal nets. 				These pumps sampled 75 cm above the bottom for 1 to 1.5 hours beginning at 11 pm 				local time. All nighttime sampling occurred within 3 days of the new moon.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Moorea Coral Reef|Reef Zooplankton abundance|Zooplankton carbon|Zooplankton composition|Reef Zooplankton nighttime abundance|Crustacea &#65533;Copepoda|Crustacea-Isopoda|Crustacea-Ostracoda|Crustacea-Tanaidacea|Crustacea-Decapoda|Crustacea-Mysidacea|Crustacea- Amphipoda|Crustacea &#65533; larvae|Annelida- Polychaetea|Cheatognatha|Appendicularia- Oikopleura sp.|Mollusca-Gastropoda- Heteropoda|Mollusca-Gastropoda-Pteropoda|Cnidaria-hydromedusae|Cnidaria- siphonophore|Chordata-Cephalochordata-Amphioxus|Fish larvae|Eggs|Mollusca- Gastropoda- Veliger larvae|Zooplankton|Forereef|Backreef|Fringing Reef|Cooks Bay|Oceanic|Populations|Time Series Program|Population and Community Dynamics|Reef Resistance and Resilience</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2011-04-21T20:06:17Z</date
></data>