<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.30564</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Interactive effects of fertility and distribution on competition and plant community structure. Year 1991 Soil nitrate and ammonium</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>There are four levels of nitrogen, corresponding to treatments A, C, E and Gin &lt;A HREF="http://www.cedarcreek.umn.edu/research/exper/e001/e001.html"&gt;E001&lt;/A&gt;, applied at the same time as in that experiment.  For adescription of fertilizer added to E052, see file &lt;A HREF="http://www.cedarcreek.umn.edu/research/methods/nutradd/nutradd.html"&gt;fertilization details&lt;/A&gt;.  There are fourlevels of soil disturbance designated 1, 2, 3 and 4.       Level 1: undisturbed       Level 2: 1 pass with a 7 HP Honda rear-tined rototiller withthe elevator set to till to a depth of 9 inches       Level 3: 2 passes or  however many required to produce about50% bare ground       Level 4: 3 passes or  however many required to produce 100%bare ground.  This requires 3 passes in some plots but 5 or 6 in  others.In  addition,  all woody  vegetation  not destroyed by  tilling is cut at the base. Rototilling is applied in late April. Each fertilization treatment receives each disturbance treatment, for a totalof sixteen treatments.  There are four replicates of each of the sixteentreatments.  In addition, the four extreme ends (lowest N, lowest disturbance,highest N, lowest disturbance, etc. ) are replicated an additional ten times.Treatments are applied in a completely randomized design.  Each of the 104plots is 5m x 5m. Measurements taken at E052 will include:  1) species abundances, 2) communitybiomass allocation to leaves/roots/stems/flowers, 3) above and below groundnet primary production and 4) rates of nitrogen mineralization.  For a list oftreatments, see the treatment layouts in file &lt;A HREF="http://www.cedarcreek.umn.edu/research/exper/e052/treatment.html"&gt;trmte52&lt;/A&gt;. The plots in E052 are enclosed by a fence to exclude mammalian herbivores.Galvanized welded-wire hardware cloth with 6mm x 6mm openings was buried to adepth of 50cm.  Additional hardware cloth extends 60cm above the ground andpoultry netting extends to 2m above the ground. In 1990, ten plots of each of four treatments (N1D1, N1D4, N4D1, N4D4, whereN is the level of nitrogen added and D is the disturbance treatment) wererandomly selected for the competition experiment.  The above and belowgroundeffects of neighbors on transplanted grass seedlings were measured using threecompetition treatments:  transplants were grown in 50cm diameter subplots 1)with no neighbors, 2) with the roots but not shoots of neighbors, 3) with allabove and belowground parts of neighbors present.  One transplant was grown inthe center of each subplot.  Competition treatments were applied to subplotswithin the main plots during 14-18 May, 1990.  Competition treatments werereplicated three times in each of the ten replicate plots for each of the fourcombinations of nitrogen supply rate and disturbance.  Thus, the 40 plots ofthe nitrogen and disturbance combinations (2 nitrogen levels x 2 disturbancelevels x 10 replicates) each contained 9 subplots (3 competition treatments x3 replicates), each subplot comprising one transplant in one competitiontreatment.  A total of 360 seedlings were transplanted.  Competitiontreatments were assigned randomly to subplots within each plot. In 1991, three species of contrasting sizes, life histories, growth rates andpositions along gradients of nitrogen and disturbance in the experiment wereused:  Schizachyrium scoparium, Agropyron repens, and Setaria viridis.Transplants were grown individually in subplots, with 1) all neighbors and 2)no neighbors.  The experiment was conducted in high and low nutrientenvironments to test for the interaction between the environment, the size andthe species.  There were ten replicate plots of each of the two environments,one receiving no additional nitrogen and the second receiving nitrogen at17g/m2/yr. In total, there were 32 transplants (3 species x 3 size classes x 2competition treatments x 1, 2 or 3 replicates) in each plot, and 20 plots (2environments x 10 replicates), or 640 transplants.  Seedlings weretransplanted into the field during 3-6 June, 1991.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Cedar Creek Natural History Area|Long Term|Ecology|Successional dynamics|Primary Productivity|Disturbance Patterns|Nutrient Budgets|Nutrient Cycles|Climatic Variation|Biodiversity|Ecosystem functioning|Nitrogen limitation|Fire Frequency|Plant Competition</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>1993</date
></data>