<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.24871</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Biomass allocation trends in old field in relation to gradients of successional age and soil nitrogen . Year 1987 Plant tissue nitrogen</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>The objective of this experiment is to assess biomass allocation trends inthe field in relation to gradients of successional age and soil nitrogen.This objective was approached in three ways:  A) 37 old fields of various ages were surveyed for above and belowground        biomass, soil N, and light penetration.  Five strips (1m x 10cm)were clipped in        each field for above ground biomass (sorted to grassesand forbs, then sorted to        leaf and stem), and 3 root cores (down to30cm) taken per strip (rinsed, dried        and weighed).  Two lightmeasurements and one pooled (3 cores) soil N        sample (for available andtotal N) were taken per strip.  B) 35 abundant species of known successional status were harvestedfrom the        field (usually 15 individuals per species), including rootscontained in a core        20x30cm, dried, sorted to stem, leaf, and root, andweighed.  These data can be        combined with the old field survey results(&lt;A HREF="http://www.cedarcreek.umn.edu/research/exper/e014/e014.html"&gt;E014&lt;/A&gt;) to estimate successional        trends in allocation.  C) Root cores will be taken from microplots in fields A, B, C, and D,all              treatments.  This will be an estimate of root biomass to becombined with the        above ground samples (&lt;A HREF="http://www.cedarcreek.umn.edu/research/exper/e001/e001.html"&gt;E001&lt;/A&gt;) to assessroot-shoot trends in response to        manipulation of soil N in fields ofdifferent age.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Cedar Creek Natural History Area|Long Term|Ecology|Successional dynamics|Primary Productivity|Disturbance Patterns|Nutrient Budgets|Nutrient Cycles|Climatic Variation|Biodiversity|Ecosystem functioning|Nitrogen limitation|Fire Frequency|Plant Competition</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>1989</date
></data>