<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.125494</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Data from: Neoadjuvant and concurrent chemotherapy have varied impacts on the prognosis of patients with the ascending and descending types of nasopharyngeal carcinoma treated with intensity-modulated radiotherapy</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Purpose: To compare the outcomes of patients with ascending type (T4&amp;N0-1) and descending type (T1-2&amp;N3) of nasopharyngeal carcinoma (NPC) treated with concurrent chemoradiotherapy (CCRT), neoadjuvant chemotherapy (NACT) + intensity-modulated radiotherapy (RT) or NACT + CCRT. Methods: Retrospective analysis of 839 patients with ascending or descending types of NPC treated at a single institution between October 2009 to February 2012. CCRT was delivered to 236 patients, NACT + RT to 302 patients, and NACT + CCRT to 301 patients. Results: The 4-year overall survival rate, distant metastasis-free survival rate, local relapse-free survival rate, nodal relapse-free survival rate, loco-regional relapse-free survival rate, and progression free survival rate were 75.2% and 73.4% (P = 0.114), 85.7% and 74.1% (P = 0.008), 88.8% and 97.1% (P = 0.013), 96.9% and 94.1% (P = 0.122), 86.9% and 91.2% (P = 0.384), 73.7% and 66.2% (P = 0.063) in ascending type and descending type. Subgroup analyses indicated that NACT + RT significantly improved distant metastasis-free survival rate and progression-free survival rate when compared with CCRT in the ascending type, and there were no significant differences between the survival curves of NACT +RT and NACT + CCRT. For descending type, there were no significant differences among the survival curves of NACT +RT, CCRT, and NACT + CCRT groups, and the survival benefit mainly came from CCRT. Conclusions: Compared with NACT + CCRT or CCRT, NACT + RT may be a reasonable approach for ascending type, Although concurrent chemotherapy was effective in descending type, NACT + CCRT may be a more appropriate strategy for descending type.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Nasopharyngeal carcinoma|Ascending type|Descending type|Intensity-modulated radiotherapy|Chemotherapy|radiotherapy</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2016-11-07T17:06:00Z</date
></data>