<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.29485</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>IPCC Climate Change Data:  CGCM1 A2a Model: 2080 Radiation</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>The first version of the Canadian Global Coupled Model,        CGCM1, and its control climate are described by Flato et al.        (1999). The atmospheric component of the model is essentially        GCMII described by McFarlane et al. (1992). It is a spectral        model with triangular truncation at wave number 32 (yielding a        surface grid resolution of roughly 3.7 degrees x3.7 degrees) and        10 vertical levels. The ocean component is based on the GFDL        MOM1.1 code and has a resolution of approximately 1.8 degrees        x1.8 degrees and 29 vertical levels. The model uses heat and        water flux adjustments obtained from uncoupled ocean and        atmosphere model runs (of 10 years and 4000 years duration        respectively), followed by an `adaption' procedure in which the        flux adjustment fields are modified by a 14 year integration of        the coupled model. A multi-century control simulation with the        coupled model has been performed using the present-day CO2        concentration to evaluate the stability of the coupled model's        climate, and to compare the modelled climate and its variability        to that observed.  An ensemble of four transient climate change        simulations has been performed and is described in Boer et al.        (1999a, b). Three of these simulations use an effective        greenhouse gas forcing change corresponding to that observed        from 1850 to the present, and a forcing change corresponding to        an increase of CO2 at a rate of 1% per year (compounded)        thereafter until year 2100. The direct forcing effect of        sulphate aerosols is also included by increasing the surface        albedo (as in Reader and Boer, 1999) based on loadings from the        sulphur cycle model of Langner and Rodhe (1991). The fourth        simulation considers the effect of greenhouse gas forcing only.        The change in climate predicted by a model clearly depends        directly on this specification of greenhouse gas (and aerosol)        forcing, and of course these are not well known. The        prescription described above is similar to the IPCC        &amp;quot,business as usual&amp;quot, scenario, and using a standard        scenario allows the results of this model to be compared to        those of other modelling groups around the world. Some initial        results from these simulations are presented below.  The climate        sensitivity of CGCM1 is about 3.5 degrees C.  For the A2        emissions scenario the main emphasis is on a strengthening of        regional and local culture, with a return to family values in        many regions. The A2 world consolidates into a series of roughly        continental economic regions, emphasizing local cultural roots.        In some regions, increased religious participation leads many to        reject a materialist path and to focus attention on contributing        to the local community. Elsewhere, the trend is towards ncreased        investment in education and science and growth in economic        productivity. Social and political structures diversify with        some regions moving towards stronger welfare systems and reduced        income inequality, while others move towards &amp;quot,lean&amp;quot,        government. Environmental concerns are relatively weak, although        some attention is paid to bringing local pollution under control        and maintaining local environmental amenities. The A2 world sees        more international tensions and less cooperation than in A1 or        B1. People, ideas and capital are less mobile so that technology        diffuses slowly. International disparities in productivity, and        hence income per capita, are maintained or increased. With the        emphasis on family and community life, fertility rates decline        only slowly, although they vary among regions. Hence, this        scenario family has high population growth (to 15 billion by2100) with comparatively low incomes per capita relative to the        A1 andB1 worlds, at US$7,200 in 2050 and US$16,000 in        2100.Technological change is rapid in some regions and slow in        others as industry adjusts to local resource endowments,        culture, and education levels. Regions with abundant energy and        mineral resources evolve more resource intensive economies,        while those poor in resources place very high priority on        minimizing import dependence through technological innovation to        improve resource efficiency and make use of substitute inputs.        The fuel mix in different regions is determined primarily by        resource availability. And divisions among regions persist in        terms of their mix of technologies, with high-income but        resource-poor regions shifting toward advanced post fossil        technologies (renewables in regions of large land availability,        nuclear in densely populated, resource poor regions) and        low-income resource-rich regions generally relying on older        fossil technologies.With substantial food requirements,        agricultural productivity is one of the main focus areas for        innovation and RD efforts in this future. Initially high levels        of soil erosion and water pollution are eventually eased through        the local development of more sustainable high-yield        agriculture.Although attention is given to potential local and        regional environmental damage, it is not uniform across regions.        For example, sulfur and particulate emissions are reduced in        Asia due to impacts on human health and agricultural production        but increase in Africa as a result of the intensified        exploitation of coal and other mineral resources. The A2 world        sees high energy and carbon intensity, and correspondingly high        GHG emissions. Its CO2 emissions are the highest of all four        scenario families.  Data are available for the following        periods:  1961-1990, 2010-2039, 2040-2069, and 2090-2099, mean        and monthly change fields.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>climate|global climate change|radiation</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2011-04-27T01:46:49Z</date
></data>