<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.116442</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Data for meta-analysis derived from studies comparing timber harvest or tree size to nest site occupancy or productivity in northern goshawks (Accipiter gentilis)</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>These are data derived from published literature for a meta-analysis assessing the degree to which timber harvest and tree size explain productivity and site occupancy in northern goshawks (Accipiter gentilis)We present these data in two alternative formats. (A) An Excel spreadsheet with multiple tabs. This spread sheet includes many comments linked to individual cells explaining the derivation of individual values. (B) A series of .csv files, each corresponding to a different tab in the Excel file. These are the same data as in the Excel sheet, but without the comments linked to individual cells. The Excel tabs / CSV files are as follows:(1) repro_rawThese are the studies that compared productivity (mostly number of fledged young per pair or per nest) to either timber harvest or tree size. We report the individual effects reported in each study and our derivation of the standard effect size &#8216;r&#8217;.(2) repro_per-study_averageFor each study listed in (1), we have calculated an average effect size (both r and Zr), corresponding average sample size (n) and average variance corresponding with Zr (vz). (3) occupancy_rawThese are the studies that compared the occupancy of nest sites or clusters of nest sites to either timber harvest or tree size. We report the individual effects reported in each study and our derivation of the standard effect size &#8216;r&#8217;.(4) occupancy_continent_study_avFor each study listed in (3), we have calculated an average effect size (both r and Zr), corresponding average sample size (n) and average variance corresponding with Zr (vz). (5) occupancy_variable_study_avFor each study listed in (3), we have calculated an average effect size (both r and Zr), corresponding average sample size (n) and average variance corresponding with Zr (vz). There is only one small difference with (4) above. One of the studies examined the correlations between occupancy and both timber harvest history and average tree size. Thus for this study, we calculated two average effects on this sheet, one corresponding to timber harvest and the other corresponding to average tree size. This facilitates comparing effects of tree size to effects of timber harvest.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>forest management|raptor|mature forest|meta-analysis|occupancy|productivity</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2016-05-27T11:54:35Z</date
></data>