<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.13756</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Little Rock Lake Experiment: Physical Limnology</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>The Little Rock Acidification Experiment was a joint project involving the USEPA (Duluth Lab), University of Minnesota-Twin Cities, University of Wisconsin-Superior, University of Wisconsin-Madison, and the Wisconsin Department of Natural Resources.  Little Rock Lake is a bi-lobed lake in Vilas County, Wisconsin, USA.  In 1983 the lake was divided in half by an impermeable curtain and from 1984-1989 the northern basin of the lake was acidified with sulfuric acid in three two-year stages.  The target pHs for 1984-5, 1986-7, and 1988-9 were 5.7, 5.2, and 4.7, respectively.  Starting in 1990 the lake was allowed to recover naturally with the curtain still in place.  Data were collected through 2000.  The main objective was to understand the population, community, and ecosystem responses to whole-lake acidification.  Funding for this project was provided by the USEPA and NSF.Parameters characterizing the physical limnology of the treatment (north basin, stations 1 and 3) and reference basin (south basin, station 2 and 4) are usually measured at one station in the deepest part of each basin (stations 1 and 2) at 0.5 to 1-m depth intervals depending on the parameter. Parameters measured at depth include water temperature, vertical penetration of photosynthetically active radiation (PAR), dissolved oxygen, chlorophyll and phaeopigments. Additional derived parameters include fraction of surface PAR at each depth and percent oxygen saturation. Auxiliary data include time of day, air temperature, cloud cover, and wind speed and direction and secchi depth.Sampling Frequency: varies - Number of sites: 4</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>North Temperate Lakes - LTER|percent oxygen saturation|physical limnology|light penetration|water temperature|dissolved oxygen|chlorophyll|chlorophyll|chlorophyll a|phaeophyton|conductivity|conductance</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2011-04-21T17:30:40Z</date
></data>