<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.29727</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>IPCC Climate Change Data: CSIRO A1a Model: 2080 Mean Temperature</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>The CSIRO Atmospheric Research Mark 2b climate model (Hirst        et al., 1996, 1999) has recently been used for a number of more        sophisticated climate change simulations. These start from 1880        to avoid the &amp;quot,cold start problem&amp;quot,.  This version of        the CSIRO model includes the Gent-McWilliams mixing scheme in        the ocean and shows greatly reduced climate drift relative to        earlier versions (e.g. Dix and Hunt, 1998). The drift in global        mean surface temperature in the new control run is about -0.02        degrees C/century. Note that the model uses flux correction.        The model atmosphere has 9 levels in the vertical and horizontal        resolution of spectral R21 (approximately 5.6 by 3.2 degrees).        The ocean model has the same horizontal resolution with 21        levels.  The equilibrium sensitivity to doubled CO2 of a mixed        layer ocean version of the model is 4.3 degrees. This is at the        high end of the range of model sensitivities (e.g. IPCC 1995,        Table 6.3). In the basic greenhouse gas experiment the model        combines the effect of all radiatively active trace gases into        an &amp;quot,equivalent&amp;quot, CO2 concentration. Observed        concentrations are used from 1880 to 1990 and the IS92a        projections into the future. This gives close to a 1%/year        compounding increase of equivalent CO2.  Another model        experiment includes the negative radiative forcing from        atmospheric sulphate aerosol. The direct aerosol forcing is        included via a perturbation of the surface albedo, similarly to        the Hadley Centre experiments described by Mitchell et al (1995)        and Mitchell and Johns (1997) . The sulphate concentrations are        the same as used in the Hadley Centre experiments. However the        chosen aerosol optical properties are different, giving a        present day forcing due to anthropogenic sulphate of about -0.4        W/m^2. This can be compared to the 1880-1990 greenhouse gas        forcing of about 2 W/m^2.  The magnitude of the 20th century        warming in the model including aerosol matches the observed        reasonably well. However there are a number of forcings missing        from the model, including solar variability, sulphate indirect        effect and the effect of soot.  The climate sensitivity of        CSIRO-Mk2 is about 4.3 degrees C (Watterson et al.,1997).From the IPCC website:  The A1 Family storyline is a case of        rapid and successful economic development, in which regional        averages of income per capita converge - current distinctions        between poor and rich countries eventually dissolve. In this        scenario family, demographic and economic trends are closely        linked, as affluence is correlated with long life and small        families (low mortality and low fertility). Global population        grows to some nine billion by 2050 and declines to about seven        billion by 2100. Average age increases, with the needs of        retired people met mainly through their accumulated savings in        private pension systems.  The global economy expands at an        average annual rate of about three percent to 2100. This is        approximately the same as average global growth since 1850,        although the conditions that lead to a global economic in        productivity and per capita incomes are unparalleled in history.        Income per capita reaches about US$21,000 by 2050. While the        high average level of income per capita contributes to a great        improvement in the overall health and social conditions of the        majority of people, this world is not without its problems. In        particular, many communities could face some of the problems of        social exclusion encountered by the wealthiest countries in the        20th century and in many places income growth could come with        increased pressure on the global commons.  Energy and mineral        resources are abundant in this scenario family because of rapid        technical progress, which both reduce the resources need to        produce a given level of output and increases the economically        recoverable reserves. Final energy intensity (energy use per        unit of GDP) decreases at an average annual rate of 1.3 percent.        With the rapid increase in income, dietary patterns shift        initially significantly towards increased consumption of meat        and dairy products, but may decrease subsequently with        increasing emphasis on health of an aging society. High incomes        also translate into high car ownership, sprawling        suburbanization and dense transport networks, nationally and        internationally. Land prices increase faster than income per        capita. These factors along with high wages result in a        considerable intensification of agriculture.  Three scenario        groups are considered in A1 scenario family reflecting the        uncertainty in development of energy sources and conversion        technologies in this rapidly changing world.  Near-term        investment decisions may introduce long-term irreversibilities        into the market, with lock-in to one technological configuration        or another. The A1B scenario group is based on a balanced mix of        energy sources and has an intermediate level of CO2 emissions,        but depending on the energy sources developed, emissions in the        variants cover a very wide range. In the fossil-fuel intensive        scenario group A1FI, emissions approach those of the A2        scenarios, conversely in scenario group A1T with low labor        productivity or of rapid progress in &amp;quot,post-fossil&amp;quot,        energy technologies, emissions are intermediate between those of        B1 and B2.  These scenario variants have been introduced into        the A1 storyline because of its &amp;quot,high growth with high        tech&amp;quot, nature, where differences in alternative technology        developments translate into large differences in future GHG        emission levels Ecological resilience is assumed to be high in        this storyline. Environmental amenities are viewed in a        utilitarian way, based on their influence on the formal economy.        The concept of environmental quality mightchange in this        storyline from&amp;quot,conservation&amp;quot, of nature to active        &amp;quot,management&amp;quot, - and marketing - of natural and        environmental services.  Data are available for the following        periods:  1961-1990, 2010-2039, 2040-2069, and 2090-2099 Mean        monthly and change fields.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>climate|global climate change|temperature</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2011-04-27T01:57:48Z</date
></data>