<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.71513</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Data from: Plasticity predicts evolution in a marine alga</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Under global change, populations have four possible responses: &#8216;migrate, acclimate, adapt or die&#8217; (Gienapp et al. 2008 Climate change and evolution: disentangling environmental and genetic response. Mol. Ecol. 17, 167&#8211;178. (doi:10.1111/j.1365-294X.2007.03413.x)). The challenge is to predict how much migration, acclimatization or adaptation populations are capable of. We have previously shown that populations from more variable environments are more plastic (Schaum et al. 2013 Variation in plastic responses of a globally distributed picoplankton species to ocean acidification. Nature 3, 298&#8211;230. (doi:10.1038/nclimate1774)), and here we use experimental evolution with a marine microbe to learn that plastic responses predict the extent of adaptation in the face of elevated partial pressure of CO2 (pCO2). Specifically, plastic populations evolve more, and plastic responses in traits other than growth can predict changes in growth in a marine microbe. The relationship between plasticity and evolution is strongest when populations evolve in fluctuating environments, which favour the evolution and maintenance of plasticity. Strikingly, plasticity predicts the extent, but not direction of phenotypic evolution. The plastic response to elevated pCO2 in green algae is to increase cell division rates, but the evolutionary response here is to decrease cell division rates over 400 generations until cells are dividing at the same rate their ancestors did in ambient CO2. Slow-growing cells have higher mitochondrial potential and withstand further environmental change better than faster growing cells. Based on this, we hypothesize that slow growth is adaptive under CO2 enrichment when associated with the production of higher quality daughter cells.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Phenotypic plasticity|Adaptation|climate change|oceanography</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2014-12-10T17:34:39Z</date
></data>