<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.47632</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>P2.sim</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Paternity and sperm count data for D. simulans. Variables: Treat &#8211; time after mating for which paternity and sperm numbers in the female reproductive tract were quantified, FirstM &#8211; transgenic line of first male by sperm label, GFP or RFP. Second male is automatically the reciprocal label, Remate &#8211; day after first mating (day 0) on which female remated, Cop1 &#8211; duration in minutes of the first copulation, Cop2 &#8211; duration in minutes of the second copulation, PriorProg &#8211; number of progeny produced by female before remating, P2.24 &#8211; proportion of progeny sired by the second male (P2) for the first 24 hrs after mating, P2.48 &#8211; P2 for the first 48 hrs after mating, P2.72 - P2 for the first 72 hrs after mating , P2 &#8211; P2 over entire time period, Bursa1 &#8211; number of first-male sperm in the bursa, Bursa2 &#8211; number of second-male sperm in the bursa, Prox1 &#8211; number of first-male sperm in the proximal half of the SR, Prox2 &#8211; number of second-male sperm in the proximal half of the SR, Dist1 &#8211; number of first-male sperm in the distal half of the SR, Dist1 &#8211; number of first-male sperm in the distal half of the SR, Dist2 &#8211; number of second-male sperm in the distal half of the SR, Caps1 &#8211; number of first-male sperm in the two spermathecal caps combined, Caps2 &#8211; number of second-male sperm in the two spermathecal caps combined, Ducts1 &#8211; number of first-male sperm in the two spermathecal ducts combined, Ducts2 &#8211; number of second-male sperm in the two spermathecal ducts combined, SR1 &#8211; number of first-male sperm in the entire SR, SR2 &#8211; number of second-male sperm in the entire SR, Sp1 &#8211; number of first-male sperm in both spermathecae combined, Sp2 &#8211; number of second-male sperm in both spermathecae combined</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Selection - Sexual|Reproductive Strategies|Behavior|Sexual Conflict|Drosophila|Sperm competition</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2013-03-15T18:53:09Z</date
></data>