<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.10695</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>International Tundra Experiment: Quantitative measurements.</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>The International Tundra Experiment (ITEX) is a consortium of  research sites seeking to understand the response of tundra plant  populations to changes in growing season temperatures through a simple  temperature manipulation and transplant experiment. The research goal  is to examine the phenologic and reproductive responses of a set of  species to experimentally-induced warming at a network of sites.  The ITEX design is hierarchical, with sites participating at whatever  level they are able. At the minimum, participation in ITEX requires  climate monitoring (using the LTER MSR standards), a temperature  manipulation using one of three possible designs, and monitoring  phenologic and reproductive variables for at least one designated  ITEX species or two other species. The temperature manipulation is achieved through use of conical or hexagonal open-top chambers  of solar fiberglass, which have been shown to increase the air  temperature at the surface approximately 3 degrees C. ITEX studies  at Niwot Ridge, a logical outgrowth of the long-term phenology  studies there, uses a factorial design based around the long-term  snowfence experiment. Twenty cones are placed behind the snowfence,  distributed at 10, 25, 45, and 75 m from the fence, each cone is  paired with an adjacent plot. Beginning with the 1995 season, 24 additional plots were implemented outside of the snowfence influence. Twelve cones are distributed beyond both the north and south edges of the snowfence area, at 10, 25, 45, and 75 m behind the line  of the snowfence, each cone is paired with an adjacent plot. This  results in the following treatments: increased winter snow, increased  summer temperature, increased snow and increased temperature,  and control. Key phenologic, growth, and reproductive traits are being  followed on marked individuals of Acomastylis rossii and Bistorta  bistortoides, and complete species composition is being monitored.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>NWT|Niwot Ridge LTER Site|LTER|Colorado|ITEX|plant development|plant growth|warming effects</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>1993</date
></data>