<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.32513</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Forest patch size, land use, and mesic forest herbs in the French Broad river basin.</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>The effect of forest fragmentation on cove-forest herbs was studied in the Southern Blue Ridge Province. Patches of mesic forests were sampled with 4 ha study plots. The coverage and density of herb species were greater in large patches (&gt;200 ha) than in small patches (less than 10 ha). Several ant-dispersed species, such as Disporum maculatum and Uvularia grandiflora, were more likely to be absent from small patches than from large patches. Wind-dispersed species, such as ferns and composites, were not affected by patch size and isolation. Small patches had reduced amounts of organic matter in the soil, suggesting that small patches have experienced more disturbance than large patches. Otherwise, there were no other differences in soil characteristics between patch sizes. Mechanisms hypothesized to have affected these populations include (a) disruption of population dynamics due to habitat fragmentation, (b) habitat degradation, and (c) anthropogenic disturbance via land use. Disturbances may have affected herb populations directly by increasing mortality rates and by degrading habitat. These habitat changes were confounded by the small size and isolation of small forest patches. During 01 June - 15 July 1995, 14 4-ha study plots were selected and sampled in forest patches ranging in area from 5 ha to &gt;10,000 ha. The sampling units for this study were the 4-ha plot and 1-ha subplots within the larger study plot. The forests studied were located on both public and private lands in Madison and Buncombe counties of North Carolina. Three of the large forest patches were owned and managed by the USDA Forest Service. To control for coarse- level habitat variation, all plots were located in mesic forests at 600-920 m elevation. Plots located in forest patches less than 25 ha in area were classified as being in small patches (N = 8). Plots in patches &gt;200 ha in area were classified as being in large patches (N = 6). Eight plots were classified as being in small patches, and each of these plots were located adifferent patch of forest. The mean SE edge-to-edge distance to the nearest patch was 42(8) m for all patches in the study area. The nearest-patch distance for the small patches containing study plots was not significantly different from this mean. Three of the six large-patch plots were located in separate patches. The three remaining large-patch plots were located in the same forested patch that was &gt;10,000 ha in area (Sites 12-14, Figure 1). The minimum distance between these three plots was &gt;1.5 km, and mesic foresthabitats were discontinuous between these plots. Therefore, these plots were treated as independent samples. Forest patch size was measured to the nearest ha using a land-cover map derived from a 1991 Thematic Mapper image (personal communication, P. Bolstad and H. Pape-University of Minnesota).  The same sized study plot (4 ha) was used to sample both large and small patches. This plot size covered a large percentage of the area of the small patches but only a minor portion of large patches. Nevertheless, keeping plot size constant allowed a more direct comparison of the communities found in the two patch sizes by eliminating the need to correct for species area effects due to different sized plots (Palmer 1991). Moreover, the patch size distribution of this landscape was highly skewed. Ninety-three percent of the patches in this landscape were small (less than 25 ha), and less than 2% were large (&gt;200 ha). In light of the difficulties of comparing the vegetation of entire patches, we chose to consider the vegetation of study plots as thesampling unit of comparison for this study. By limiting our study to closed-canopy, mesic, deciduous forest, we attempted to control for environmental characteristics that might affect herb populations. We defined mesic forest as a community located on a north-facing or sheltered slope with forest canopy dominants of more than one of the following species:  Liriodendron tulipifera, Acer saccharum, Tilia americana, Aesculus octandra, Carya cordiformis, and Betula lenta. Fagus grandifolia, Quercus rubra, Acerrubrum were also often present. Extensive stands of Rhododendron maximum and Tsuga canadensis were avoided although small stands of both species were encountered. Only closed- canopy forests with trees &gt;50 cm dbh were sampled. All plots were in second growth forest that had been disturbed before 1945 by logging and/or agriculture. We found no evidence that any of the plots had been cultivated, but woodland grazing has been a common practice in this region (Owsley 1949). A detailed history of disturbance was not available for these patches, nevertheless, we attempted to control for disturbance history in the plot selection process by choosing sites with minimal evidence of recent anthropogenic disturbances. To assess the recent history (within 20 years) of anthropogenic disturbance, land owners were interviewed and physical evidence of disturbance (e.g., fences, stumps, road beds) were noted for each plot. Plots that had experienced recent timber harvest or intensive woodland grazing were rejected. It was impossible to locate plots in small patches with no evidence of disturbance. Therefore, plots were selected in large patches that roughly matched the level of disturbance observed in small patches. That is, we did not compare plots in small patches with plots in large patches of forest that could be classified as old-growth with minimal human disturbance. Field Sampling The diversity and abundance of vascular plants were measured for each study plot. Each study plot was divided into four 1-ha subplots (four subplots per plot * 14 plots= 56 subplots). For each plot, herb and shrub diversity and abundance were measured using 40 0.5-m2 quadrats. The herb/shrub quadrats were located using a stratified random sampling design with each 1-ha subplot receiving 10 quadrats. Quadrats were located at least 20 m from forest edges, however, our ability to avoid the forest edge was limited in small forest patches.  Only a small fraction of a 5-ha patch was &gt;100 m from an edge. In the herb/shrub quadrats, the number of emergent stems for each species was recorded along with a visual estimate of each species percent coverage within the quadrat. Coverage was estimated for foliage up to two m above the ground surface. The number of stems per quadrat for each species was used as an estimate of density. Soil samples were taken from each 1-ha subplot by collecting mineral soil to a depth of 15 cm. The soil was collected from a point adjacent to each of the 10 herb quadrats and combined to form a composite sample for the subplot. Samples were dried at 70 degrees C for 48 hrs and mailed for testing to the Soil Testing Laboratory of the North Carolina Department of Agriculture, Agronomic Division. This laboratory measured aspects of soil chemistry, texture, nutrient availability, and organic matter relevant to agricultural and forestry uses (see Tucker 1996 for soil lab methods). Data Analysis The soil analyses produced 15 measures of soil texture and chemistry for each 1-ha subplot. The covariance structure of these 15 metrics was analyzed using a factor analysis with a principal components solution and varimax rotation (PROC FACTOR, SAS 1989) in order to reduce the 15 soil metrics to five complex soil factors (Johnson and Wichern 1988). Based on the absolute value of the rotated factor loadings, specific soil metrics were associated with each factor. This data reduction effectively removed the covariance structure of the data set, producing uncorrelated factor scores. The factor scores for each subplot were used as independent variables to assess the effects of soil attributes on vegetation. A t-test for two samples with unequal variances was used todetermine whether soils differed between plots located in large versus small patches (SAS 1989). Seventeen herb species (Table 1) were selected as representative of cove-forest communities based on published descriptions of their habitat (e.g., Radford et al. 1968, Weakley 1995). For each species studied, the coverage and density estimates were summed for each 1-ha subplot to reduce the number of zero counts. Then, the coverage sums were arcsin-square root transformed and the density sums were square-root transformed to increase normality of the data (Sokal and Rohlf 1995). These values represent the coverage and abundance of herb species for each 1-ha subplot, the same scale as the soil measurements.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Coweeta|LTER|land use|habitat fragmentation|cove forest|herbaceous species|cove forest|population persistence|disturbance|habitat quality|soil carbon|soil nutrients</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2011-04-27T04:10:48Z</date
></data>