<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.91685</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Data from: Bayesian inference of selection in a heterogeneous environment from genetic time-series data</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Evolutionary geneticists have sought to characterize the causes and molecular targets of selection in natural populations for many years. Although this research program has been somewhat successful, most statistical methods employed were designed to detect consistent, weak to moderate selection. In contrast, phenotypic studies in nature show that selection varies in time and that individual bouts of selection can be strong. Measurements of the genomic consequences of such fluctuating selection could help test and refine hypotheses concerning the causes of ecological specialization and the maintenance of genetic variation in populations. Herein, I proposed a Bayesian non-homogenous hidden Markov model to estimate effective population sizes and quantify variable selection in heterogeneous environments from genetic time-series data. The model is described and then evaluated using a series of simulated data, including cases where selection occurs on a trait with a simple or polygenic molecular basis. The proposed method accurately distinguished neutral loci from non-neutral loci under strong selection, but not from those under weak selection. Selection coefficients were accurately estimated when selection was constant or when the fitness values of genotypes varied linearly with the environment, but these estimates were less accurate when fitness was polygenic or the relationship between the environment and the fitness of genotypes was non-linear. Past studies of temporal evolutionary dynamics in lab populations have been remarkably successful. The proposed method makes similar analyses of genetic time-series data from natural populations more feasible, and thereby could help answer fun damental questions about the causes and consequences of evolution in the wild.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Adaptation|Ecological Genetics|Natural Selection and Contemporary Evolution|Population Genetics - Empirical</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2015-07-16T17:03:36Z</date
></data>