<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.18631</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Raw D and 18O isotope data for a core from the center and moat of the BBC collapse scar: Bonanza Creek Experimental Forest Flood Plains</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>This data set contains D and 18O data for a core from the center and moat (0 and 6 m) of the BBC collapse scar. Two well-preserved cores from the center of the bog was collected in March 2003 with a gasoline-powered permafrost corer. Cores were stored frozen and sampled using a radial saw. The core was sampled every two cm for macrofossil, diatom analysis and chemistry.Oxygen isotope ratios in aquatic cellulose has been shown to be a reliable tracer of lakewater isotope ratios (Sauer et al., 2001). I predicted that ?D and ?18O signatures in Sphagnum leaves would respond to enrichment and depletion in the bog water over time, providing an independent line of evidence for diatom-inferred hydrologic change.All isotope samples were processed by the Alaska Stable Isotope Facility using a Thermo Finnigan TC EA and Deltaplus XL mass spectrometer (Thermo Electron Corporation, Bremen, Germany) in continuous flow mode. Data were reported relative to standard mean ocean water (SMOW). Instrument precision was 1.2 ? SE for ?D and 0.3 ? SE for ?18O. I separated Sphagnum leaves from the bog and moat cores, and ran whole organic matter samples for ?D and ?18O stable isotopes.To determine the correlation between ?D and ?18O stable isotopes in peat leaves and bog water, I analyzed samples of Sphagnum and adjacent surface water. I collected surface water samples without headspace and refrigerated at 4 ?C until sample analysis. Snow samples were kept frozen until analysis. I refrigerated surface sample Sphagnum leaves from branches directly below the capitulum after harvest until analysis for ?D and ?18O stable isotopes. I identified Sphagnum samples to species.This data set was collected to relate ?D and ?18O to fires, changes in succession, changes in hydrology, and diatom assemblages.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>transect|isotope|chemistry|oxygen|bog|moat|deuterium|sphagnum</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2005-11-24</date
></data>