<data><id>2e102194-f384-4712-89a4-5db7a3fc409a</id><eml:eml/dataset/title>Spatially explicit database of tree related microhabitats (TreMs). Version 1.2. Integrate+ project</eml:eml/dataset/title><eml:eml/dataset/abstract/para>&#8216;Tree &#8211; tree&#8217; interactions are important structuring mechanisms for forest community dynamics. Forest management takes advantage of competition effects on tree growth by removing or retaining trees to achieve management goals. Both competition and silviculture have thus a strong effect on density and distribution of Tree related Microhabitats (TreMs) which are key features for forest taxa at the stand scale (e.g. Bouget et al. 2013, 2014). In particular, spatially explicit data to understand patterns and mechanisms of TreM formation in forest stands are rare. To train and eventually improve decision making capacities related to the integration of biodiversity aspects into forest management 39 usually 1 ha (100 m x 100m) permanent plots were established in dominant forest communities of Europe. Due to their demonstration character the selection of plots was non-systematic. They do, however, cover a broad range of forest types (e.g. beech-oak, beech-fir (-spruce), oak-hornbeam, pine-spruce, etc.), altitudinal gradient (from 25 m &#8211; 1850 m) and site conditions (e.g. oligotrophic Luzulo-Fagetum or Vaccinio-Pinetum to mesotrophic Galio-Fagetum or Milio-Fagetum). For each plot the following data is collected: (1) tree location as polar coordinates (stem base map), (2) tree species, (3) forest mensuration data (dbh in [cm], tree height in [m]), (4) tree related microhabitats (TreMs) and (5) tree status (living or standing dead). In addition to the spatial dendrometric data we provide information on plot establishment, management history (year of last intervention), forest type, plot location (state, region, country), elevation, means for annual precipitation and temperature, and the natural forest community.</eml:eml/dataset/abstract/para><date>2017-07-25</date></data>