<data><id>31770fdd-e4c5-4971-a2a8-31eadf292c8e</id><eml:eml/dataset/title>Checklist of the flowering plants of the island of Rodrigues, Indian Ocean</eml:eml/dataset/title><eml:eml/dataset/abstract/para>This dataset is the checklist of the native flowering species of the island of Rodrigues, Indian Ocean. This checklist is prepared by The Mauritius Herbarium, using information from the &#8216;Flore des Mascareignes&#8217;and newer published literature. It lists the valid name of recognised native flowering species following APG IV (2016). It includes possible native species - those species that include Mauritius in their range of distribution and are known not to have been introduced. Next versions are going to include vernacular names, known synonyms used in the Mascarenes and origin (endemic, native, probably native), and source (publication citation).This databasing effort has been funded by BID Africa Call 2017, grant BID-AF2017-SMA_0316 (https://www.gbif.org/project/aRCxBBF1BYU2C0us62ea4/getting-the-plants-to-all-dissemination-of-information-from-the-collection-of-the-mauritius-herbarium.)This first version of this checklist is a step towards a comprehensive updated and curated list of the native flowering plants species of the island of Rodrigues. The most recent flora of Rodrigues is being published under the collaboration of Mauritius, France and the UK, under series &#8216;Flore des Mascareignes&#8221;. The first volume of the series was published in 1976, with three volumes in preparation (Poaceae and Cyperaceae that are expected soon, and Orchidaceae). It is expected that an update and curated list will support the scientific community, the Mauritius Government (Rodrigues is part of the Republic of Mauritius) and also the general public. Rodrigues is one of the most ecologically devasted islands in the world,and has one of the most threatened flora in the world, therefore good quality information is essential to decision makers and conservationist.</eml:eml/dataset/abstract/para><date>2019-01-28</date></data>