<data><id>4085aaae-d914-4cfd-8bfa-fbadcf3a0b04</id><eml:eml/dataset/title>(Appendix B) Dinoflagellate cysts in Southeast Pacific Ocean surface sediments</eml:eml/dataset/title><eml:eml/dataset/abstract/para>orty-eight surface sediment samples from the southeast (SE) Pacific (25-53&#176;S) are investigated for the determination of the spatial distribution of organic-walled dinoflagellate cysts along the western South American continental margin. Fifty-five different taxa are recorded and reflect oceanic or coastal assemblages. The oceanic assemblages are characterised by low cyst concentrations and the dominance of autotrophs, while the coastal assemblages generally contain a higher number of cysts, which are mainly produced by heterotrophic species. Highest cyst concentrations are observed in the active upwelling system offshore Concepci&#243;n (35-37&#176;S). Brigantedinium spp., Echinidinium aculeatum, Echinidinium granulatum/delicatum and cysts of Protoperidinium americanum dominate assemblages related to upwelling. Echinidinium aculeatum appears to be the best indicator for the presence of all year round active upwelling cells. Other protoperidinioid cysts may also occur in high relative abundances in coastal regions outside active upwelling systems, if the availability of nutrients, co-responsible for the presence/absence of their main food sources such as diatoms and other protists, is sufficient. The importance of nutrient availability as a determining environmental variable influencing cyst signals on a regional scale (SE Pacific) is demonstrated through statistical analyses of the data. Because of the importance of nutrients, uncertainties about the outcomes of quantitative sea-surface temperature (SST) reconstructions (Modern Analogue Technique) based on dinoflagellate cysts may arise, since no interaction between different hydrographical variables is considered in this approach. The combination of the SE Pacific surface sample dataset with other published cyst data from the Southern Hemisphere resulted in a database which includes 350 samples: the 'SH350 database'. This database is used to test the accuracy of the quantitative reconstructions by calculating and comparing the estimated versus observed values for each site. An attempt to perform quantitative SST reconstructions on the last 25 cal ka of site ODP1233 (41&#176;S, 74&#176;27'W) is made and again stresses the importance of other environmental variables such as nutrient availability in determining the dinoflagellate cyst assemblages.</eml:eml/dataset/abstract/para><date>2010-01-01</date></data>