<data><id>4ba955bf-646f-47bf-86cc-e47655bb3542</id><eml:eml/dataset/title>Specialists instead of generalists oxidize alkanes in anoxic marine                hydrocarbon seep sediments</eml:eml/dataset/title><eml:eml/dataset/abstract/para>The anaerobic oxidation of non-methane hydrocarbons mediated by                sulfate-reducing bacteria (SRB) is a major process of organic matter degradation at                marine hydrocarbon seeps. Several SRB have been successfully cultured, however,                knowledge about in situ active organisms is still very limited. Here, we identified                alkane-degrading key players from two contrasting seeps at the Mediterranean Amon                Mud Volcano (Amon MV) and Guaymas Basin in the Gulf of California using                complementary stable-isotope probing (SIP) techniques. Anoxic sediments were                incubated with 13C-labeled butane or dodecane under close to in situ conditions.                DNA- and RNA-based SIP in combination with 454-pyrosequencing (PYRO-SIP) allowed the                identification of four phylogenetically distinct deltaproteobacterial groups of                alkane-oxidizing SRB within the family Desulfobacteraceae. We named the groups                degrading short-chain alkanes &#8216;SCA-SRB1' and &#8216;SCA-SRB2' and those degrading                long-chain alkanes &#8216;LCA-SRB1' and &#8216;LCA-SRB2'. CARD-FISH with newly developed                specific probes revealed a high relative in situ abundance of SCA-SRB1 and SCA-SRB2                with 2% of the total community, while groups LCA-SRB1 and LCA-SRB2 were below 1% of                total cells. Protein-based SIP (Protein-SIP), which enables to trace stable isotopes                from substrate to protein, confirmed alkane-degrading key players of the family                Desulfobacteraceae. In addition, Protein-SIP indicated additional carbon sources for                13C biosynthesis besides alkanes, and gave insights into possible metabolic                pathways: (1-methylalkyl)succinylation as initial step of butane degradation and the                oxidative Wood&#8211;Ljungdahl pathway as terminal point of alkane                degradation.</eml:eml/dataset/abstract/para><date>2019-04-05</date></data>