<data><id>572a4f02-fae9-4052-a10d-03fecbeb18de</id><eml:eml/dataset/title>Plant Diversity and Distribution on the Continental Cameroon Mountains</eml:eml/dataset/title><eml:eml/dataset/abstract/para>This database is a combination of sets of Plant data made in the Continental Cameroon Mountains at Rumpi Hills Forest Reserve (RHFR), and Mbembe Forest Reserve (MFR) within 2011 to 2016. This preliminary database project will run from November 2017 to November 2018 and is implemented by Tropical Plant Exploration Group (TroPEG) Cameroon and Biodiversity Institute, University of Kansas, USA in collaboration with the Department of Botany and Plant Physiology, University of Buea, under a project titled: Mobilization of Biodiversity Data Related to Protected Areas and Threatened Species in Western Cameroon. This project is controlled and managed under project number: BID-AF2017-0039-SMA of the Biodiversity Information for Development (BID) of the Global Biodiversity Information Facility (GBIF) with funds from the European Union (EU).At the Mbembe Forest Reserve, four one hectare plots were sampled at different vegetation types of semi-deciduous, grassland and woody savanna forest following the method of Condit 1998. Coordinates (Latitude, Longitude and elevation) were recorded at the four corners of each plot. Plots were selected based on physical and human factors like climate, altitude, slopes, and degree of forest used. Plot data was replicated independently and randomly using quadrants. Diameter of all trees and lianas in each plot &#8805; 1 cm (10 mm) were recorded and specimens collected mostly for doubtful species. Specimens for well-known species were not collected. At Rumpi Hills Forest Reserve, 25 1-ha plots were sampled, with GPS coordinates of the four corners of each plot recorded to assure repeated plot locations in the future. Precise coordinates of each plot are available in tabular form at http://hdl.handle.net/1808/25180. Plots were established following line transects of 500 m x 20 m, which were sub-divided into 25 quadrats of 20 m x 20 m each (Thomas et al., 2003). This was to facility data collection and to reduce error margin during data collections. In mountainous areas, plots were located strategically so that 25 quadrats of 20 x 20 m representing one-hectare fit within a particular sampling area. All trees and lianas within each plot with dbh &#8805;10 cm were measured with the help of a diameter tape, while in five nested plots of 10 m x 10 m, all trees and lianas with dbh &#8804;10 cm were measured with the aid of a caliper. Most species were identified in the field by two Botanists (Sainge Moses and Mambo Peter). Doubtful species were collected for further identification at the National Herbarium of Cameroon using other specimens in the herbarium, Botanists, floras, and monographs. The current database is based on physical specimen&#8217;s observations. A total of 23,427 occurrence records are presented in this first pass database, accounting to two classes, 39 orders, 83 families, 335 genera and 723 species. This database will be hosted by GBIF Cameroon and VERTNET, published by TroPEG Cameroon, and will be made available to Global Biodiversity Information Facility (GBIF) portal for visibility.</eml:eml/dataset/abstract/para><date>2018-10-26</date></data>