<data><id>5e8bab95-57f4-47b2-8ff2-e65e09ea6743</id><eml:eml/dataset/title>The Genus Epipactis Zinn (Orchidaceae) in the Komi Republic</eml:eml/dataset/title><eml:eml/dataset/abstract/para>The point set contains data on the distribution of Epipactis species in the Komi Republic. Epipactis Zinn is mostly a Eurasian genus with a south central distribution. According to recent classification, the genus is divided into two monophyletic sister sections, distinguished based on the shape and color of the lip, the gynostemium structure, and the presence and shape of papillae and hairs, it presently contains 59 species clustered in 8 groups (Delforge, 2006). In the territory of the Komi Republic genus is represented by three species &#8211; Epipactis atrorubens (Hoffm.) Besser, E. helleborine (L.) Crantz and E. palustris (L.) Crantz.The dark red helleborine, E. atrorubens, is a perennial orchid species, which is widely distributed across Europe and extending to the Ural Mountains in Asia and western Siberia (Efimov, 2004). In the Komi Republic, the species is on its northern distribution border. It grows on outcrops of carbonate rocks in the Timan Range, in the North and Sub-Polar Urals (Teteryuk, Kirillova, 2011). The plant prefers open slide limestone slopes, pine and larch forests with close begging of the calcium-containing rocks.The broad-leaved helleborine, E. helleborine, is a Eurasian species (Kolanowska, 2013) introduced in the 19th century to several regions of North America. It usually grows in deciduous and coniferous forest communities, on edges and in clearings in woodland (Delforge, 2006). In the Komi Republic the species is found in the South of the region. It prefers moist mixed forests and forest bogs (Teteryuk, Kirillova, 2011).The marsh helleborine, E. palustris, is a perennial summer-green orchid of Central Asia and Europe and inhabits lowlands and habitats up to 2000 m a. s. l. (Baum, 1998). Only two locations of this species are known in the Komi Republic.</eml:eml/dataset/abstract/para><date>2019-06-24</date></data>