<data><id>89e22f48-ea07-48d3-9c41-bad6a6d4c934</id><eml:eml/dataset/title>Checklist of mammal species of Prioksko-Terrasny reserve</eml:eml/dataset/title><eml:eml/dataset/abstract/para>Checklist of mammal species of the Prioksko-Terrasny Reserve was established on the basis of own observations of the animals and traces of their activities, made since 2005, published materials and Chronicles of the Nature Reserve. Own observations included - observations on routes in different parts of the reserve, winter route surveys of non-hibernating large mammals, tracking movements of animals on footprints in the snow, catches of small mammals, catches of bats by spider webs, accounts of beavers and beaver settlements (Albov, Khlyap, 2015, 2016). Cytogenetic and molecular genetic studies of hedgehogs, roe deer, and some species of small mammals have been carried out (Albov et al., 2010, 2015, Baskevich et al., 2009, 2016, 2016, Bogdanov et al., 2014).The list includes 62 species that inhabited the reserve from the beginning of its existence (1945). Of these, 13 species appeared here in the first 50 years of its existence. Two such new species contained and bred in a fenced area nursery: Bison bison constantly in captivity, Bison bonasus (young) were released from the enclosure only in the summer from 1951 to 1992. During the same period, two species (Rattus rattus and Neovison vison) disappeared from the reserve territory. In addition, there are hybridization processes, and it is not clear: whether there were ever on the territory of the reserve purebreds Erinaceus europaeus. DNA of this species was found only in hybrid individuals Erinaceus europaeus x Erinaceus roumanicus (Albov et al., 2015). There is no evidence of the presence of purebred deer (Cervus nippon, Cervus elaphus) and roe deer (Capreolus pygargus, Capreolus capreolus). All this makes it difficult to determine the exact number of mammal species in the modern fauna of the reserve.Data standardisation was supported by a GBIF - FinBIF data mobilization grant for European Russia  (Russia-02).</eml:eml/dataset/abstract/para><date>2018-09-03</date></data>