<data><id>9a10be01-3d0c-4f6e-9811-0627bd7a210d</id><eml:eml/dataset/title>High occurrence of jellyfish predation by black-browed and Campbell albatross identified by DNA metabarcoding 2017</eml:eml/dataset/title><eml:eml/dataset/abstract/para>This spreadsheet provides the sequences counts for the DNA groups found in the scats of black-browed albatross at New Island and Steeple Jason Island, Falkland Islands, Diego Ram&#237;rez and Albatross Islet, Chile, Bird Island, South Georgia, Canyon des Sourcils Noirs, Kerguelen Archipelago, France, Macquarie Island, Australia, and Campbell albatross at Campbell Island, NZ.Scat samples were collected in 2013/14 and 2014/15 at New Island, Steeple Jason Island, Macquarie Island, Campbell Island and Bird Island, in 2013/14 and 2015/16 at Kerguelen, in 2014/15 and 2015/16 at Albatross Islet and in 2013/14 at Diego Ram&#237;rez. Samples were collected during Incubation (Oct-Nov), early chick-rearing (Dec-Jan) or late-chick rearing (Feb-Mar). Due to the availability of birds at the colony, samples were predominantly collected from adults during incubation and early chick-rearing and chicks during late chick rearing. Samples sizes were too low during this study to directly compare dietary differences between chicks and adults, however, dietary comparisons between breeding stages were examined for sites where samples were collected during multiple breeding stages.Samples were PCR amplified with a universal metazoan primer set that is highly conserved and amplifies a region of the nuclear small subunit ribosomal DNA gene (18S rDNA). Details of the molecular methods and synthesis of this data can be found in: McInnes, J.C., Alderman, R., Raymond, B., Lea, M-A., Deagle, B., Catry, P., Gras, M., Phillip, R.A., Stanworth, A., Suazo, C., Thompson, D., Weimerskirch, H., Gras. M., and Jarman, S.N. High occurrence of jellyfish predation by black-browed and Campbell albatross identified by DNA metabarcoding. Molecular Ecology.</eml:eml/dataset/abstract/para><date>2018-10-02</date></data>