<data><id>a79c2b50-6c8a-11de-8226-b8a03c50a862</id><eml:eml/dataset/title>Queensland Museum provider for OZCAM</eml:eml/dataset/title><eml:eml/dataset/abstract/para>Queensland Museum provider for OZCAMQueensland Museum collections date back to the 1860s. Many early specimen records contained incomplete or inaccurate spatial information and in such cases, no interpretation of accuracy has been applied herein. When the museum commenced databasing in the mid-1980s, terms were introduced to represent assumed accuracies of collecting information. The terms below are a refinement of disparate lists and have been used for mapping to the Darwin Core field 'coordinateUncertaintyInMeters'. The table below shows how the terms are represented in metres of accuracy and the assumptions made in assigning these values.Term    coordinateUncertaintyInMeters    AssumptionsSurveyed (ground control)	1	International Terrestrial Reference Frame is used for ground survey mappingGoogle Earth	20	Latitude and longitude taken from Google Earth by positioning cursor over land featureGPS reading	50	In-field GPS reading, but correct datum is not assumedCollector's data	500	Generalised - usually legacy data, pre-GPSCentrepoint of geographic unit	1000	Centroid values used when no other, more accurate method has been recorded, (e.g. "Fraser Island").Gazetteer	1000	Gazeteer values used when no other, more accurate method has been recorded,(e.g. "Bundaberg, Queensland").Geographic location given	1000	Gazeteer values used when no other, more accurate method has been recorded, (e.g. "Blue Lake").Point in Polygon method	10000	Centroid values used when no other, more accurate method has been recorded, (e.g. "Springbrook National Park").Regional Approximation	10000	Centroid values used when no other, more accurate method has been recorded, (e.g. "Torres Strait").Level 1 - excellent	20	Adopted CSIRO terminologyLevel 2 - good	50	Adopted CSIRO terminologyLevel 3 - satisfactory	100	Adopted CSIRO terminologyLevel 4 - poor	500	Adopted CSIRO terminologyLevel 5 - doubtful	1000	Adopted CSIRO terminologyGeological Map (1:25 000 scale)	25	Accuracy by designationTopographic Map (1:25 000 scale)	25	Accuracy by designationGeological Map (1:50 000 scale)	50	Accuracy by designationTopographic Map (1:50 000 scale)	50	Accuracy by designationGeological Map (1:100 000 scale)	100	Accuracy by designationTopographic Map (1:100 000 scale)	100	Accuracy by designationGeological Map (1:250 000 scale)	250	Accuracy by designationTopographic Map (1:250 000 scale)	250	Accuracy by designationGeological Map (1:500 000 scale)	500	Accuracy by designationTopographic Map (1:500 000 scale)	500	Accuracy by designationTopographic Map (1:1 000 000 scale)	1000	Accuracy by designationMap Reading - accurate to 1 minute	1853	Mathematical extrapolation</eml:eml/dataset/abstract/para><date>2019-06-28</date></data>