<data><id>a814f323-ccc0-44b7-b188-4c155867deb7</id><eml:eml/dataset/title>Greater London Habitat Survey tree data</eml:eml/dataset/title><eml:eml/dataset/abstract/para>The dataset consists of tree records in London collated by GiGL from multiple habitat surveys commissioned by the London Ecology Unit and Greater London Authority from the mid-80s to present and by the Borough for the tree records in Wandsworth. Records were collected through habitat surveys, mostly from borough-wide surveys but some from individual site surveys.The dataset has been created by Greenspace Information for Greater London CIC (GiGL). GiGL mobilises, curates and shares data that underpin our knowledge of London&#8217;s natural environment. We provide impartial evidence to enable informed discussion and decision-making in policy and practice. Please acknowledge GiGL in any use of the data e.g. &#8220;Greenspace Information for Greater London CIC (2018). http://www.gigl.org.uk/. Accessed: [Download date].&#8221;The records range from 1983-2009. The majority of records have a full date (DD/MM/YYYY), however, a small number of records are recorded to season or month and year.Tree records from the following genera are included in this dataset: Abelia, Abies, Acacia, Acca, Acer, Aesculus, Ailanthus, Albizia, Alnus, Amelanchier, Aralia, Araucaria, Arbutus, Betula, Broussonetia, Carpobrotus, Carya, Castanea, Catalpa, Cedrus, Celtis, Cercidiphyllum, Cercis, Chamaecyparis, Chitalpa, Cornus, Corylus, Crataegus, Cryptomeria, Cunninghamia, Cupressus, Diospyros, Eucalyptus, Euonymus, Fagus, Ficus, Fraxinus, Ginkgo, Gleditsia, Hibiscus, Hippophae, Ilex, Juglans, Juniperus, Koelreuteria, Laburnum, Lagerstroemia, Larix, Ligustrum, Liquidambar, Liriodendron, Magnolia, Malus, Mespilus, Metasequoia, Morus, Nothofagus, Nyssa, Osmanthus, Ostrya, Parrotia, Photinia, Picea, Pinus, Platanus, Podocarpus, Populus, Prunus, Pseudolarix, Pseudotsuga, Pyrus, Quercus, Robinia, Salix, Sequoia, Sequoiadendron, Sophora, Sorbus, Stewartia, Styrax, Syringa, Tamarix, Taxus, Thuja, Tilia, Torreya, Trachycarpus, Tsuga, Ulmus, Zea, Zelkova, Ziziphus.</eml:eml/dataset/abstract/para><date>2018-10-15</date></data>