<data><id>adb0abac-e771-4f85-9914-b4a8b16ad74a</id><eml:eml/dataset/title>FLORA OF THE KURILSKIY NATURE RESERVE</eml:eml/dataset/title><eml:eml/dataset/abstract/para>Monitoring and inventory of the species of the Kurilsky Nature Reserve is carried out since 1984. Flora of the reserve totals 1915 species, including 374 species of mosses, 271 species of algae, 91 species of mushrooms and 214 species of lichens. The Red Data Books of the Russian Federation and the Sakhalin Region includes 104 species of vascular plants.The vegetation cover is characterized by the altitudinal zonality. Comprising 80% of the protective zone forests form the basis of the vegetation cover. Dark-coniferous forests formed by the Sakhalin fir (Abies sachalinensis), Yezzo and Glen&#8217;s spruce (Picea jezoensis, P. glehnii) account for 62% of the forested area. Deciduous forests formed by Erman's birch (Betula ermanii), Manchurian alder (Alnus hirsuta), Japanese rowan (Sorbus commixta), Mayr&#8217;s maple (Acer mayrii), tree aralia (Kalopanax septemlobus) with the undergrowth of panicled hydrangea (Hydrangea paniculata), elderberry (Sambucus miquelii), Sakhalin bilberry (Vaccinium smallii) and woody vines of the variegated-leaf hardy kiwi and hardy kiwi (Actinidia kolomikta, Actinidia arguta), climbing hydrangea (Hydrangea petiolaris), Asian poison ivy (Toxicodendron orientale) occupy 19% of the reserve. The same part of the territory (19%) is covered with the overgrowth of the Siberian dwarf pine (Pinus pumila).Demin and Oskolki Islands are characterized by meadow herbs and grasses-fruticous communities. The stem height of the main representatives of tall grasses&#8211; the Sakhalin knotweed (Reynoutria sachalinensis), bear&#8217;s angelica (Angelica ursina), Cacalia robusta, and Aleutian ragwort (Senecio cannabifolius) &#8211; reaches 4 m.A particular landscape role is played by the representatives of the Sasa genus (creeping bamboo) which form the dense impenetrable overgrowth in the forest glades and understocked stands. Bamboo helps strengthen slopes and plays a major role in soil formation thanks to a powerful root system and abundant litter. The reserve has 12 species of this plant.The flora of the reserve accounts for 1339 species, including 374 species of mosses, 263 species of algae, more than 200 species of mushrooms and more than 300 species of lichens. 104 species of vascular plants are listed in the Red Data Books of Russia (2008) and the Sakhalin Region (2005). The most interesting plants are the ones found only on Kunashir Island, in the area ofits northern border: the Amur maple (Acer japonicum), Japanese monarch birch (Betula maximowicziana), Daphniphyllum humile, Japanese rhododendron (Rhododendron tschonoskii), whitebark magnolia (Magnolia hypoleuca), Japanese hydrangea vine (Schizophragma hydrangeoides), Japanese lime (Tilia maximowicziana) and others [Barkalov, 2003].</eml:eml/dataset/abstract/para><date>2019-09-12</date></data>