<data><id>ae394d3b-5c98-4df4-beed-4b22b1bf059e</id><eml:eml/dataset/title>Micromycetes of vascular plants of the Nurata Nature Reserve, Uzbekistan</eml:eml/dataset/title><eml:eml/dataset/abstract/para>The dataset of micromycetes on vascular plants of the Nurata Nature Reserve (Nuratau Mountains, Uzbekistan) was compiled for the first time as a result of field research conducted in 2009-2017. In total, 287 species, 58 forms and 4 variations of micromycetes belonging to 80 genera, 41 families, 17 orders, 6 class and 2 division have been identified. Twenty four new records to the mycobiota of Uzbekistan were found (Mycosphaerella artemisiae Tilak, Neopseudocercosporella capsellae (Ellis &amp; Everh.) Videira &amp; Crous, Ramularia trifolii Jaap, Septoria dauci Nicolas &amp; Agg&#233;ry, Septoria trifolii Ellis, Septoria ranunculacearum L&#233;v., Septoria cyperi Ellis &amp; Everh, Rhabdospora eremuri Ohl, Rhabdospora galii Died, Diplodia celtidis Roum., Phyllosticta prostrata Brunaud, Phyllosticta trifolii Richon, Phyllosticta silenes Peck, Asteromella tanaceti (Vasyag.) Vanev &amp; Aa, Selenophoma nebulosa (Rostr.) Lavrov, Camarosporium achilleae Holl&#243;s, Phoma hedysari Th&#252;m., Phoma mororum Sacc., Hendersonia ephedrae Holl&#243;s, Erysiphe cichoracearum f. tanaceti Jacz., Diplocarpon alpestre (Sorauer) B. Sutton), Puccinia  schneideri J. Schr&#246;t., Puccinia onopordi P. Syd. &amp; Syd., Puccinia behenis G.H. Otth). The annotated checklist includes detailed information for each species, such as collection number, date, location, and host plant. The 41 species, and 10 forms of micromycetes were recorded on 45 new host plants (Aecidium ranunculacearum DC. on Ranunculus mindshelkensis B.Fedtsch., Alternaria brassicae (Berk.) Sacc. &#8211; Crambe cordifolia subsp. kotschyana (Boiss.) Jafri, Anthracoidea eleocharidis Kukkonen &#8211; Carex stenophylla subsp. stenophylloides (V.I.Krecz.) T.V.Egorova, Ascochyta pisi Lib. &#8211; Cicer grande (Popov) Korotkova, Asteromella tanaceti (Vasyag.) Vanev &amp; Aa &#8211; Tanacetopsis karataiensis (Kovalevsk.) Kovalevsk, Blumeria graminis &#8211; Poa trivialis L., Cytospora capitata Sacc. &amp; Schulzer &#8211; Pyrus regelii Rehder, Diplocarpon mespili (Sorauer) B. Sutton &#8211; Pyrus regelii Rehder, Erysiphe. cichoracearum f. lactucae Jacz. &#8211; Scariola orientalis (Boiss.) Soj&#225;k, E. cichoracearum f. tanaceti Jacz. &#8211; Lepidolopha komarowii C.Winkl., E. communis f. dianthi Jacz. &#8211; Dianthus helenae Vved., E. umbelliferarum f. ferulae Golovin &#8211; Ferula penninervis Regel &amp; Schmalh., Ferula angreni Korovin, E. umbelliferarum f. scandicis Jacz. &#8211; Physocaulis nodosus Koch, Las&#305;obotrys lonicerae (Fr.) Kunze &#8211; Lonicera bracteolaris Boiss. &amp; Buhse, Leveillula compositarum f. artemisiae (Jacz.) Golovin &#8211; Artemisia sogdiana Bunge, L. compositarum f. helichrysi (Jacz.) Golovin &#8211; Helichrysum nuratavicum Krasch., L. labiatarum f. dracocephali Golovin &#8211; Dracocephalum nuratavicum Adylov, L. labiatarum f. phlomidis (Jacz.) Golovin &#8211; Phlomis nubilans Zakirov, L. labiatarum f. scutellariae (Jacz.) Golovin &#8211; Scutellaria ramosissima Popov, Melasmia sp. &#8211; Leonurus turkestanicus V.I.Krecz. &amp; Kuprian., Phoma hyperici Allesch. &#8211; Dianthus helenae Vved., Ph.  astragali-alpini Oudem. &#8211; Astragalus sieversianus Pall., Phyllosticta werestshagini Murashk. &#8211; Rindera tetraspis Pall., Puccinia celakovskyana Bub&#225;k &#8211; Galium karakulense Pobed., P.  conferta &#8211; Artemisia juncea Kar. &amp; Kir., P. cousiniae P. Syd. &amp; Syd. &#8211; Cousinia eriotricha Juz., C. pseudodshisakensis Tschern. &amp; Vved., P. echinopsis DC. &#8211; Echinops nuratavicus A.D.Li, P. monticola Kom. &#8211; Geranium linearilobum DC, P. onopordi P. Syd. &amp; Syd. &#8211; Onopordum olgae Regel &amp; Schmalh., P. persistens  Plowr. &#8211; Thalictrum isopyroides C.A. Mey., P. phlomidis Th&#252;m. &#8211; Leonurus turkestanicus, Phlomis thapsoides Bunge, P. pyrethri Rabenh. &#8211; Tanacetopsis karataiensis (Kovalevsk.) Kovalevsk., P. schneideri J. Schr&#246;t. &#8211; Thymus seravschanicus Klokov, P. sogdiana Kom. &#8211; Ferula angreni Korovin, Ramularia filaris Fresen. &#8211; Prunus domestica L., Rhabdospora sp. &#8211; Ixiolirion tataricum (Pall.) Schult. &amp; chult.f., Septoria  hyperici Roberge ex Desm. &#8211; Hypericum perforatum L., S. meliloti (Lasch) Sacc. &#8211; Melilotus albus Medik., Sphaerotheca fugax Penz. &amp; Sacc. &#8211; Geranium rotundifolium L., Sph. fuliginea Jacz. &#8211; Lophanthus schtschurowskianus (Regel) Lipsky, Sph. fuliginea f. sedi Kalymb. &#8211; Pseudosedum lievenii (Ledeb.) A. Berger, Sphaerotheca sp. &#8211; Orthurus kokanicus Juz., Tranzscheliella otophora Lavrov &#8211; Stipa lipskyi Roshev., Urocystis sorosporioides &#8211; Thalictrum sultanabadense Stapf, Uromyces acantholimonis Syd. &amp; P. Syd. &#8211; Acantholimon nuratavicum Zakirov, Valsa ceratophora Tul. &amp; C. Tul. &#8211; Amygdalus bucharica Korsh., Vankya heufleri (Fuckel) Ershad &#8211; Tulipa turkestanica (Regel) Regel). The dataset includes information for each species, such as collection number, date, location, and host plant.</eml:eml/dataset/abstract/para><date>2018-05-19</date></data>