<data><id>bda0bc4d-4818-4c32-81f2-08c227ce83cb</id><eml:eml/dataset/title>BID-AF2015-0004-NAC ETUDES DES ESPECES EN  ZONE INDUSTRIELLE (SCANTOGO)AU TOGO</eml:eml/dataset/title><eml:eml/dataset/abstract/para>Mining in all its phases causes huge loss of biodiversity through habitat fragmentation that transform significantly and affects the landscape in which it takes place. In the short, medium or long term, it may endanger the well-being and even the survival of riparian populations. In the context of sustainable development which requires the integration of environmental, social and economic components, this research aims not only to the restoration of biodiversity in Sika-Kondji quarry landscape but through it, the socioeconomic well-being of riparian populations. Specifically it aims to characterize and map habitats of this landscape and potentials ecological corridors that connect them. On the other hand, it also aims to identify various activities of riparian populations related to ecosystems, characteristics and socioeconomic importance of these activities. To reach these objectives, Google Earth images of study area were been photo-interpreted and digitized using Google Earth Pro software coupled with QGIS software in order to have land cover map on which spatial analysis allow to detect  potentials ecological corridors. Floristic, forest and ecological inventories were done using sigmatiste approach of Braun-blanquet. Socioeconomic surveys were also done. The treatment of data was done using Excel, Minitab 16 and CAP softwares. At the end of this research, it appears that the landscape of the study area is predominantly agricultural landscape containing significant biodiversity. A total of 225 species belonging to 172 genera and 55 families were identified and four (04) phytosociological groups were discriminated according to two (2) ecological gradients: submersion and soil texture. The Shannon index and Pielou equitability of these groups show regular distribution of species. Weibull distribution of diameters and heights, associated to low densities of wood species show that these groups are youngers and much degraded. Investigations revealed that agriculture, firewood collecting, hunting, fishing and timber exploitation are main activities of riparian population in ecosystems. Unfortunately these activities may adversely affect these ecosystems if adequate actions are not done. In order to solve this problem, recommendations and study landscape zoning plan have been proposed.</eml:eml/dataset/abstract/para><date>2018-08-01</date></data>