<data><id>f67d4560-51fa-4443-9ce3-acced5515eec</id><eml:eml/dataset/title>Further investigations of the effects of the Nella Dan oil spill 1988/94</eml:eml/dataset/title><eml:eml/dataset/abstract/para>Metadata record for data expected from ASAC Project 1003Further investigations of the effects of the Nella Dan oil spill on intertidal benthic communities at Macquarie Island: continued recovery of kelp holdfast communities.See the link below for public details on this project.The project investigated spatial variation in kelp holdfast macrofaunal communities 7 years after the initial oil spill. The project was expanded to cover more sites than were sampled in projects 250 (ASAC_250) and 672 (ASAC_672). Results indicated that an impact was still detectable at one of the 3 oiled sites.This dataset contains the 1988 and 1994 data. Holdfast data from the 1994/1995 season is also included (comparing east versus west).The numbers are total individuals of each species that were found in each holdfast sample. This is a basic, though standard, species-abundance matrix.The site codes used in this project are:SB = Sandy BaySEC = Secluded BayBB = Buckles BayGC = Garden CoveGG = Green GorgeGB = Goat BayHMB = Half Moon BayBAUER = Bauer BayOther codes as for oil spill dataThe first number given after the site code is the site number at that sampling location. The second number is the replicate at that site. Thus sb(1)3 is Sandy Bay site 1, replicate 3.The fields in this dataset are:SpeciesYearSiteQuality: 2018-08-28 - The original datasheet was reformatted to fit OBIS/GBFI/IPT Biodiversity.AQ standards. The new datasheet "DurvillaeaHoldfastAssocFauna88_94.csv" provides the data of fauna associated with holdfast of Durvillaea antarctica from Macquarie Island, samples were collected in 1988 and 1994. This new data sheet contains datasetID, occurrenceID, country, event date, decimal latitude, decimal longitude, locality, eventDate, eventRemarks, basisOfRecord, occurrenceStatus, organismQuantity, organismQunatityType, associatedTaxa and associatedReference. It also provides species identification to the lowest taxonomical rank that could be determined. Species names are matched in WoRMS (World Register of Marine Species).</eml:eml/dataset/abstract/para><date>2018-10-16</date></data>