<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.820375</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Growth, respiration and photophysiology of coral massive Porites spp. in the experiment of Moorea</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>I tested the hypothesis that high pCO2 (76.6 Pa and 87.2 Pa vs. 42.9 Pa) has no effect on the metabolism of juvenile massive Porites spp. after 11 days at 28 &#176;C and 545 &#181;mol quanta/m**2/s. The response was assessed as aerobic dark respiration, skeletal weight (i.e., calcification), biomass, and chlorophyll fluorescence. Corals were collected from the shallow (3-4 m) back reef of Moorea, French Polynesia (17&#176;28.614'S, 149&#176;48.917'W), and experiments conducted during April and May 2011. An increase in pCO2 to 76.6 Pa had no effect on any dependent variable, but 87.2 Pa pCO2 reduced area-normalized (but not biomass-normalized) respiration 36 %, as well as maximum photochemical efficiency (Fv/Fm) of open RCIIs and effective photochemical efficiency of RCIIs in actinic light (Delta F/F'm ), neither biomass, calcification, nor the energy expenditure coincident with calcification (J/g) was effected. These results do not support the hypothesis that high pCO2 reduces coral calcification through increased metabolic costs and, instead, suggest that high pCO2 causes metabolic depression and photochemical impairment similar to that associated with bleaching. Evidence of a pCO2 threshold between 76.6 and 87.2 Pa for inhibitory effects on respiration and photochemistry deserves further attention as it might signal the presence of unpredictable effects of rising pCO2.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Alkalinity, total, Alkalinity, total, standard error, Animalia, Aragonite saturation state, Aragonite saturation state, standard error, Benthic animals, Benthos, Bicarbonate ion, Biomass, Calcification/Dissolution, Calcification rate of calcium carbonate, Calcite saturation state, Calculated using CO2SYS, Calculated using seacarb after Nisumaa et al. (2010), Carbon, inorganic, dissolved, Carbonate ion, Carbonate system computation flag, Carbon dioxide, Cnidaria, Coast and continental shelf, Containers and aquaria (20- 1000 L or &lt; 1 m**2), Effective photochemical quantum yield, Excitation pressure, EXP, Experiment, Fluorescence, Fluorescence, maximum, French Polynesia, Fugacity of carbon dioxide (water) at sea surface temperature (wet air), Growth/Morphology, Irradiance, Irradiance, standard error, Laboratory experiment, Maximum photochemical quantum yield of photosystem II, Metabolic expenditure, Moorea, OA-ICC, Ocean Acidification International Coordination Centre, Partial pressure of carbon dioxide (water) at sea surface temperature (wet air), Partial pressure of carbon dioxide (water) at sea surface temperature (wet air), standard error, pH, pH, standard error, Porites sp., Potentiometric titration, Primary production/Photosynthesis, Respiration, Respiration rate, oxygen, Salinity, Sample code/label, Single species, South Pacific, Species, Spectrophotometric, Surface area, Temperature, water, Temperature, water, standard error, Treatment, Tropical</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2012-11-13</date></data>