<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.778272</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>(Appendix) Late Cretaceous calcareous nannofossils of DSDP Holes 80-549 and 80-551</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>he early late Cretaceous (Cenomanian&#8211;early Turonian) is thought to have been one of the warmest periods of the Phanerozoic. This period was characterised by tropical sea surface temperatures of up to 36 &#176;C and a pole-to-equator-gradient of less than 10 &#176;C. The subsequent Turonian&#8211;Maastrichtian was characterised by a continuous climatic cooling, peaking in the Maastrichtian. This climatic cooling and the resulting palaeoceanographic changes had an impact on planktic primary producer communities including calcareous nannofossils. In order to gain a better understanding of these Cenomanian&#8211;Maastrichtian palaeoceanographic changes, calcareous nannofossils have been studied from the proto North Atlantic (Goban Spur, DSDP Sites 549, 551). In order to see potential differences between open oceanic and shelf dwelling nannofossils, the data from Goban Spur have been compared to findings from the European shelf (northern Germany).A total of 77 samples from Goban Spur were studied for calcareous nannofossils revealing abundant (mean 6.2 billion specimens/g sediment) and highly diverse (mean 63 species/sample) nannofossil assemblages. The dominant taxa are Watznaueria spp. (mean 30.7%), Prediscosphaera spp. (mean 18.3%), Zeugrhabdotus spp. (mean 8.3%), Retecapsa spp. (mean 7.2%) and Biscutum spp. (mean 6.6%). The Cenomanian assemblages of both Goban Spur (open ocean) and Wunstorf (shelf) are characterised by elevated abundances of high fertility taxa like Biscutum spp., Zeugrhabdotus spp. and Tranolithus orionatus. Early Turonian to Maastrichtian calcareous nannofossil assemblages of Goban Spur are, however, quite different to those described from European sections. Oceanic taxa like Watznaueria spp., Retecapsa spp. and Cribrosphearella ehrenbergii dominate in Goban Spur whereas the fertility indicators Biscutum spp. and T. orionatus are more abundant in the European shelf assemblages. This shift from a homogeneous distribution of calcareous nannofossils in the Cenomanian towards a heterogeneous one in the Turonian&#8211;Maastrichtian implies a change of the ocean circulation. The &#8220;eddy ocean&#8221; system of the Cenomanian was replaced by an oceanic circulation similar to the modern one in the Turonian&#8211;Maastrichtian, caused by the cooling. The increased pole-to-equator-gradients resulted in an oceanic circulation similar to the modern one.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>80-549, 80-551, Ahmuellerella octoradiata, Ahmuellerella regularis, Amphizygus brooksii, Angulofenestrella cf. snyderi, Arkhangelskiella cymbiformis, Assipetra sp., Axopodorhabdus albianus, Biscutum constans, Biscutum coronum, Biscutum ellipticum, Biscutum magnum, Biscutum melaniae, Biscutum notaculum, Braarudosphaera africana, Braarudosphaera bigelowii, Broinsonia enormis, Broinsonia matalosa, Broinsonia parca constricta, Broinsonia parca expansa, Broinsonia parca parca, Broinsonia signata, Bukrylithus ambiguus, Calculites cf. obscurus, Calculites sp., Ceratolithoides aculeus, Ceratolithoides amplector, Ceratolithoides indiensis, Ceratolithoides longissimus, Chiastozygus antiquus, Chiastozygus bifarius, Chiastozygus litterarius, Chiastozygus platyrhethus, Chiastozygus synquadriperforatus, Chiastozygus trabalis, Corollithion completum, Corollithion exiguum, Corollithion kennedyi, Corollithion madagaskarensis, Corollithion signum, Cretarhabdus conicus, Cretarhabdus striatus, Cribrocorona gallica, Cribrosphaerella ehrenbergii, Cribrosphaerella sp., Cruciellipsis sp., Cyclagelosphaera reinhardtii, Cyclagelosphaera sp., Cylindralithus sculptus, Cylindralithus serratus, Deep Sea Drilling Project, DEPTH, sediment/rock, Diazomatolithus lehmanii, Discorhabdus ignotus, Diversity, simple, DRILL, Drilling/drill rig, DSDP, Eiffellithus cf. eximius, Eiffellithus eximius, Eiffellithus gorkae, Eiffellithus hancockii, Eiffellithus parallelus, Eiffellithus sp., Eiffellithus turriseiffelii, Eprolithus eptapetalus, Eprolithus floralis, Eprolithus octopetalus, Eprolithus rarus, Eprolithus sp., Eprolithus spp., Evenness of species, Event label, Flabellites oblongus, Gartnerago obliquum, Gartnerago segmentatum, Gartnerago theta, Glomar Challenger, Grantarhabdus coronadventis, Haqius circumradiatus, Helenea chiastia, Helicolithus compactus, Helicolithus trabeculatus, Kamptnerius magnificus, Lapideacassis blackii, Lapideacassis glans, Leg80, Lithraphidites acutus, Lithraphidites carniolensis, Lithraphidites praequadratus, Lithraphidites pseudoquadratus, Lithraphidites quadratus, Loxolithus armilla, Lucianorhabdus cf. cayeuxii, Lucianorhabdus cf. quadrifidus, Manivitella pemmatoidea, Markalius inversus, Marthasterites simplex, Micrantholithus obtusus, Microrhabdulus decoratus, Micula concava, Micula decussata, Micula murus, Micula swastica, Miravestina berganii, Misceomarginatus pleniporus, Nannoconus sp., Nannofossils, Nannofossil zone, Neocrepidolithus sp., Nephrolithus frequens, North Atlantic/ESCARPMENT, North Atlantic/SPUR, Octocyclus reinhardtii, ODP sample designation, Orastrum campanense, Palaeopontosphaera sp., Perchnielsenella stradneri, Percivalia fenestrata, Perissocyclus fenestratus, Pervilithus varius, Petrarhabdus copulatus, Petrarhabdus vietus, Placozygus cf. fibuliformis, Placozygus fibuliformis, Prediscosphaera arkhangelskyi, Prediscosphaera cf. stoveri, Prediscosphaera cretacea, Prediscosphaera grandis, Prediscosphaera majungae, Prediscosphaera microrhabdulina, Prediscosphaera sp., Prediscosphaera spinosa, Prediscosphaera spp., Prolatipatella multicarinata, Quadrum eneabrachium, Quadrum eptabrachium, Quadrum gartneri, Quadrum hexabrachium, Quadrum intermedium, Radiolithus planus, Reinhardtites anthophorus, Reinhardtites cf. levis, Reinhardtites levis, Retecapsa angustiforata, Retecapsa crenulata, Retecapsa ficula, Retecapsa schizobrachiata, Retecapsa spp., Retecapsa surirella, Rhagodiscus achlyostaurion, Rhagodiscus angustus, Rhagodiscus asper, Rhagodiscus indistinctus, Rhagodiscus splendens, Rotelapillus biarcus, Rotelapillus crenulatus, Rotelapillus nieliae, Rotelapillus sp., Rucinolithus hayi, Rucinolithus magnus, Rucinolithus sp., Sample code/label, Scapholithus fossilis, Seribiscutum primitivum, Shannon Diversity Index, Staurolithites cf. gausorhethium, Staurolithites ellipticus, Staurolithites flavus, Staurolithites imbricatus, Staurolithites mielnicensis, Staurolithites mutterlosei, Staurolithites sp., Stoverius achylosus, Tegumentum stradneri, Tetrapodorhabdus decorus, Tortolithus hallii, Tranolithus minimus, Tranolithus orionatus, Tubodiscus sp., Uniplanarius gothicus, Uniplanarius sissinghii, Uniplanarius trifidus, Watznaueria barnesiae, Watznaueria biporta, Watznaueria britannica, Watznaueria fossacincta, Watznaueria ovata, Watznaueria spp., Zeugrhabdotus bicrescenticus, Zeugrhabdotus biperforatus, Zeugrhabdotus diplogrammus, Zeugrhabdotus elegans, Zeugrhabdotus embergeri, Zeugrhabdotus erectus, Zeugrhabdotus noeliae, Zeugrhabdotus praesigmoides, Zeugrhabdotus scutula, Zeugrhabdotus sigmoides, Zeugrhabdotus spp., Zygodiscus tunisiensis</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2011-03-27</date></data>