<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.896100</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Data on bird communities on the study plots of the Kilimanjaro Research Unit including all bird individuals observed during point counts</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>We used audiovisual point counts on eight subplots per plot to record birds in the warm dry season (December to March) and in the cold dry season (July to October). We established circles with a 20-m radius in densely vegetated habitats (savanna and all forest habitats) and 35.5 m &#215; 35.5 m squares at Helichrysum plots, covering the same sampling area in all habitat types. All birds heard or seen in one subplot were counted for 10 min and identified to species level. Point counts started 15 min before sunrise and were completed before 09:00. All 480 point counts (30 plots &#215; 8 subplots &#215; 2 seasons) were conducted by the same observer (Ferger S. W.) to reduce inter-observer variability. This dataset contains also bird individuals that were recorded higher than maximum canopy height at the respective subplots in the respective season (see publication for details).</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>according to Stevenson &amp; Fanshawe, ALTITUDE, Area/locality, Barometer, Comment, Counted, DATE/TIME, Date/time end, Date/time start, Distance, Event label, Global positioning system (GPS), Habitat, Height, Investigator, KiLi, KiLi_cof1, KiLi_cof2, KiLi_cof3, KiLi_cof4, KiLi_cof5, KiLi_fer0, KiLi_fer1, KiLi_fer2, KiLi_fer3, KiLi_fer4, KiLi_flm1, KiLi_flm2, KiLi_flm3, KiLi_flm4, KiLi_flm5, KiLi_foc1, KiLi_foc2, KiLi_foc3, KiLi_foc4, KiLi_foc5, KiLi_fod1, KiLi_fod2, KiLi_fod3, KiLi_fod4, KiLi_fod5, KiLi_fpd1, KiLi_fpd2, KiLi_fpd3, KiLi_fpd4, KiLi_fpd5, KiLi_fpo1, KiLi_fpo2, KiLi_fpo3, KiLi_fpo4, KiLi_fpo5, KiLi_gra1, KiLi_gra2, KiLi_gra3, KiLi_gra4, KiLi_gra5, KiLi_hel1, KiLi_hel2, KiLi_hel3, KiLi_hel4, KiLi_hel5, KiLi_hom1, KiLi_hom2, KiLi_hom3, KiLi_hom4, KiLi_hom5, KiLi_mai1, KiLi_mai2, KiLi_mai3, KiLi_mai4, KiLi_mai5, KiLi_sav1, KiLi_sav2, KiLi_sav3, KiLi_sav4, KiLi_sav5, KiLi_sun1, KiLi_sun2, KiLi_sun3, KiLi_sun4, Kilimanjaro Research Group, LATITUDE, LONGITUDE, Mount Kilimanjaro, Tanzania, Number, Number of birds, Observation, Plot, Season, Species</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2018-11-19</date></data>