<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.891228</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Different Mid-Pleistocene transition analysis from IODP Site 306-U1314</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Marine sediments from the Integrated Ocean Drilling Project (IODP) Site U1314 (56.36&#176;N, 27.88&#176;W), in the subpolar North Atlantic, were studied for their planktonic foraminifera, calcium carbonate content, and Neogloboqudrina pachyderma sinistral (sin.) &#948;13C records in order to reconstruct surface and intermediate conditions in this region during the Mid&#8208;Pleistocene Transition (MPT). Variations in the palaeoceanography and regional dynamics of the Arctic Front were estimated by comparing CaCO3 content, planktonic foraminiferal species abundances, carbon isotopes and ice&#8208;rafted debris (IRD) data from Site U1314 with published data from other North Atlantic sites. Site U1314 exhibited high abundances of the polar planktonic foraminifera N.&#8201;pachyderma sin. and low CaCO3 content until Marine Isotope Stage (MIS) 26, indicating a relatively southeastward position of the Arctic Front (AF) and penetration of colder and low&#8208;salinity surface arctic water&#8208;masses. Changing conditions after MIS 25, with oscillations in the position of the AF, caused an increase in the northward export of the warmer North Atlantic Current (NAC), indicated by greater abundances of non&#8208;polar planktonic foraminifera and higher CaCO3. The N.&#8201;pachyderma sin. &#948;13C data indicate good ventilation of the upper part of the intermediate water layer in the eastern North Atlantic during both glacial and interglacial stages, except during Terminations 24/23, 22/21 and 20/1. In addition, for N.&#8201;pachyderma (sin.) we distinguished two morphotypes: non&#8208;encrusted and heavily encrusted test. Results indicate that increases in the encrusted morphotype and lower planktonic foraminiferal diversity are related to the intensification of glacial conditions (lower sea&#8208;surface temperatures, sea&#8208;ice formation) during MIS 22 and 20.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Integrated Ocean Drilling Program / International Ocean Discovery Program, IODP</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2018-06-19</date></data>