<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.122790</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Abundance of living coccolithophores in the northern Arabian Sea (Table 2)</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>The present study was conducted to provide information about living coccolithophores from the northern Arabian Sea as potential proxies in palaeoceanographic studies. In all, 71 plankton samples from 16 stations collected in September 1993 were analysed for their contents of living coccolithophores. Absolute abundances range from less than 400 coccospheres per litre in surface waters to 35 000 spheres per litre at intermediate water depths. From 49 identified taxa, nine species contribute significant cell numbers of more than 2000 coccospheres per litre and comprise more than 10% of the communities in at least one sample. Important species are (in approximate order of cell abundances): Gephyrocapsa oceanica, Florisphaera profunda, Oolithotus antillarum, Calciosolenia murrayi, Umbellosphaera irregularis, Emiliania huxleyi, Umbellosphaera tenuis, Calciopappus rigidus, and Algirosphaera robusta. At most profiles, a vertical succession of coccolithophore species was found. Calciosolenia murrayi and C. rigidus were restricted to surface waters, whereas high numbers of F. profunda and A. robusta occurred at depths below 40 m. The coccolithophore communities reflected the local oceanographic situation and seemed to be more dependent on mixed layer depth and nutrient availability than on temperature and salinity changes. Additionally, synecologic competition with diatoms in part controlled the species composition and generally reduced the abundance of coccolithophores. Synecological and ecological tolerances of species were discussed with the help of cluster analysis.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Algirosphaera robusta, Arabian Sea, Calciopappus rigidus, Calciosolenia murrayi, DEPTH, water, Emiliania huxleyi, Event label, Florisphaera profunda, Gephyrocapsa oceanica, MS, Multisonde, Nanoplankton, Nanoplankton, other, Oolithotus antillarum, PAKOMIN, SO90, SO90_101MS, SO90_117MS, SO90_122MS, SO90_16MS, SO90_170MS, SO90_185MS, SO90_26MS, SO90_32MS, SO90_36MS, SO90_45MS, SO90_48MS, SO90_5MS, SO90_73MS, SO90_80MS, SO90_89MS, SO90_8MS, Sonne, Syracosphaeraceae, Umbellosphaera irregularis, Umbellosphaera tenuis</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2003-10-08</date></data>