<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.836852</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Zooplankton abundance and size structure in the North Atlantic from M87/1_466-1</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Data on zooplankton abundance and biovolume were collected in concert with data on the biophysical environment during the development of the phytoplankton spring bloom at 4 stations in the North Atlantic. Station 1 in the Icelandic Basin was visited four times (26 March, 8 April, 18 April, 27 April), Station 2 in the southern Norwegian Sea was visited three times (30 March, 13 April, 23 April), Station 3 in the North Sea was visited twice (2 April, 15 April) and one intermediate station was visited once. The data were sampled by a Laser Optical Plankton Counter (LOPC, Rolls Royce Canada Ltd.) that was mounted on a carousel water sampler together with a Conductivity-Temperature-Depth sensor (CTD, SBE19plusV2, Seabird Electronics, Inc., USA). Based on the LOPC data, abundance (individuals/m**3) and biovolume (mm3/m**3) were calculated as described in the LOPC Software Operation Manual [(Anonymous, 2006), http://www.brooke-ocean.com/index.html]. LOPC data were regrouped into 49 size groups of equal log10 (body volume) increments (Edvardsen et al., 2002, doi:10.3354/meps227205). LOPC data quality was checked as described in Basedow et al. (2013, doi:10.1016/j.pocean.2012.10.005). CTD data were screened for erroneous (out of range) values and then averaged to the same frequency as the LOPC data (2 Hz). All data were processed using especially developed scripts in the python programming language. The LOPC is an optical instrument designed to count and measure particles (0.1 to 30 mm equivalent spherical diameter) in the water column (Herman et al., 2004, doi:10.1093/plankt/fbh095). The size of particles as equivalent spherical diameter (ESD) was computed as described in the manual (Anonymous, 2006), and in more detail in Checkley et al. (2008, doi:10.4319/lo.2008.53.5_part_2.2123) and Gaardsted et al. (2010, doi:10.1111/j.1365-2419.2010.00558.x).</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Abundance per volume, Basin Scale Analysis, Synthesis and Integration, Biovolume per volume, Calculated, Chlorophyll total, CTD/Rosette, CTD-RO, DATE/TIME, Deep Convection Cruise, DEPTH, water, EURO-BASIN, Latitude of event, Longitude of event, LOPC-CTD-F (Laser Optical Plankton counter together with CTD and fluorescence sensor), M87/1_466-1, M87/1a, Meteor (1986), Number, Salinity, Station 2, Temperature, water</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2014-10-17</date></data>