<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.315208</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Range table from nannofossils in ODP Hole 159-959A</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description /><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>159-959A, Abundance estimate, Calcidiscus leptoporus, Calcidiscus macintyrei, Clausioccus sp. cf. C. fenestratus, Coccolithus eopelagicus, Coccolithus miopelagicus, Coccolithus pelagicus, Coronocyclus nitescens, Cyclicargolithus abisectus, Cyclicargolithus floridanus, Depth, composite, DEPTH, sediment/rock, Dictyococcites bisectus, Discoaster adamanteus, Discoaster calcaris, Discoaster calculosus, Discoaster deflandrei, Discoaster divaricatus, Discoaster druggii, Discoaster exilis, Discoaster icarus, Discoaster lidzi, Discoaster nephados, Discoaster petaliformis, Discoaster saundersi, Discoaster sp. cf. D. exilis, Discoaster sp. cf. D. variabilis, DRILL, Drilling/drill rig, Geminilithella rotula, Gulf of Guinea, Hayaster perplexus, Helicosphaera acuta, Helicosphaera ampliaperta, Helicosphaera elongata, Helicosphaera euphratis, Helicosphaera gartneri, Helicosphaera intermedia, Helicosphaera kamptneri, Helicosphaera mediterranea, Helicosphaera obliqua, Helicosphaera recta, Helicosphaera scissura, Helicosphaera stalis, Helicosphaera truempyi, Joides Resolution, Leg159, Nannofossil abundance, Nannofossils preservation, Ocean Drilling Program, ODP, ODP sample designation, Orthorhabdus serratus, Pontosphaera multipora, Reticulofenestra gartneri, Reticulofenestra haqii, Reticulofenestra lockeri, Reticulofenestra minuta, Reticulofenestra minutula, Sample code/label, Solidopons petrae, Sphenolithus abies, Sphenolithus belemnos, Sphenolithus capricornutus, Sphenolithus ciperoensis, Sphenolithus compactus, Sphenolithus conicus, Sphenolithus dissimilis, Sphenolithus distentus, Sphenolithus elongatus, Sphenolithus heteromorphus, Sphenolithus moriformis, Sphenolithus predistentus, Tetralithoides symeonidesii, Triquetrorhabdulus auritus, Triquetrorhabdulus carinatus, Triquetrorhabdulus milowii</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2005-07-18</date></data>