<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.848615</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Underway measurements of dissolved gases along POLARSTERN cruise track ANT-XXVII/2</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>We present measurements of pCO2, O2 concentration, biological oxygen saturation (Delta O2/Ar) and N2 saturation (Delta N2) in Southern Ocean surface waters during austral summer, 2010-2011. Phytoplankton biomass varied strongly across distinct hydrographic zones, with high chlorophyll a (Chla) concentrations in regions of frontal mixing and sea-ice melt. pCO2 and Delta O2 /Ar exhibited large spatial gradients (range 90 to 450 &#181;atm and -10 to 60%, respectively) and co-varied strongly with Chla. However, the ratio of biological O2 accumulation to dissolved inorganic carbon (DIC) drawdown was significantly lower than expected from photosynthetic stoichiometry, reflecting the differential time-scales of O2 and CO2 air-sea equilibration. We measured significant oceanic CO2 uptake, with a mean air-sea flux (~ -20 mmol m-2 d-1) that significantly exceeded regional climatological values. N2 was mostly supersaturated in surface waters (mean Delta N2 of +2.5 %), while physical processes resulted in both supersaturation and undersaturation of mixed layer O2 (mean Delta O2phys = 2.1 %). Box model calculations were able to reproduce much of the spatial variability of Delta N2 and Delta O2phys along the cruise track, demonstrating significant effects of air-sea exchange processes (e.g. atmospheric pressure changes and bubble injection) and mixed layer entrainment on surface gas disequilibria. Net community production (NCP) derived from entrainment-corrected surface Delta O2 /Ar data, ranged from ~ -40 to &gt; 300 mmol O2 m-2 d-1 and showed good coherence with independent NCP estimates based on seasonal mixed layer DIC deficits. Elevated NCP was observed in hydrographic frontal zones and regions of sea-ice melt with shallow mixed layer depths, reflecting the importance of mixing in controlling surface water light and nutrient availability.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>ANT-XXVII/2, CT, DATE/TIME, DEPTH, water, derived, Gas Tension Device, LATITUDE, LONGITUDE, Nitrogen, partial pressure, Nitrogen, total dissolved, Nitrogen saturation, OCEANET, Oxygen, Oxygen, partial pressure, Oxygen optode, Aanderaa, type 3830, Oxygen saturation, Polarstern, Pressure, atmospheric, Pressure, total, dissolved gases, PS77, PS77/2-track, Salinity, Ships weather station, South Atlantic Ocean, Temperature, water, Thermosalinograph, Underway cruise track measurements</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2015-08-07</date></data>