<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.810696</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>(Table 14) Benthic foraminifera in late Miocene sediments of DSDP Hole 90-592</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description /><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>90-592, Alabamina haitiensis, Anomalina globulosa, Anomalina semicribrata, Anomalinoides cf. alazanensis, Anomalinoides globulosa, Bolivinopsis praelonga, Brizalina pusilla, Brizalina reticulata, Bulimina striata, Bulimina truncana, Cassidulina crassa, Chrysalogonium equisetiformis, Cibicides lobatulus, Cibicides spp., Cibicides wuellerstorfi, Cibicidoides bradyi, Cibicidoides cf. cicatricosus, Cibicidoides cf. ungerianus, Cibicidoides cicatricosus, Cibicidoides subhaidingeri, Deep Sea Drilling Project, Dentalina neugeboreni, DEPTH, sediment/rock, Discanomalina semiipunctata, DRILL, Drilling/drill rig, DSDP, Eggerella bradyi, Ehrenbergina pacifica, Fissurina capillosa, Foraminifera, benthic preservation, Globocassidulina subglobosa, Glomar Challenger, Heterolepa kullenbergi, Heterolepa rugosa, Holmanella sp., Hopkinsina mioindex, Karreriella bradyi, Karreriella cf. baccata, Karreriella subrotunda, Laticarinina altocamerata, Laticarinina bullbrooki, Laticarinina halophora, Leg90, Martinottiella antarctica, Martinottiella communis, Martinottiella variabilis, Melonis affinis, Melonis barleeanus, Melonis nicobarensis, Miliolidae, Nodosaria consobrina, Nodosaria stiliformis, ODP sample designation, Oridorsalis umbonatus, Orthomorphina perversa, Osangularia bengalensis, Planktonic foraminifera zone, Planulina sp., Pleurostomella alternans, Pullenia bulloides, Pullenia coryelli, Pullenia quadriloba, Pullenia quinqueloba, Pyrgo murrhina, Rectuvigerina ongelyi, Rectuvigerina spinea, Sample code/label, Sigmoilopsis schlumbergeri, Siphonina australis, Siphotextularia catenata, South Pacific/Tasman Sea/CONT RISE, Sphaeroidina bulloides, Stilostomella insecta, Stilostomella lepidula, Stilostomella pomuligera, Stilostomella subspinosa, Textularia agglutinans, Textularia lythostrata, Textularia sp., Uvigerina gemmaeformis, Uvigerina hispida, Uvigerina hispidocostata, Uvigerina hornbrooki, Uvigerina proboscidea, Uvigerina striata, Uvigerina striatissima</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>1986-04-25</date></data>