<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.833819</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Clearence rates by Calanus finmarchicus and Calanus helgolandicus determined experimentally</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>We studied the response in development times of Calanus finmarchicus and Calanus helgolandicus to changes in temperature and food conditions. The ingestion response to temperature was determined in the laboratory, where the copepods C. finmarchicus and C. helgolandicus were fed the diatom Thalassiosira weissflogii (cultivated at 18&#176;C-20&#176;, 12 : 12 light :dark cycle, exponential growth). C. finmarchicus was obtained for experiments from the Gullmar fjord. C. finmarchicus was incubated at in situ temperature (5&#176;C) until the experiments were performed. First-generation cultures were grown in the laboratory at 15&#176;C from the eggs from the Sta. L4 females. During growth both C. finmarchicus and C. helgolandicus cultures were fed a mixture of the cryptophyte Rhodomonas salina, the diatom Thalassiosira weissflogii, and the dinoflagellate Prorocentrum minimum. Five 600-mL glass bottles containing 1400 cells mL**-1 or 5 mg chlorophyll a (Chl a) L**-1 of T. weissflogii (200 mg C) and 1-2 C. finmarchicus or C. helgolandicus copepodite stage 5 (CV) or females were incubated in darkness at series of temperatures between 1&#176;C and 21 &#177; 0.5&#176;C. Three bottles without copepods served as control. In the C. helgolandicus experiment, T. weissflogii cells were counted at the beginning and end of the experiment in the grazing bottles and controls using a Coulter CounterH (MultisizerTM 3, Beckman Coulter). In the C. finmarchicus experiment, phytoplankton reduction was determined by Chl a measurements. The reduction in phytoplankton during any of the experiments was generally below 20% and never more than 32%. Clearance rates were calculated following Harris et al. (2000).</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Basin Scale Analysis, Synthesis and Integration, C_finmarchicus_FOODEXP, C_helgolandicus_FOODEXP, Calanus finmarchicus, clearance rate, Calanus helgolandicus, clearance rate, Date/Time of event, English Channel, EURO-BASIN, Event label, Gullmar Fjord, Skagerrak, Sweden, Latitude of event, Longitude of event, Net, NET, Replicates, Standard error, Temperature, water, Treatment: light intensity</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2014-07-07</date></data>