<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.123359</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Counts of polycystine radiolarian at station TT007_10-MOC19</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description /><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>02290054 MOC19, Acanthocorys variabilis, Acrosphaera murrayana, Acrosphaera spinosa, Actinomma arcadophorum/medianum, Actinomma cf. hystrix, Actinomma leptodermum, Amphirhopalum ypsilon, Amphisplecta cf. acrostoma, Antarctissa strelkovi/denticulata, Anthocyrtidium ophirense, Anthocyrtidium zanguebaricum, Arachnocorys umbelifera, Axoprunum stauraxonium, Botryocyrtis scutum, Botryostrobus aquilonaris, Botryostrobus auritus/australis, Callimitra emmae, Carpocanarium papillosum group, Carpocanistrum spp., Cladoscenium cf. tricolpum, Collosphaera huxleyi, Collosphaera tuberosa, Coracalyptra cervus, Cornutella profunda, Counting, Cycladophora davisiana cornutoides, Cycladophora davisiana davisiana, Dendrospyris borealis, Depth, bottom/max, Depth, top/min, DEPTH, water, Desmospyris anthocyrtoides/stabilis, Dictyoceras acanthicum, Dictyocoryne profunda, Dictyocoryne truncatum, Dictyophimus bicornis/columba, Dictyophimus cf. tripus, Dictyophimus clevei, Dictyophimus crisiae/hirundo group, Dictyophimus gracilipes, Dictyophimus infabricatus, Dictyophimus platycephalus, Disolenia quadrata/zanguebarica, Druppatractus pyriformis/irregularis, Equatorial Pacific, Eucecryphalus sp., Euchitonia elegans/furcata, Euchitonia triangulum, Eucyrtidium acuminatum, Eucyrtidium hexagonatum, Giraffospyris angulata, Heliodiscus asteriscus, Helotholus histricosa, Hexacontium laevigatum/enthacanthum, Hexapyle spp., Hymeniastrum euclidis, JGOFS, Joint Global Ocean Flux Study, Lamprocyclas maritalis group, Lamprocyrtis hannai, Lamprocyrtis nigriniae, Lampromitra cf. coronata, Lampromitra quadricuspis, Larcopyle buetschlii, Larcospira quadrangula, Liriospyris reticulata, Litharachnium tentorium, Lithelius minor, Lithomelissa borealis, Lithomelissa cf. galeata, Lithomelissa hystrix, Lithomelissa laticeps, Lithomelissa setosa, Lithomelissa thoracites, Lithostrobus cf. hexagonalis, Lophocoorys polycantha, Lophophaena cf. capito, Lophospyris pentagona pentagona, MOC, MOCNESS opening/closing plankton net, Number, Octopyle stenozona, Ommatartus tetrathalamus tetrathalamus, Peridium sp./longispinum, Peripyramis circumtexta/Plectopyramis dodecomma, Phormopyris stabilis scaphipes, Phormostichoartus corbula, Phorticium pylonium, Plectacantha sp./oikiskos, Porodiscus sp., Prunopyle antarctica, Pterocanium grandiporus, Pterocanium korotnevi, Pterocanium praetextum group, Pterocanium sp., Pterocanium trilobum, Pterocorys clausus, Pterocorys hertwigii, Pterocorys minythorax, Pterocorys sabae, Radiolarians, population density, Rhodospyris sp., Sample ID, Siphonosphaera polysiphonia, Spongaster tetras, Spongocore puella, Spongopyle osculosa, Spongotrochus glacialis group, Spongurus cf. elliptica, Spongurus pylomaticus, Spongurus sp., Stichopilium bicorne, Stylatractus spp., Stylochlamydium asteriscus, Stylodictya aculeata/validispina, Tetrapyle octacantha, Theocalyptra bicornis, Theocalyptra bicornis var., Theocorythium trachelium group, Theopilium tricostatum, Thomas G. Thompson, TT007, TT007_10-MOC19, Volume, Zygocircus sp.</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2003-10-15</date></data>