<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.706183</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Chemical and isotope compositions of bottom sediments from ODP Leg 168, Eastern Flank of the Juan de Fuca Ridge</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Ten sites were drilled in the eastern flank of the Juan de Fuca Ridge (North East Pacific) along a 100 km-long east-west transect during Leg ODP 168. This study focuses on the mineralogical and chemical study of sediments that overly basaltic basement through which seawater circulates. Silicate authigenesis was observed in the sediment layer just above basement at sites located more than 30 km from the ridge axis. This sediment alteration is particularly abundant at ODP Sites 1031 and 1029 where authigenic formation of Fe-Mg rich smectite and zeolite and the dissolution of biogenic calcite are observed. Comparison of the distribution of the alteration in the basal sediment collected along this transect suggests that diffusional transport of aqueous solutes from the basement into the overlying sediment cannot produce the mineralogical and chemical changes in the basal sediments at Sites 1031 located on a basement topographic high, and at Site 1029 located at about 50 km from the ridge axis on a buried basement area. Vertical advection of basement fluid though the sediment section is required to produce this alteration. These processes are still active at Site 1031, based on systematic variations in pore-water profiles and temperatures obtained from stable isotopic data on calcium carbonates and the nature of authigenic minerals. At Site 1029, there is no present-day advection of basement fluids though the sediment section, suggesting that this is a relic site for fluid flow.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>168-1026C, 168-1027B, 168-1027C, 168-1028A, 168-1029A, 168-1030B, 168-1031A, 168-1032A, DRILL, Drilling/drill rig, Joides Resolution, Juan de Fuca Ridge, North Pacific Ocean, Leg168, North Pacific Ocean, Ocean Drilling Program, ODP</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2001-10-17</date></data>