<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.94584</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Percent contribution of diatom species in surface sediments, brine</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description /><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>129, Actinocyclus curvatulus, Actinocyclus elongatus, Actinocyclus exiguus, Actinocyclus octonarius, Actinocyclus subtilis, Alveus marinus, Asterolampra marylandica, Asteromphalus arachne, Asteromphalus cleveanus, Asteromphalus flabellatus, Asteromphalus heptactis, Azpeitia africana, Azpeitia neocrenulata, Azpeitia nodulifera, Bacteriastrum delicatulum/furcatum, Bacteriastrum elongatum, Bacteriastrum hyalinum, Center for Marine Environmental Sciences, Chaetoceros affinis, Chaetoceros atlanticus, Chaetoceros compressus, Chaetoceros concavicornis, Chaetoceros didymus, Chaetoceros lorenzianus, Chaetoceros messanensis, Chaetoceros peruvianus, Chaetoceros spp., Chaetoceros spp. resting spores, Coscinodiscus janischii, Coscinodiscus radiatus, Coscinodiscus reniformis, Coscinodiscus spp., Coscinodiscus thorii, Counting, diatoms, Cyclotella litoralis, Dactyliosolen spp., DEPTH, sediment/rock, Detonula spp., Diatoms, nonplanktic, Diatoms freshwater, Diatoms indeterminata, Elevation of event, Event label, Fragilariopsis doliolus, Fragilariopsis spp., GeoB7802-1, GeoB7803-2, Haslea spp., Hemiaulus hauckii, Hemiaulus sinensis, Hemidiscus cuneiformis, Latitude of event, Leptocylindrus mediterraneus, Longitude of event, M52/3, MARUM, Mastogloia rostrata, Meteor (1986), MUC, MultiCorer, Neodelphineis indica, Neodelphineis spp., Nitzschia bicapitata, Nitzschia braarudii, Nitzschia capuluspalae, Nitzschia interruptestriata, Nitzschia longissima, Nitzschia sicula, Northern Red Sea, Shaban Deep Area, Odontella spp., Paralia spp., Planktoniella sol, Pleurosigma directum, Pleurosigma spp., Proboscia spp., Pseudo-nitzschia delicatissima, Pseudo-nitzschia fraudulenta, Pseudo-nitzschia granii, Pseudo-nitzschia prolongatoides, Pseudo-nitzschia subfraudulenta, Pseudosolenia calcar-avis, Pseudotriceratium punctatum, Rhizosolenia acicularis, Rhizosolenia bergonii, Rhizosolenia castracanei var. castracanei, Rhizosolenia hebetata, Rhizosolenia Imbricatae, Rhizosolenia pungens, Rhizosolenia setigera, Rhizosolenia spp., Roperia tessellata, Thalassionema bacillare, Thalassionema nitzschioides var. capitulata, Thalassionema nitzschioides var. claviformis, Thalassionema nitzschioides var. incurvata, Thalassionema nitzschioides var. inflata, Thalassionema nitzschioides var. parva, Thalassionema spp., Thalassiosira delicatula, Thalassiosira eccentrica, Thalassiosira ferelineata, Thalassiosira leptopus, Thalassiosira lineata, Thalassiosira oceanica, Thalassiosira oestrupii var. oestrupii, Thalassiosira oestrupii var. venrickae, Thalassiosira pacifica, Thalassiosira poro-irregulata, Thalassiosira sackettii forma sackettii, Thalassiosira spp., Thalassiosira subtilis, Thalassiosira symmetrica, Thalassiothrix spp.</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2004-04-01</date></data>