<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.683836</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Pliocene-Pleistocene oxygen isotope record DSDP Site 586, Ontong Java Plateau, Pacific Ocean i</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Oceanographic changes in the western equatorial Pacific during the past 6 Ma are inferred from oxygen isotopic analyses of planktic and benthic foraminifera from Ontong Java Plateau (DSDP Site 586). The taxa are Globigerinoides sacculifer, Pulleniatina, Cibicidoides wuellerstorfi, and Oridorsalis umbonatus. Cooling and ice buildup are indicated by an 18O enrichment of 0.3 per mil in the planktic species near 3.4 Ma. This shift apparently is compensated in the benthic data by a warming of the deep waters by between 1&#176; and 2&#176; C. We suggest that the dominant source of upper deep water supply to the Pacific changed from Antarctic to North Atlantic at that time, the North Atlantic-derived water being warmer. Near 2.8 Ma (approximately) the planktic foraminifera again record an enrichment in 18O (Delta delta18O=0.25 per mil). We suggest ice buildup in the northern hemisphere as the cause, because of subsequent sharp increase in fluctuations of the delta18O signal, that is, instability. The enrichment is magnified in the benthic foraminifera (Delta delta18O = 0.5 per mil) by a cooling of the deep water by 1.5&#176; at the time, presumably signalling a glacial-type reduction of North Atlantic Deep Water (NADW) production.Episodic divergence between the signals of G. sacculifer and Pulleniatina in the Pleistocene apparently reflects periods of increased upwelling in the western equatorial Pacific. The amplitude of ice volume fluctuations cannot be reconstructed from delta18O data alone, unless there are constraints on temperature variations. The increase in amplitude of fluctuation of the benthic and planktic signals during the Pleistocene may be attributed either to an increase in maximum ice volume, or to an increase in the fractionation of continental ice, or a combination of both causes.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>89-586_Site, COMPCORE, Composite Core, Deep Sea Drilling Project, DSDP, Glomar Challenger, Leg89, South Pacific</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>1992-02-25</date></data>