<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.728777</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>(Table 10) Eocene-Oligocene diatom biostratigraphy of ODP Hole 120-748B</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description /><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>120-748B, Actinoptychus spp., Arachnoidiscus spp., Asterolampra affinis, Asterolampra gradiata, Asterolampra grevillei, Asterolampra punctifera, Asterolampra schmidtii, Asterolampra tela, Asterolampra uraster, Asterolampra vulgaris cellulosa, Asterolampra vulgaris hyalina, Asteromphalus oligocenicus, Asteromphalus symmetricus, Azpeitia gombosii, Azpeitia oligocenica, Baxteriopsis brunii, Bogorovia veniamini, Brightwellia coronata, Brightwellia hyperborea, Brightwellia spiralis, Cestodiscus antarcticus, Cestodiscus convexus, Cestodiscus pulchellus, Cestodiscus pulchellus var. novazelandica, Cestodiscus reticulatus, Coscinodiscus hajosiae, Coscinodiscus lewisianus, Coscinodiscus lewisianus var. levis, Coscinodiscus marginatus, Coscinodiscus mutabilis, Coscinodiscus rhombicus, Coscinodiscus superbus, Dactyliozolen antarcticus, DEPTH, sediment/rock, Diatoms indeterminata, Diatom zone, DRILL, Drilling/drill rig, Epoch, Ethmodiscus rex, Hemiaulus caracteristicus, Hemiaulus incisus, Hemiaulus polycystinorum, Hemiaulus rectus var. twista, Hemiaulus taurus, Joides Resolution, Kozloviella minor, Leg120, Lisitzinia ornata, Navicula udintsevii, Ocean Drilling Program, ODP, ODP sample designation, Paralia architecturalis, Paralia sulcata, Paralia sulcata var. crenulata, Pleurosigma spp., Pseudorocella barbadensis, Pseudotriceratium radiosoreticulatum, Pyxilla reticulata, Rhizosolenia antarctica, Rhizosolenia hebetata, Rhizosolenia oligocaenica, Rhizosolenia sp., Rhizosolenia styliformis, Rocella gelida, Rocella gelida var. schraderi, Rocella praenitida, Rocella vigilans, Rossiella symmetrica, Rouxia granda, Rouxia hannae, Rouxia obesa, Rutilariopsis sp., Sample code/label, Sceptroneis grunowii, Sceptroneis lingulatus, Sceptroneis pesplanus, Sceptroneis tenue, Simonseniella praebarboi, Skeletonema barbadiense, South Indian Ridge, South Indian Ocean, Stellarima spp., Stephanopyxis grunowii, Stephanopyxis ornata, Stephanopyxis turris, Synedra jouseana, Thalassiosira bukryi, Thalassiosira primalabiata, Triceratium groningensis, Triceratium inconspicuum, Triceratium polymorphus, Triceratium unguiculatum, Xanthiopyxis acrolophra, Xanthiopyxis oblonga, Xanthiopyxis panduraeformis, Xanthiopyxis sp.</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>1992-10-27</date></data>