<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.729508</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Pollen and macroremains from sediment core Aschenh&#252;tte</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>The Upper Pleistocene sediments of the Aschenh&#252;tte sink-hole (west of Herzberg am Harz, Lower Saxony) enable one to make interesting correlations between palynological and geological results. The sequence is composed of limnic-telmatic deposits (Eemain to Lower Weichselian) and loess with paleosoils (Weichselian). Sedimentation started during the hornbeam-dominated phase of the Eemian interglacial period and continued throughout the Eemian, the Weichselian Br&#246;rup interstadial (sensu Andersen) and parts of the preceding and the following stadial phases, the Herning and the Rederstall stadials.As opposed to most of the known Eemian sites spruce was a major tree species during the hornbeam-dominated phase of the Eemian. The vegetational  development during the interstadial phase does not show a period of climatic deterioration as is the case for the Br&#246;rup interstadial when considering regions with a more demanding vegetation or regions close to the natural boundaries of the tree species concerned. Pollen or seeds of Bruckenthalia and Picea omoricoides have not been found in the Aschenh&#252;tte cores.The limnic-telmatic sediments interlock with loess-paleosoils (Eemian soil and Lower Weichselian bleaching soils) at the lake shore. They are overlaid by loess paleosoils of the Stillfried-B interstadial (Hattorf soil and Lohne soil). Lake level fluctuations were determined by means of the facies distribution and isochrones as defined by pollen analysis. A relatively high stand of the lake level existed after the end of the Eemian interglacial and during the Br&#246;rup interstadial periods. In the course of the Herning stadial period the water level dropped, whereas during the Rederstall stadial phase the lake basin was covered by sediments and therefore dried up.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Aschenh&#252;tte, EDEA, Edelman auger, H77, Lower Saxony, Northern Germany</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>1988-11-24</date></data>