<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.779776</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Foraminifera abundances and biostratigraphy of Cenozoic sediments from the Ontong Java Plateau</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>The Ontong Java Plateau in the western equatorial Pacific contains a deposition record of biserial planktonic foraminifers concentrated in the Paleogene, in which frequencies up to 67% of the planktonic foraminifers are reported, and in the late Neogene, in which a maximum frequency of 48% is reported. Biserial planktonic foraminifers are rare or absent in the latest Oligocene and early Miocene, an interval characterized by warm bottom water and low temperature gradients. These conditions supported a surface assemblage rather than the biserial planktonic foraminifers, whose Neogene species inhabited the oxygen minimum at intermediate depths in the upper water column.Biserial planktonic foraminifers tend to be of high frequency during high sea stands and low frequency during low sea level, presumably in response to the strengthening or weakening of the oxygen minimum. Species extinction and evolution events occur during low sea stands in the Neogene and sometimes correspond to strong reflection horizons of the plateau's seismic stratigraphy.The biserial species are useful biostratigraphic indexes in the plateau section. The last occurrence (LO) of Streptochilus martini corresponds with the Eocene/Oligocene boundary, S. subglobigerum without Neogloboquadrina acostaensis indicates Zone N15, S. latum occurs from the middle of Zone N16 to near the top of Zone N17, S. globigerum ranges from near the top of Zone N17 to the middle of Zone N19/N20, and the S. globulosum continuous range begins just before the first left-to-right coiling change of Pulleniatina, but the species becomes rare in the Pleistocene section.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>130-806B, 130-807A, 130-807C, 7-62, Deep Sea Drilling Project, DRILL, Drilling/drill rig, DSDP, Glomar Challenger, Joides Resolution, Leg130, Leg7, North Pacific/RIDGE, North Pacific Ocean, Ocean Drilling Program, ODP</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>1993-04-23</date></data>