<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.739883</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Pollen profile TAR1_N, Tarnawa Wyzna, Poland</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description /><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Abies alba, Acer, Alisma plantago-aquatica, Allium vineale-type, Alnus, Anemone-type, Anthemis-type, Artemisia, Aruncus dioicus, Asarum europaeum, Asteroideae undifferentiated, Aster-type, Astrantia-type, Avena-type, Bellis-type, Betula cf. B. nana, Betula undifferentiated, Bilderdykia convolvulus-type, Botrychium, Bupleurum, Calla palustris, Calluna vulgaris, Caltha-type, Campanula, Carpinus betulus, Caryophyllaceae, Centaurea cf. C. kotschyana, Centaurea cyanus-type, Centaurea jacea-type, Centaurea mollis-type, Centaurea scabiosa-type, Cerastium-type, Cerealia undifferentiated, Cerinthe, cf. Aconitum, cf. Andromeda polifolia, cf. Myosoton aquaticum, cf. Potentilla palustris, cf. Sorbus aucuparia, cf. Swertia, cf. Veratrum, cf. Xanthium, Chenopodiaceae, Chrysosplenium, Cichorioideae, Cirsium/Carduus, Cladium mariscus, Corylus avellana, Cruciferae, Cyperaceae undifferentiated, Delphinium-type, DEPTH, sediment/rock, Diphasium complanatum-type, Drosera cf. D. rotundifolia, Echium, Empetrum cf. E. nigrum, Ephedra distachya-type, Ephedra fragilis-type, Equisetum, Euphorbia, Fagopyrum, Fagus sylvatica, Filipendula, Frangula alnus, Fraxinus excelsior, Gagea-type, Gentiana asclepiadea-type, Geranium, Geum, Glyceria-type, Gnaphalium-type, Gramineae undifferentiated, Gymnocarpium dryopteris, Gypsophila fastigiata, Hedera helix, Hiller sampler, HILS, Hippophae rhamnoides, Hordeum-type, Humulus/Cannabis, Huperzia selago, Hypericum, Impatiens, Jasione montana, Juglans, Juniperus, Knautia, Lamiastrum-type, Larix, Ledum palustre, Leucojum/Galanthus, Lilium, Linaria, Linum catharticum-type, Linum usitatissimum, Lonicera nigra-type, Loranthus, Lychnis-type, Lycopodium annotinum, Lycopodium clavatum, Lycopus-type, Lysimachia vulgaris-type, Melampyrum, Menyanthes trifoliata, Mercurialis perennis, Ophioglossum, Papaver argemone, Parnassia palustris, Pedicularis, Picea abies, Pinus cembra, Pinus undifferentiated, Plantago lanceolata, Plantago major, Plantago media, Pleurospermum austriacum, Polygonum aviculare, Polygonum bistorta, Polygonum persicaria-type, Polypodiaceae undifferentiated, Polypodium vulgare, Populus, Potamogeton, Potentilla-type, Prunella-type, Pteridium aquilinum, Pulsatilla, Quercus, Ranunculus, Rhamnus catharticus, Rhinanthus-type, Rhynchospora alba, Ribes, Rubiaceae, Rubus, Rumex acetosa-type, Rumex acetosella-type, Rumex longifolius-type, Rumex undifferentiated, Salix, Sambucus cf. S. nigra, Sanguisorba minor, Sanguisorba officinalis, Saussurea-type, Saxifraga cf. S. hirculus, Saxifraga oppositifolia-type, Scabiosa, Scilla-type, Scirpus sect. Pterolepis-type, Scleranthus annuus, Secale cereale, Selaginella selaginoides, Senecio-type, Silene dioica-type, Silene-type, Solanum dulcamara, Solidago-type, Sparganium-type, Sphagnum, Stachys-type, Stellaria cf. S. graminea, Stellaria cf. S. nemorum, Stellaria holostea, Symphytum, TAR1_N, Tarnawa Wyzna, Poland, Thalictrum, Tilia cordata-type, Tilia platyphyllos, Trifolium, Trifolium pratense, Triticum-type, Tussilago-type, Typha latifolia, Ulmus, Umbelliferae, Urtica cf. U. dioica, Vaccinium-type, Valeriana, Viburnum cf. V. opulus, Viola palustris-type, Viscum, Vitis, Zea mays</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2010-06-08</date></data>