<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.830802</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Seawater carbonate chemistry and calcification of the crustose coralline alga Hydrolithon onkodes in a laboratory experiment</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Anthropogenic CO2 emissions have exacerbated two environmental stressors, global climate warming and ocean acidification (OA), that have serious implications for marine ecosystems. Coral reefs are vulnerable to climate change yet few studies have explored the potential for interactive effects of warming temperature and OA on an important coral reef calcifier, crustose coralline algae (CCA). Coralline algae serve many important ecosystem functions on coral reefs and are one of the most sensitive organisms to ocean acidification. We investigated the effects of elevated pCO2 and temperature on calcification of Hydrolithon onkodes, an important species of reef-building coralline algae, and the subsequent effects on susceptibility to grazing by sea urchins. H. onkodes was exposed to a fully factorial combination of pCO2 (420, 530, 830 &#181;atm) and temperature (26, 29 &#176;C) treatments, and calcification was measured by the change in buoyant weight after 21 days of treatment exposure. Temperature and pCO2 had a significant interactive effect on net calcification of H. onkodes that was driven by the increased calcification response to moderately elevated pCO2. We demonstrate that the CCA calcification response was variable and non-linear, and that there was a trend for highest calcification at ambient temperature. H. onkodes then was exposed to grazing by the sea urchin Echinothrix diadema, and grazing was quantified by the change in CCA buoyant weight from grazing trials. E. diadema removed 60% more CaCO3 from H. onkodes grown at high temperature and high pCO2 than at ambient temperature and low pCO2. The increased susceptibility to grazing in the high pCO2 treatment is among the first evidence indicating the potential for cascading effects of OA and temperature on coral reef organisms and their ecological interactions.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Alkalinity, total, Alkalinity, total, standard deviation, Aragonite saturation state, Benthos, Bicarbonate ion, Bicarbonate ion, standard error, Calcification/Dissolution, Calcite saturation state, Calcite saturation state, standard error, Calcium carbonate, removed, Calcium carbonate, removed, standard deviation, Calculated using CO2SYS, Calculated using seacarb after Nisumaa et al. (2010), Carbon, inorganic, dissolved, Carbonate ion, Carbonate ion, standard error, Carbonate system computation flag, Carbon dioxide, Coast and continental shelf, Containers and aquaria (20- 1000 L or &lt; 1 m**2), Fugacity of carbon dioxide (water) at sea surface temperature (wet air), Hydrolithon onkodes, Laboratory experiment, Macroalgae, Net calcification rate of calcium carbonate, Net calcification rate of calcium carbonate, standard error, North Pacific, OA-ICC, Ocean Acidification International Coordination Centre, Partial pressure of carbon dioxide, standard deviation, Partial pressure of carbon dioxide (water) at sea surface temperature (wet air), pH, pH, standard deviation, Plantae, Potentiometric titration, Rhodophyta, Salinity, Salinity, standard error, Single species, Species, Species interaction, Spectrophotometric, Temperature, Temperature, water, Temperature, water, standard deviation, Treatment, Tropical</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2012-03-21</date></data>