<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.889634</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Pollen profile REINBERC, Reinberg, Germany</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description /><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Abies, Acer campestre-type, Aethusa cynapium-type, Alnus, Amphitrema flavum, Anagallis arvensis-type, Anagallis tenella/A. minima, Angelica palustris-type, Anthemis/Aster-type, Anthemis-type, Anthriscus sylvestris-type, Apiaceae undifferentiated, Apium inundatum-type, Arbutus unedo, Arctostaphylos uva-ursi, Arenaria montana, Armeria maritima/Limonium vulgare, Armeria maritima (type A), Armeria maritima (type B), Artemisia, Assulina, Aster-type, Astragalus alpinus, Astragalus danicus-type, Avena/Triticum-group, Betula/Corylus, Betula nana-type, Betula pubescens-type, Betula undifferentiated, Betuloid-type, Bisaccate, Botrychium lunaria-type, Botryococcus, Bupleurum falcatum-group, Calluna vulgaris, Caltha palustris-type, Carpinus-type, Carum carvi-type, Carum verticillatum-type, Caryophyllaceae undifferentiated, Cedrus, Centaurea cyanus-type, Cerastium fontanum-group, Cerealia undifferentiated, cf. Acer campestre-type, cf. Adonis vernalis-type, cf. Apiaceae, cf. Artemisia, cf. Blechnum spicant, cf. Buxus, cf. Caltha palustris-type, cf. Carpinus-type, cf. Carya-type, cf. Cerastium fontanum-group, cf. Chaerophyllum hirsutum, cf. Cornus mas-type, cf. Digitalis purpurea-type, cf. Dryas octopetala, cf. Dryopteris filix-mas/D. cristata, cf. Euphorbia, cf. Fabaceae, cf. Fagus, cf. Filipendula, cf. Fraxinus, cf. Fumana-type, cf. Helianthemum, cf. Heracleum sphondyllium-type, cf. Hippophae rhamnoides, cf. Hornungia-type, cf. Ilex-type, cf. Juniperus-type, cf. Liliaceae, cf. Liquidambar styraciflua, cf. Lotus-type, cf. Mentha-type, cf. Menyanthes trifoliata-type, cf. Nymphaea alba-type, cf. Nyssa, cf. Onobrychis-type, cf. Plantago maritima-type, cf. Polypodium vulgare-type, cf. Polystichum-type, cf. Populus, cf. Potamogeton-type, cf. Potentilla-type, cf. Pterocarya fraxinifolia-type, cf. Ranunculus acris-type, cf. Rhus typhina, cf. Ribes rubrum-type, cf. Sambucus nigra-type, cf. Sanguisorba minor, cf. Saxifraga oppositifolia-type, cf. Saxifraga stellaris-type, cf. Scrophularia-type, cf. Scutellaria-type, cf. Sedum-type, cf. Selaginella selaginoides, cf. Seseli libanotis-type, cf. Silene vulgaris-type, cf. Sinapis-type, cf. Solanum dulcamara-type, cf. Thelypteris palustris, cf. Trifolium-type, cf. Tsuga, cf. Valeriana dioica-type, cf. Viscum, Chaerophyllum bulbosum-type, Chaerophyllum temulentum-type, Chamaenerion angustifolium-type, Chenopodiaceae/Amaranthaceae, Cicuta virosa-type, Circaea, Cirsium/Serratula-type, Coryloide-type, Corylus, Counted exote, Counting, palynology, Crithmum maritimum-type, Cyperaceae, DEPTH, sediment/rock, Dianthus superbus-type, Diphasiastrum-type, Diporotheca, Dryas octopetala, Echium vulgare, Empetrum nigrum, Entophlyctis lobata, EPD, Ephedra distachya-type, Ephedra fragilis-type, Equisetum, Ericales undifferentiated, Exotic concentration, Fabaceae undifferentiated, Fagopyrum esculentum-type, Fagus, Falcaria vulgaris-type, Fern sporangium, Filipendula, Frangula alnus, Fraxinus, Galium-type, Gelasinospora, Geum, Glaucium flavum-type, Hedera helix, Helianthemum, Helicoon pluriseptatum, Heracleum sphondylium-type, Hippophae rhamnoides, Hordeum-group, Hornungia-type, Humulus lupulus, Hystrix, Ilex-type, Indeterminata, Jasione-type, Juglans-type, Juniperus, Juniperus-type, Lactuceae, Levisticum officinale-type, Liquidambar styraciflua, LIVC, Livingstone corer, Lonicera periclymenum-type, Lotus-type, Lycopodium annotinum-type, Lycopodium clavatum, Melampyrum-type, Mentha-type, Menyanthes trifoliata, Moehringia trinervia-group, Monolete spore(s), Mougeotia, Myrica, Myriophyllum verticillatum, Narthecium/Fritillaria/Scilla-type, Neurospora, Nuphar, Nymphaea alba-type, Nyssa, Oenanthe fistulosa-type, Onobrychis-type, Ononis-type, Parnassia palustris-type, Pediastrum boryanum-type, Pediastrum duplex-type, Peucedanum palustre-type, Picea, Pimpinella anisum-type, Pimpinella major-type, Pinguicula, Pinus diploxylon-type, Pinus haploxylon-type, Pinus undifferentiated, Plantaginaceae undifferentiated, Plantago coronopus-type, Plantago lanceolata-type, Plantago major/media-type, Plantago maritima-type, Plantago tenuiflora-type, Poaceae, Polemonium-type, Pollen and spores, other, Polygonum aviculare-type, Polygonum convolvulus-type, Polypodium vulgare-type, Potamogeton-type, Potentilla-type, Pre-Quaternary pollen, Pre-Quaternary spores, Pteridium aquilinum-type, Pterocarya fraxinifolia-type, Quercus, Ranunculus acris-type, REINBERC, Reinberg, Ribes rubrum-type, Rosaceae undifferentiated, Rumex acetosa-group, Rumex acetosa-type, Rumex acetosella, Rumex aquaticus-group, Rumex conglomeratus-group, Sagina apetala-type, Sagina procumbens-type, Salix, Sambucus nigra-type, Sample volume, Sanguisorba minor, Saxifraga stellaris-type, Scleranthus annuus-type, Secale cereale, Selaginella selaginoides, Silaum silaus-type, Silene dioica-type, Sinapis-type, Sison amomum-type, Sium latifolium-type, Solanum dulcamara-type, Sorbus, Sparganium emersum-type, Sparganium erectum-type, Sphagnum, Spirogyra, Tablets, Thalictrum flavum-type, Tilia, Trifolium-type, Trinia glauca-type, Typha angustifolia, Typha latifolia-type, Ulmus, Urtica dioica-type, Utricularia, Vaccinium-group, Vicia cracca-type, Vicia-type, Viscum, Zygnemataceae undifferentiated</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2018-05-04</date></data>