<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.903909</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Carbon flows in the ecosystems Lake Santo and Lake Scuro (northern Apennines, Italy)</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>System level indices from ecosystem network analysis (ENA) were calculated for the carbon flow networks representing Lake Santo and Lake Scuro ecosystems. Long-term data were used to construct the time series of networks representing carbon flows in the two ecosystems (Lake Santo: 1973, 1991, 2001, 2003 and 2007-2009, Lake Scuro: 1986, 1989-1994, 1998, 2003 and 2007-2009). The following indices were calculated: H - diversity of flows, AMI - average mutual information, HC - residual diversity, DC - development capacity, A - ascendency, O - overhead, TST - total system throughput, P - primary productivity (of phytoplankton), TOM - total organic matter, IR - flow redundancy, IC - internal connectance (data in file ScottiM_2019_lakes-indices.zip).All flows in the networks constructed to model carbon circulation in Lake Santo and Lake Scuro are reported. The time series includes 7 networks in the case of Lake Santo (1973, 1991, 2001, 2003 and 2007-2009) and 12 networks for Lake Scuro (1986, 1989-1994, 1998, 2003 and 2007-2009). Lake Santo is composed of 26 compartments (23 living and 3 non-living) while Lake Scuro has 22 compartments (19 living and 3 non-living). Four types of flows are summarized: (i) input from outside the system (i.e. photosynthesis or carbon flows due to leaves or other organic materials that contribute to the standing stocks of water DOC and water POC), (ii) export of still usable carbon outside system's boundaries (i.e. carbon burial into the sediment from benthic POC), (iii) respiration/dissipation, and (iv) inter-compartmental exchanges among compartments composing the system (i.e. flows from prey/resources to predators/consumers). All flows are in grams of carbon per cubic meter per year. Table columns represent: (i) donor compartments, (ii) recipient compartments, (iii) short explanation of the processes represented, (iv) strength of the flows (i.e. amount of carbon transferred) during the various years of the time series (i.e. 7 years for Lake Santo and 12 years for Lake Scuro) (data in file ScottiM_2019_lakes-dataset.zip).</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>climate change, ecosystem network analysis, File content, File format, File name, File size, information theory indices, LTER network, Uniform resource locator/link to file</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2019-07-17</date></data>