<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.777615</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Clay mineralogy on five NBP cores</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>During 2006, the SHALDRIL program recovered cores of Eocene through Pliocene material at four locations in the northwestern Weddell Sea, each representing a key period in the evolution of the Antarctic Peninsula ice cap. The recovered cores are not continuous, yet they provide a record of climate change with samples from the late Eocene, late Oligocene, middle Miocene, and early Pliocene and represent the only series of samples recovered from the northwestern Weddell Sea and spanning the Cenozoic and the initial growth of the peninsula ice cap. Late Eocene sediments sampled in the James Ross Basin are typically characterized by very dark greenish-gray muddy fine sand with some preserved burrowing and are interpreted to represent a shallow water continental shelf setting. Rare dropstones, primarily of well-cemented sandstones and minor ice-rafted material consisting of angular grains with glacially influenced surface features record the onset of mountain glaciation, the earliest such evidence in the region. The remaining cores were collected on the Joinville Plateau to the north of the James Ross Basin. The late Oligocene sediments consist of dark gray sandy mud with some clay lenses and many burrows, likely representing a distal delta or shelf setting. This core contains only very few and small dropstones, and the individual grains show decreased angularity and fewer glacial surface features relative to late Eocene deposits. The middle Miocene strata are composed of pebbly gray diamicton, representing proximal glacimarine sediments. The lower Pliocene section also contains many ice-rafted pebbles but is dominated by sandy units rather than diamicton and is interpreted to represent a current-winnowed deposit, similar to the modern contour current-influenced sediments of the region.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>DRILL, Drilling/drill rig, Joinville Plateau, Nathaniel B. Palmer, NBP06-02A, NBP0602A-12A, NBP0602A-3C, NBP0602A-5D, NBP0602A-6C, NBP0602A-6D, Northern James Ross Basin, SHALDRIL II</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2012-03-13</date></data>