<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.678533</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Plio-Pleistocene diatom biostratigraphy from ODP Leg 177, Atlantic sector of the Southern Ocean</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Seven sites were drilled during Ocean Drilling Program Leg 177 in the Atlantic sector of the Southern Ocean (SO) on a transect over the Antarctic Circumpolar Current from the Subantarctic to the Antarctic Zone. At four sites sediments were recovered with a Pliocene/Pleistocene sediment package of up to 580 m allowing the refinement of previous diatom zonation concepts. Samples were analyzed on stratigraphic distribution and abundance of diatom species. A refined diatom biozonation tied to the geomagnetic polarity record is proposed. For the middle and late Pleistocene two zonations applicable to the northern and southern area of the SO were constructed, considering different latitudinal distributions of biostratigraphic diatom marker species. The southern zonation for the Pleistocene relies on the occurrence of species of the genus Rouxia, R. leventerae and R. constricta n. sp. as well as on a revised last occurrence datum (LOD) of Actinocyclus ingens (0.38 Ma, late marine isotope stage (MIS) 11). The use of these new stratigraphic marker species refines the temporal resolution for biostratigraphic age assignment to up to 0.1 Myr. In particular the LOD of R. leventerae as an indicator for the MIS 6/5 boundary (Termination II) will improve future dating of carbonate-free Antarctic sediments. These new data were obtained from sediments of Sites 1093 and 1094 (Antarctic Zone). The northern zonation for the middle and late Pleistocene time interval is based on the Pleistocene abundance pattern of Hemidiscus karstenii which was already proposed by previous investigations (e.g. Gersonde and Barcena, 1998). One new species (R. constricta) and two new combinations (Fragilariopsis clementia, Fragilariopsis reinholdii) are proposed in this study.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>177-1089, 177-1090, 177-1091, 177-1092, 177-1093, 177-1094, COMPCORE, Composite Core, Joides Resolution, Leg177, Ocean Drilling Program, ODP, South Atlantic Ocean</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2002-01-22</date></data>