<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.836403</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Vertical profiles of environmental parameters measured from physical, optical and imaging sensors during station TARA_065 of the Tara Oceans expedition 2009-2013</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>The Tara Oceans Expedition (2009-2013) sampled the world oceans on board a 36 m long schooner, collecting environmental data and organisms from viruses to planktonic metazoans for later analyses using modern sequencing and state-of-the-art imaging technologies. Tara Oceans Data are particularly suited to study the genetic, morphological and functional diversity of plankton. The present data set includes properties of seawater, particulate matter and dissolved matter from physical, optical and imaging sensors mounted on a vertical sampling system (Rosette) used during the 2009-2013 tara Oceans Expedition. It comprised 2 pairs of conductivity and temperature sensors (SEABIRD components), and a complete set of WEtLabs optical sensors, including chrorophyll and CDOM fluorometers, a 25 cm transmissiometer, and a one-wavelength backscatter meter. In addition, a SATLANTIC ISUS nitrate sensor and a Hydroptic Underwater Vision Profiler (UVP) were mounted on the rosette. In the Arctic Ocean and Arctic Seas (2013), a second oxygen sensor (SBE43) and a four frequency Aquascat acoustic profiler were added. The system was powered on specific Li-Ion batteries and data were self-recorded at 24HZ. Sensors have all been factory calibrated before, during and after the four year program. Oxygen was validated using climatologies (WOA09). Nitrate and Fluorescence data were adjusted with discrete measurements from Niskin bottles mounted on the Rosette, and optical darks were performed monthly on board. A total of 839 quality checked vertical profiles were made during the tara Oceans expedition 2009-2013.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>[RVSS], Angular scattering coefficient, 470 nm, at 117 degrees with respect to the incident beam, Backscattering coefficient of particles, 470 nm, Basis of event, Beam attenuation coefficient of particles, Campaign of event, Chlorophyll a, Comment of event, Conductivity, Date/Time of event, Density, sigma-theta (0), DEPTH, water, derived from chlorophyll fluorescence sensor, WET Labs, derived from CTD, SEA-BIRD, derived from SBE43 oxygen sensor, Device of event, Event label, File name, Fluorescence, colored dissolved organic matter, Fondation Tara Expeditions, FondTara, integrated over the angular domain 90-180 degree, Latitude of event, Longitude of event, Mamoudzou to Cape Town, Stations: TARA_055-066, Optical backscattering coefficient, 470 nm, Optical beam attenuation coefficient, 660 nm, Optional event label, Oxygen, Particle concentration, fractionated, Particle volume, fractionated, Pressure, water, Rosette Vertical Sampling System, Salinity, Station label, SV Tara, TARA_20100624Z, TARA_20100712T0650Z_065_EVENT_CAST, TARA_20100712T1106Z_065_EVENT_CAST, TARA_20100712T1151Z_065_EVENT_CAST, TARA_20100712T1241Z_065_EVENT_CAST, TARA_20100712T1420Z_065_EVENT_CAST, Tara Oceans Expedition, Temperature, water, Temperature, water, potential, TOE-2009-2013, Underwater vision profiler, UVP, URI of event</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2014-10-08</date></data>