<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.736020</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Oxygen microprofiles and porewater chemistry in sediments of the Skagerrak</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Sediment porewater oxygen profiles were measured with micro and needle electrodes in sediment cores of 27 stations in the Skagerrak (northeastern North Sea). Oxygen penetration depth ranged from 3 to 20 mm depth. Fluxes estimated from the oxygen gradients varied from 3 to 18 mmol m**-2 d**-1. Oxygen penetration and flux depend on water depth, but possibly more on the hydrological conditions, related to the import of fresh organic matter by primary production in the water column. Oxygen fluxes were not related to the total organic carbon (TOC) content of the sediments. Stations in the eastern part of the Skagerrak showed high burial rates of TOC.At 6 stations porewater chemistry of Fe, Mn and NO3- was strongly associated with the oxygen distribution. The average relative contribution of terminal electron acceptors to carbon mineralisation was estimated at 85% for O2, 0.5% for Mn, 4.5% for [NO3]3-, 1% for Fe and 9% for [SO4]2-.At one station the occurrence of exceptionally high solid manganese oxyhydroxides was probably related to an active internal manganese cycle.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>A84-01, A84-02, A84-03, A84-04, A84-05, A84-06, A84-07, A84-08, A84-09, A84-11, A84-12, A84-13, A84-14, A84-15, A84-16, A84-17, A84-18, A84-19, A84-20, A84-21, A84-22, A84-23, A84-24, A84-25, A84-26, A84-27, A84-28, Aurelia, Aurelia_08_1984, Aurelia_08_1984_01_BC, Aurelia_08_1984_02_BC, Aurelia_08_1984_03_BC, Aurelia_08_1984_04_BC, Aurelia_08_1984_05_BC, Aurelia_08_1984_06_BC, Aurelia_08_1984_07_BC, Aurelia_08_1984_08_BC, Aurelia_08_1984_09_BC, Aurelia_08_1984_11_BC, Aurelia_08_1984_12_BC, Aurelia_08_1984_13_BC, Aurelia_08_1984_14_BC, Aurelia_08_1984_15_BC, Aurelia_08_1984_16_BC, Aurelia_08_1984_17_BC, Aurelia_08_1984_18_BC, Aurelia_08_1984_19_BC, Aurelia_08_1984_20_BC, Aurelia_08_1984_21_BC, Aurelia_08_1984_22_BC, Aurelia_08_1984_23_BC, Aurelia_08_1984_24_BC, Aurelia_08_1984_25_BC, Aurelia_08_1984_26_BC, Aurelia_08_1984_27_BC, Aurelia_08_1984_28_BC, BC, Box corer, ORFOIS, Origin and Fate of Biogenic Particle Fluxes in the Ocean</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>1993-03-31</date></data>