<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.846950</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Abundance of mesozooplankton in the western part of the Black Sea in summer 2005 during Phase 2: Leg1 from the GEF Project</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>The sampling area was extended to the Western-South area off the Black Sea coast from Kaliakra cape toward the Bosforous. Samples were collected along four transects. The whole dataset is composed of 17 samples (from 10 stations) with data of mesozooplankton species composition abundance and biomass. Sampling for zooplankton was performed from bottom up to the surface at depths depending on water column stratification and the thermocline depth. These data are organized in the &#8220;Control of eutrophication, hazardous substances and related measures for rehabilitating the Black Sea ecosystem: Phase 2: Leg I: PIMS 3065&#8221;.  Data Report is not published.Zooplankton samples were collected with vertical closing Juday net,diameter - 36cm, mesh size 150 &#181;m. Tows were performed from surface down to bottom meters depths in discrete layers. Samples were preserved by a 4% formaldehyde sea water buffered solution. Sampling volume was estimated by multiplying the mouth area with the wire length.Mesozooplankton abundance: The collected material was analysed using the method of Domov (1959). Samples were brought to volume of 25-30 ml depending upon zooplankton density and mixed intensively until all organisms were distributed randomly in the sample volume. After that 5 ml of sample was taken and poured in the counting chamber which is a rectangle form  for taxomomic identification and count.  Large (&gt; 1 mm body length) and not abundant species were calculated in whole sample. Counting and measuring of organisms were made in the Dimov chamber under the stereomicroscope to the lowest taxon possible. Taxonomic identification was done at the Institute of Oceanology by Kremena Stefanova using the relevant taxonomic literature (Mordukhay-Boltovskoy, F.D. (Ed.). 1968, 1969,1972). Taxon-specific abundance: The collected material was analysed using the method of Domov (1959). Samples were brought to volume of 25-30 ml depending upon zooplankton density and mixed intensively until all organisms were distributed randomly in the sample volume. After that 5 ml of sample was taken and poured in the counting chamber which is a rectangle form  for taxomomic identification and count. Copepods and Cladoceras were identified and enumerated, the other mesozooplankters were identified and enumerated at higher taxonomic level (commonly named as mesozooplankton groups). Large (&gt; 1 mm body length) and not abundant species were calculated in whole sample. Counting and measuring of organisms were made in the Dimov chamber under the stereomicroscope to the lowest taxon possible. Taxonomic identification was done at the Institute of Oceanology by Kremena Stefanova using the relevant taxonomic literature (Mordukhay-Boltovskoy, F.D. (Ed.). 1968, 1969,1972).</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Acartia clausi, adult, Acartia clausi, c1-c5, Acartia clausi, nauplii, Acartia tonsa, adult, Acartia tonsa, c1-c5, after Dimov (1959), Aurelia aurita, Aurelia aurita, ephyra, Beroe ovata, Bivalvia, veliger, Black Sea, Calanus euxinus, adult, Calanus euxinus, c1-c5, Calanus euxinus, nauplii, Centropages ponticus, adult, Centropages ponticus, c1-c5, Centropages ponticus, nauplii, Cirripedia, cypris, Cirripedia, nauplii, Copepoda, c1-c5, Copepoda, nauplii, Copepoda, ova, Ctenophora, ova, Date/Time of event, Decapoda, larvae, Depth, bottom/max, Depth, top/min, DEPTH, water, Euryte longicauda, Evadne tergestina, Event label, Favella ehrenbergii, Gastropoda, veliger, GEF-Phase2_Leg1, GEF-Phase2_Leg1-Zoo_1, GEF-Phase2_Leg1-Zoo_10, GEF-Phase2_Leg1-Zoo_2, GEF-Phase2_Leg1-Zoo_3, GEF-Phase2_Leg1-Zoo_4, GEF-Phase2_Leg1-Zoo_5, GEF-Phase2_Leg1-Zoo_6, GEF-Phase2_Leg1-Zoo_7, GEF-Phase2_Leg1-Zoo_8, GEF-Phase2_Leg1-Zoo_9, Harpacticoida sp., JUDAY, Juday net, Latitude of event, Longitude of event, Mesozooplankton, Mnemiopsis leidyi, Noctiluca scintillans, Oikopleura dioica, Oithona nana, Oithona similis, adult, P1BT, P1KR, P1TR, P1VA, P3KR, P3VA, P4KR, P4TR, P4VA, P6KR, Paracalanus parvus, adult, Paracalanus parvus, c1-c5, Penilia avirostris, Pisces, larvae, Pleopis polyphemoides, Pleurobrachia pileus, Polychaeta, larvae, Pontella mediterranea, Pseudocalanus elongatus, adult, Pseudocalanus elongatus, c1-c5, Rotatoria sp., Sagitta setosa, adult, Sagitta setosa, juvenile, Sample comment, SESAME, Southern European Seas: Assessing and Modelling Ecosystem Changes, Synchaeta vorax, Vladimir Parshin</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2015-06-12</date></data>