<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.712323</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Strontium isotope ratios of planktonic foraminifera from late Neogene sediment samples</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>A curve describing the variation of the strontium isotopic composition of seawater for the late Neogene (9 to 2 Ma) was constructed from 87Sr/86Sr analyses of marine carbonate in five Deep Sea Drilling Project (DSDP) sites: 502, 519, 588, 590, and 593. The strontium isotopic composition of the oceans increased between 9 and 2 Ma with several changes in slope. From 9 to 5.5 Ma, 87Sr/86Sr values were nearly constant at ~0.708925. Between 5.5 and 4.5 Ma, 87Sr/86Sr ratios increased monotonically at a rate of not, vert, similar 1 * 10**-4 per million years. The steep slope during this interval provides the potential for high resolution strontium isotope stratigraphy across the Miocene/Pliocene boundary. The rate of change of 87Sr/86Sr decreases to near zero again during the interval 4.5-2.5 Ma, and ratios average 0.709025.The relatively rapid increase of 87Sr/86Sr between 5.5 and 4.5 Ma must be related to changes in the flux or average 87Sr/86Sr ratios of the major inputs of Sr to the oceans. Quantitative modelling of these inputs suggests that the increase was most probably caused by an increase in the dissolved riverine flux of strontium to the oceans, an increase in the average 87Sr/86Sr composition of river water, or some combination of these parameters. Modelling of this period as a transient-state requires a pulse-like increase in the input of 87Sr to the oceans between 5.5 and 4.5 Ma. Alternatively, the 5.5-4.5 Ma period can be modelled as a simple transition from one steady-state to another if the oceanic residence time of strontium was eight times less than the currently accepted value of 4 Ma.During the time interval of steep 87Sr/86Sr increase, other geochemical and sedimentologic changes also occur including an increase in sediment accumulation rates, a drop in the calcite compensation depth (CCD), and a decrease in the delta13C of dissolved bicarbonate (i.e., "carbon shift"). The simplest mechanism to explain 87Sr/86Sr variation and these related geochemical changes is to invoke an increase in the dissolved chemical fluxes carried by rivers to the oceans. This, in turn, implies increased chemical denudation rates of the continents and shelves during the late Neogene. The increase in chemical weathering rates is attributed to increased exposure of the continents by eustatic regression, intensified glacial/interglacial cycles, and accelerated rates of global tectonism beginning at 5.5 Ma during the latest Miocene.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>68-502, 73-519, 90-588, Caribbean Sea/RIDGE, Deep Sea Drilling Project, DRILL, Drilling/drill rig, DSDP, Glomar Challenger, Leg68, Leg73, Leg90, South Atlantic/RIDGE, South Pacific/Tasman Sea/CONT RISE</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>1989-02-06</date></data>