<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.804469</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Nannofossil datums and abundance in sediments from ODP Leg 164 sites</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Twenty routinely used nannofossil datums in the late Neogene and Quaternary were identified at three Blake Ridge sites drilled during Leg 164. The quantitative investigation of the nannofossil assemblages in 236 samples selected from Hole 994C provide new biostratigraphic and paleoceanographic information. Although mostly overlooked previously, Umbilicosphaera aequiscutum is an abundant component of the late Neogene flora, and its last occurrence at ~2.3 Ma is a useful new biostratigraphic event. Small Gephyrocapsa evolved within the upper part of Subzone CN11a (~4.3 Ma), and after an initial acme, it temporarily disappeared for 400 k.y., between 2.9 and 2.5 Ma. Medium-sized Gephyrocapsa evolved in the latest Pliocene ~2.2 Ma), and after two short temporary disappearances, common specimens occurred continuously just above the Pliocene/Pleistocene boundary. The base of Subzone CN13b should be recognized as the beginning of the continuous occurrence of medium-sized (&gt;4 &#181;m) Gephyrocapsa. Stratigraphic variation in abundance of the very small placoliths and Florisphaera profunda alternated, indicating potential of the former as a proxy for the paleoproductivity. At this site, it is likely that upwelling took place during three time periods in the late Neogene (6.0-4.6 Ma, 2.3-2.1 Ma, and 2.0-1.8 Ma) and also in the early Pleistocene (1.4-0.9 Ma). Weak upwelling is also likely to have occurred intermittently through the late Pliocene. Due to the sharp and abrupt turnover of the nannofossils, which resulted from an evolution of very competitive species, the paleoproductivity of the late Pleistocene is not clear. The site was mostly in an oligotrophic central gyre setting during the 4.6- to 2.3-Ma interval, intermittently between 2.1 and 1.4 Ma, and continuously for the last several tens of thousand years.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Ocean Drilling Program, ODP</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2000-12-19</date></data>