<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.780575</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>(Table T2) Spectral reflectance record for ODP Site 188-1165</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Two main alternating facies were observed at Ocean Drilling Program (ODP) Site 1165, drilled in 3357 m water depth into the Wild Drift (Cooperation Sea, Antarctica): a dark gray, laminated, terrigenous one (interpreted as muddy contourites) and a greenish, homogeneous, biogenic and coarse fraction-bearing one (interpreted as hemipelagic deposits with ice rafted debris [IRD]). These two cyclically alternating facies reflect orbitally driven changes (Milankovitch periodicities) recorded in spectral reflectance, bulk density, and magnetic susceptibility data and opal content changes. Superimposed on these short-term variations, significant uphole changes in average sedimentation rates, total clay content, IRD amount, and mineral composition were interpreted to represent the long-term lower to upper Miocene transition from a temperate climate to a cold-climate glaciation. The analysis of the short-term variations (interpreted to reflect ice sheet expansions controlled by 41-k.y. insolation changes) requires a quite closely spaced sampled record like that provided by the archive multisensor track. Among those, cycles are best described by spectral reflectance data and, in particular, by a parameter calculated as the ratio of the reflectivity in the green color band and the average reflectivity (gray). In this data report a numerical evaluation of spectral reflectance data was performed and substantiated by correlation with core photos to provide an objective description of the color variations within Site 1165 sediments. The resulting color description provides a reference to categorize the available samples in terms of facies and, hence, a framework for further analyses. Moreover, a link between visually described features and numerical series suitable for spectral analyses is provided.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>188-1165B, 188-1165C, Color, a*, Color, b*, Color, L*, lightness, Color, X, Color, Y, Color, Z, Color code HLS-system, Color GREEN, Color reflectance at 400 nm wavelength, Color reflectance at 410 nm wavelength, Color reflectance at 420 nm wavelength, Color reflectance at 430 nm wavelength, Color reflectance at 440 nm wavelength, Color reflectance at 450 nm wavelength, Color reflectance at 460 nm wavelength, Color reflectance at 470 nm wavelength, Color reflectance at 480 nm wavelength, Color reflectance at 490 nm wavelength, Color reflectance at 500 nm wavelength, Color reflectance at 510 nm wavelength, Color reflectance at 520 nm wavelength, Color reflectance at 530 nm wavelength, Color reflectance at 540 nm wavelength, Color reflectance at 550 nm wavelength, Color reflectance at 560 nm wavelength, Color reflectance at 570 nm wavelength, Color reflectance at 580 nm wavelength, Color reflectance at 590 nm wavelength, Color reflectance at 600 nm wavelength, Color reflectance at 610 nm wavelength, Color reflectance at 620 nm wavelength, Color reflectance at 630 nm wavelength, Color reflectance at 640 nm wavelength, Color reflectance at 650 nm wavelength, Color reflectance at 660 nm wavelength, Color reflectance at 670 nm wavelength, Color reflectance at 680 nm wavelength, Color reflectance at 690 nm wavelength, Color reflectance at 700 nm wavelength, DEPTH, sediment/rock, Difference, DRILL, Drilling/drill rig, Event label, Indian Ocean, Joides Resolution, Leg188, Munsell Color System (1994), Ocean Drilling Program, ODP, ODP sample designation, Run Number, Sample code/label, Spectrophotometer Minolta CM-2002</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2012-05-07</date></data>