<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.779087</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Halocarbon and pigment profiles in the waters of the Amundsen and Ross Seas, Antarctica</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Little is known regarding the distribution of volatile halogenated organic compounds (halocarbons) in Antarctic waters, and their relation to biophysical variables. During the austral summer (December to January) in 2007-08 halocarbon and pigment concentrations were measured in the Amundsen (100-130&#186;W) and Ross Sea (158&#186;W- 160&#186;E). In addition, halocarbons were determined in air, snow and sea ice. The distribution of halocarbons was influenced to a large extent by sea ice, and to a much lesser extent by pelagic biota.  Concentrations of naturally produced halocarbons were elevated in the surface mixed layer in ice covered areas compared to open waters in polynyas and in the bottom waters of the Ross Sea.  Higher concentrations of halocarbons were also found in sea ice brine compared to the surface waters. Incubations of snow revealed an additional source of halocarbons.  The distribution of halocarbons also varied considerably between the Amundsen and Ross Seas, mainly due to the different oceanographic settings.  For iodinated compounds, weak correlations were found with the presence of pigments indicative of Phaeocystis, mainly in the Ross Sea.  Saturation anomalies for the surface water and brine (in sea ice) were determined for the two indicator halocarbons bromoform and chloriodomethane. For bromoform, the surface water anomalies varied between -83 and 11%, whereas chloroiodomethane anomalies varied between -6 and 1,200%. The saturation anomalies for brine varied between -56 to 120% for bromoform and 91 to 22,000% for chloroiodomethane, indicating that sea ice could be a possible source both to the atmosphere and the surface waters.  Polar waters can have a substantial impact on global halocarbon budgets and need to be included in large-scale assessments.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>1,1,1-Trichloroethane, 1,2-Dibromoethane, 19-Butanoyloxyfucoxanthin, 19-Hexanoyloxyfucoxanthin, 1-Iodobutane, 1-Iodoethane, 1-Iodopropane, 2-Iodobutane, Amundsen Sea, Bromochloromethane, Bromodichloromethane, Bromoiodomethane, Calculated, Chloroiodomethane, Chlorophyll a, Chlorophyll a, fractionated, Chlorophyll c3, CTD, SEA-BIRD SBE 911plus, CTD/Rosette, CTD-RO, Date/Time of event, Density, sigma, in situ, Density, sigma-theta (0), DEPTH, water, Dibromochloromethane, Dibromomethane, Diiodomethane, Estimated, Event label, Fucoxanthin, Gas chromatography, Ekdal &amp; Abrahamsson, 1997, Ice coverage, Iodomethane, Latitude of event, Longitude of event, Oden, Oden Southern Ocean, OSO07/08, OSO07/08_10, OSO07/08_11, OSO07/08_12, OSO07/08_13, OSO07/08_14, OSO07/08_15, OSO07/08_16, OSO07/08_17, OSO07/08_18, OSO07/08_19, OSO07/08_20, OSO07/08_21, OSO07/08_22, OSO07/08_23, OSO07/08_24, OSO07/08_25, OSO07/08_26, OSO07/08_27, OSO07/08_28, OSO07/08_29, OSO07/08_30, OSO07/08_31, OSO07/08_32, OSO07/08_33, OSO07/08_4, OSO07/08_5, OSO07/08_6, OSO07/08_7, OSO07/08_8, OSO07/08_9, Salinity, Temperature, water, Tribromomethane</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2012-04-11</date></data>