<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.759978</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Abundance of dinoflagellates and ciliates at time series station Helgoland Roads, North Sea, in 2007</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description /><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Acineta sp., Akashiwo sanguinea, Amphidinium cf. sphenoides, Amphidinium crassum, Askenasia regina, Askenasia sp., BAH, Balanion comatum, fractionated, Ceratium furca, Ceratium fusus, Ceratium horridum, Ceratium lineatum, Cyclotrichium sp., Cyrtostrombidium sp., fractionated, DATE/TIME, DEPTH, water, Didinium gargantua, Dinophysis sp., Diplopsalis cf. lenticula, Euplotes sp., Eutintinnus sp., fractionated, Favella ehrenbergii, German Bight, North Sea, Gonyaulax cf. spinifera, Gymnodinium chlorophorum, Gymnodinium sp., fractionated, Gyrodinium, fractionated, Gyrodinium calyptoglyphe, Gyrodinium sp., fractionated, HelgolandRoads, HelgolandRoadsTimeseries, Heterocapsa cf. niei, Heterocapsa cf. rotundata, Kabeltonne, Katodinium glaucum, Katodinium sp., fractionated, Laboea strobila, Leegaardiella cf. ovalis, Leegaardiella cf. sol, Lohmanniella oviformis, Long-term Ecological Research at AWI, LTER, Meeresstation Helgoland, Mesodinium pulex, Mesodinium sp., fractionated, Mesoporos sp., MON, Monitoring, Myrionecta rubra, fractionated, Nematodinium sp., Noctiluca scintillans, Peridiniella cf. danica, Polykrikos kofoidii, Prorocentrum balticum, Prorocentrum micans, Prorocentrum triestinum, Protoperidinium bipes, Protoperidinium brevipes, Protoperidinium cf. claudicans, Protoperidinium cf. conicum, Protoperidinium cf. divergens, Protoperidinium cf. leonis, Protoperidinium cf. minutum group, Protoperidinium cf. obtusum, Protoperidinium cf. pyriforme group, Protoperidinium cf. subinerme, Protoperidinium denticulatum, Protoperidinium depressum, Protoperidinium excentricum, Protoperidinium ovatum, Protoperidinium pellucidum, Protoperidinium pentagonum, Protoperidinium sp., fractionated, Protoperidinium thorianum, Pyrophacus horologium, Quantitative phytoplankton method (Uterm&#246;hl, 1958), Rimostrombidium sp., Salpingella sp., Scrippsiella, Scuticociliates, fractionated, Shelf Seas Systems Ecology @ AWI (former Biologische Anstalt Helgoland), Spathidium sp., Spatulodinium pseudonoctiluca, Stenosemella sp., Strobilidium cf. neptunii, Strobilidium cf. sphaericum, Strobilidium cf. spiralis, Strobilidium sp., fractionated, Strombidinopsis sp., fractionated, Strombidium, fractionated, Strombidium capitatum, Strombidium cf. acutum, Strombidium cf. conicum, Strombidium cf. emergens, Strombidium cf. epidemum, fractionated, Strombidium cf. lynni, Strombidium cf. tressum, Strombidium sp., fractionated, Tiarina fusus, Tintinnidium cf. balechi, Tintinnid sp., fractionated, Tintinnopsis cf. radix, Tintinnopsis sp., Tontonia gracillima, Torodinium robustum, fractionated, Vorticella sp., Warnowia sp.</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2010-05-02</date></data>