<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.740031</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Neodymium isotopic ratios and clay mineral composition from ODP Hole 1147A and Site 184-1148</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Ocean Drilling Program sampling of the distal passive margin of South China at Sites 1147 and 1148 has yielded clay-rich hemipelagic sediments dating to 32 Ma (Oligocene), just prior to the onset of seafloor spreading in the South China Sea. The location of the drill sites offshore the Pearl River suggests that this river, or its predecessor, may have been the source of the sediment in the basin, which accounts for only not, vert, similar ~1.8% of the total Neogene sediment in the Asian marginal seas. A mean erosion depth of not, vert, similar ~1 km over the current Pearl River drainage basin is sufficient to account for the sediment volume on the margin. Two-dimensional backstripping of across-margin seismic profiles shows that sedimentation rates peaked during the middle Miocene (11-16 Ma) and the Pleistocene (since 1.8 Ma). Nd isotopic analysis of clays yielded epsilonNd values of -7.7 to -11.0, consistent with the South China Block being the major source of sediment. More positive epsilonNd values during and shortly after rifting compared to later sedimentation reflect preferential erosion at that time of more juvenile continental arc rocks exposed along the margin. As the drainage basin developed and erosion shifted from within the rift to the continental interior epsilonNd values became more negative. A rapid change in the clay mineralogy from smectite-dominated to illite dominated at not, vert, similar 15.5 Ma, synchronous with middle Miocene rapid sedimentation, mostly reflects a change to a wetter, more erosive climate. Evidence that the elevation of the Tibetan Plateau and erosion in the western Himalaya both peaked close to this time supports the suggestion that the Asian monsoon became much more intense at that time, much earlier than the 8.5 Ma age commonly accepted.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>184-1147A, 184-1148A, 184-1148B, AGE, Chlorite, DEPTH, sediment/rock, DRILL, Drilling/drill rig, Event label, Illite, Joides Resolution, Kaolinite, Leg184, Mass spectrometer VG 354, Neodymium 143/Neodymium 144, Neodymium 143/Neodymium 144, error, Ocean Drilling Program, ODP, ODP sample designation, Opal-CT, Sample code/label, Smectite, South China Sea, X-ray diffraction TEXTUR, clay fraction, &#949;-Neodymium</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2002-04-01</date></data>