<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.848983</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Abundance and biomass of zooplankton from 1981-1985 collected in front of Constanta city, Black Sea</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>The  Est Constanta 1981-1985 dataset contains zooplankton data collected allong a 5 station transect in front of the city Constanta (44&#176;10'N, 28&#176;41.5'E &#8211; EC1, 44&#176;10'N, 28&#176;47'E &#8211; EC2, 44&#176;10'N, 28&#176;54'E &#8211; EC3, 44&#176;10'N, 29&#176;08'E &#8211; EC4, 44&#176;10'N, 29&#176;22'E &#8211; EC5). Zooplankton sampling was undertaken at 5 stations where samples were collected using a Juday closing net in the 0-10, 10-25, 25-50m layer (depending also on the water masses). The dataset includes samples analysed for mesozooplankton species composition and abundance.Sampling volume was estimated by multiplying the mouth area with the wire length. Taxon-specific mesozooplankton abundance was count under microscope. Total abundance is the sum of the counted individuals. Total biomass Fodder, Rotifera , Ctenophora and Noctiluca was estimated using a tabel with wet weight for each species an stage.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Abundance per volume, Acartia clausi, c1, Acartia clausi, c2, Acartia clausi, c3, Acartia clausi, c4, Acartia clausi, c5, Acartia clausi, female, Acartia clausi, male, Acartia clausi, nauplii, Bivalvia, larvae, Black Sea, Brachionus calyciflorus calyciflorus, Calanus euxinus, c2, Calanus euxinus, c3, Calanus euxinus, c4, Calanus euxinus, c5, Calanus euxinus, female, Calanus euxinus, male, Calanus euxinus, nauplii, Calculated, Centropages ponticus, c3, Centropages ponticus, c4, Centropages ponticus, c5, Centropages ponticus, female, Centropages ponticus, male, Centropages ponticus, nauplii, Cirripedia, cypris, Cirripedia, nauplii, Computed/Converted, Counting, Coxliella helix, Ctenophora, biomass, Cyclops sp., Date/Time of event, Decapoda, larvae, Depth, bottom/max, Depth, top/min, DEPTH, water, EC1, EC2, EC3, EC4, EC5, Est_Constanta_Apr_85_EC1, Est_Constanta_Apr_85_EC2, Est_Constanta_Apr_85_EC3, Est_Constanta_Apr_85_EC4, Est_Constanta_Aug_81_EC1, Est_Constanta_Aug_81_EC2, Est_Constanta_Aug_81_EC3, Est_Constanta_Aug_81_EC4, Est_Constanta_Aug_81_EC5, Est_Constanta_Aug_82_EC1, Est_Constanta_Aug_82_EC2, Est_Constanta_Aug_82_EC3, Est_Constanta_Aug_82_EC4, Est_Constanta_Aug_82_EC5, Est_Constanta_Aug_83_EC3, Est_Constanta_Aug_83_EC4, Est_Constanta_Aug_83_EC5, Est_Constanta_Aug_84_EC1, Est_Constanta_Aug_84_EC2, Est_Constanta_Aug_84_EC3, Est_Constanta_Aug_84_EC4, Est_Constanta_Aug_84_EC5, Est_Constanta_Aug_85_EC1, Est_Constanta_Aug_85_EC2, Est_Constanta_Aug_85_EC3, Est_Constanta_Aug_85_EC4, Est_Constanta_Feb_82_EC1, Est_Constanta_Feb_82_EC2, Est_Constanta_Feb_82_EC3, Est_Constanta_Feb_82_EC4, Est_Constanta_Feb_82_EC5, Est_Constanta_Feb_83_EC3, Est_Constanta_Feb_83_EC4, Est_Constanta_Feb_83_EC5, Est_Constanta_Jul_81_EC1, Est_Constanta_Jul_81_EC2, Est_Constanta_Jul_81_EC3, Est_Constanta_Jul_81_EC4, Est_Constanta_Jul_81_EC5, Est_Constanta_Jun_81_EC1, Est_Constanta_Jun_81_EC2, Est_Constanta_Jun_81_EC3, Est_Constanta_Jun_81_EC4, Est_Constanta_Jun_81_EC5, Est_Constanta_Mai_85_EC1, Est_Constanta_Mai_85_EC2, Est_Constanta_Mai_85_EC3, Est_Constanta_Mai_85_EC4, Est_Constanta_Mai_85_EC5, Est_Constanta_Mar_84_EC1, Est_Constanta_Mar_84_EC2, Est_Constanta_Mar_84_EC3, Est_Constanta_Mar_84_EC4, Est_Constanta_Mar_84_EC5, Est_Constanta_May_81_EC1, Est_Constanta_May_81_EC2, Est_Constanta_May_81_EC3, Est_Constanta_May_81_EC4, Est_Constanta_May_81_EC5, Est_Constanta_May_82_EC1, Est_Constanta_May_82_EC2, Est_Constanta_May_82_EC3, Est_Constanta_May_82_EC4, Est_Constanta_May_82_EC5, Est_Constanta_May_83_EC1, Est_Constanta_May_83_EC2, Est_Constanta_May_83_EC3, Est_Constanta_May_83_EC4, Est_Constanta_May_83_EC5, Est_Constanta_May_84_EC1, Est_Constanta_May_84_EC2, Est_Constanta_May_84_EC3, Est_Constanta_May_84_EC4, Est_Constanta_May_84_EC5, Est_Constanta_Nov_81_EC3, Est_Constanta_Nov_81_EC4, Est_Constanta_Nov_81_EC5, Est_Constanta_Oct_85_EC1, Est_Constanta_Oct_85_EC2, Est_Constanta_Oct_85_EC3, Est_Constanta_Oct_85_EC4, Est_Constanta_Oct_85_EC5, EstConstanta_81-85, Estimated, Eurytemora hirundoides, juvenile, Evadne spinifera, Evadne tergestina, Event label, Favella ehrenbergii, Gastropoda, larvae, Harpacticoida, Helicostomella subulata, JUDAY, Juday net, Latitude of event, Longitude of event, Metacylis mediterranea, Noctiluca, biomass, Noctiluca scintillans, Oikopleura dioica, Oithona nana, female, Oithona nana, juvenile, Oithona nana, male, Oithona nana, nauplii, Oithona similis, female, Oithona similis, juvenile, Oithona similis, male, Oithona similis, nauplii, Oithona similis, ova, Paracalanus parvus, c1, Paracalanus parvus, c2, Paracalanus parvus, c3, Paracalanus parvus, c4, Paracalanus parvus, c5, Paracalanus parvus, female, Paracalanus parvus, male, Paracalanus parvus, nauplii, Penilia avirostris, Pleopis polyphemoides, Pleurobrachia pileus, Polychaeta, larvae, Pontella mediterranea, Pseudocalanus elongatus, c1, Pseudocalanus elongatus, c2, Pseudocalanus elongatus, c3, Pseudocalanus elongatus, c4, Pseudocalanus elongatus, c5, Pseudocalanus elongatus, female, Pseudocalanus elongatus, male, Pseudocalanus elongatus, nauplii, Pseudocalanus elongatus, ova, Rotifera, Rotifera, biomass, Sagitta setosa, Sample comment, Sample volume, SESAME, Southern European Seas: Assessing and Modelling Ecosystem Changes, Steaua de Mare, Strombidium sp., Synchaeta littoralis, Synchaeta sp., Tiarina fusus, Tintinnopsis beroidea, Tintinnopsis campanula, Tintinnopsis cylindrica, Tintinnopsis tubulosa, Zooplankton, biomass, Zooplankton, fodder, biomass</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2015-08-31</date></data>