<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.758631</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Seawater carbonate chemistry and Littorina obtusata biological processes during experiments, 2009</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Our understanding of the effects of ocean acidification on whole organism function is growing, but most current information is for adult stages of development. Here, we show the effects of reduced pH seawater (pH 7.6) on aspects of the development, physiology and behaviour of encapsulated embryos of the marine intertidal gastropod Littorina obtusata. We found reduced viability and increased development times under reduced pH conditions, and the embryos had significantly altered behaviours and physiologies. In acidified seawater, embryos spent more time stationary, had slower rotation rates, spent less time crawling, but increased their movement periodicity compared with those maintained under control conditions. Larval and adult heart rates were significantly lower in acidified seawater, and hatchling snails had an altered shell morphology (lateral length and spiral shell length) compared to control snails. Our findings show that ocean acidification may have multiple, subtle effects during the early development of marine animals that may have implications for their survival beyond those predicted using later life stages.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Alkalinity, total, Animalia, Aragonite saturation state, Behaviour, Benthic animals, Benthos, Bicarbonate ion, Bottles or small containers/Aquaria ( 20 L), Calcite saturation state, Calculated using seacarb after Nisumaa et al. (2010), Carbon, inorganic, dissolved, Carbonate ion, Carbonate system computation flag, Carbon dioxide, Coast and continental shelf, Development, EPOCA, EUR-OCEANS, European network of excellence for Ocean Ecosystems Analysis, European Project on Ocean Acidification, Experimental treatment, Experiment day, Fugacity of carbon dioxide (water) at sea surface temperature (wet air), Growth/Morphology, Laboratory experiment, Littorina obtusata, Littorina obtusata, aperture area, Littorina obtusata, aperture length, Littorina obtusata, aperture width, Littorina obtusata, eggs, empty, Littorina obtusata, embryo, deformed, Littorina obtusata, embryo, half hatched, Littorina obtusata, embryo, time, spinning, Littorina obtusata, embryo, time, stationary, Littorina obtusata, embryo, time crawling, Littorina obtusata, embryo, time moving, Littorina obtusata, embryo, twin, Littorina obtusata, embryo, viable, Littorina obtusata, hatched, Littorina obtusata, hatched, hearbeat, Littorina obtusata, hearbeat, ad, Littorina obtusata, hearbeat, larval, Littorina obtusata, lateral shell length, Littorina obtusata, lateral shell mid-length, Littorina obtusata, periodisation, moving, Littorina obtusata, periodisation, stationary, Littorina obtusata, periodisation, total, Littorina obtusata, rate of motion, whilst moving, Littorina obtusata, spiral length, Littorina obtusata, total rate of motion, Littorina obtusata, ventral shell length, Littorina obtusata, ventral shell width, Mollusca, North Atlantic, OA-ICC, Ocean Acidification International Coordination Centre, PAR sensor LI-700, Li-COR Inc., Partial pressure of carbon dioxide (water) at sea surface temperature (wet air), pH, pH 209 meter (Hanna Instruments), Replicates, Reproduction, Salinity, see reference(s), Single species, Temperate, Temperature, water</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2009-03-28</date></data>