<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.820339</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Short-term metabolic and growth responses of the cold-water coral lophelia pertusa to ocean acidification</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Cold-water corals are amongst the most three-dimensionally complex deep-sea habitats known and are associated with high local biodiversity. Despite their importance as ecosystem engineers, little is known about how these organisms will respond to projected ocean acidification. Since preindustrial times, average ocean pH has already decreased from 8.2 to ~ 8.1. Predicted CO2 emissions will decrease this by up to another 0.3 pH units by the end of the century. This decrease in pH may have a wide range of impacts upon marine life, and in particular upon calcifiers such as cold-water corals. Lophelia pertusa is the most widespread cold-water coral (CWC) species, frequently found in the North Atlantic. Data here relate to a short term data set (21 days) on metabolism and net calcification rates of freshly collected L. pertusa from Mingulay Reef Complex, Scotland. These data from freshly collected L. pertusa from the Mingulay Reef Complex will help define the impact of ocean acidification upon the growth, physiology and structural integrity of this key reef framework forming species.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Alkalinity, total, Alkalinity, total, standard deviation, Alkalinity anomaly technique (Smith and Key, 1975), Animalia, Aragonite saturation state, Aragonite saturation state, standard deviation, Benthic animals, Benthos, Bicarbonate ion, Calcification/Dissolution, Calcification rate, standard error, Calcification rate of calcium carbonate, Calcite saturation state, Calculated using CO2SYS, Calculated using seacarb after Nisumaa et al. (2010), Carbon, inorganic, dissolved, Carbon, inorganic, dissolved, standard deviation, Carbonate ion, Carbonate system computation flag, Carbon dioxide, Cnidaria, Coast and continental shelf, Containers and aquaria (20- 1000 L or &lt; 1 m**2), EXP, Experiment, Fugacity of carbon dioxide (water) at sea surface temperature (wet air), Growth/Morphology, Growth rate, Growth rate, standard error, Incubation duration, Laboratory experiment, Lophelia pertusa, Mingulayreef, North Atlantic, OA-ICC, Ocean Acidification International Coordination Centre, Partial pressure of carbon dioxide (water) at sea surface temperature (wet air), pH, pH, standard deviation, Polyp number, Respiration, Respiration rate, oxygen, Respiration rate, oxygen, standard deviation, Respiration rate, oxygen, standard error, Salinity, Single species, Species, Temperate, Temperature, water, Tissue, dry mass, UKOA, United Kingdom Ocean Acidification research programme</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2013-10-14</date></data>