<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.54321</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Pollen analysis of sediment profile HAE10 from H&#228;melsee</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description /><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Acer, Acroperus harpae, Alnus, Alona affinis, Alona guttata, Alonella excisa, Alonella nana, Apiaceae apioide-type, Artemisia, Asplanchna priodonta, Betula, Bosmina longirostris-group, Brachionus cf. urceolaris, Brassicaceae, Calluna, Campanulaceae, Camptocercus rectirostris, Carpinus betulus, Caryophyllaceae, Centaurea cyanus, Centaurea jacea-type, Ceratophyllum: spines, Changes in the Geo-Biosphere during the last 15000 years, Chaoborus flavicans, Chenopodiaceae, Chironomidae, other, Cladocera, nonplanktic, Cladocera, planktic, Coelastrum polychordum, Collotheca sp., Conochilus natans, Corylus, Cosmarium sp., Counting, palynology, Cyperaceae, Daphnidae mandibles and claws, DEPTH, sediment/rock, Dryopteris, Empetrum, Ephedra fragilis-type, Equisetum, Ericales, Euastrum sp., Eurycercus lamellatus, Fagopyrum, Fagus, Filinia longiseta passa/Filinia hofmanni, Filipendula, Frangula alnus, Fraxinus, GeoBio15k, Gramineae, HAE10, H&#228;melsee, Hedera, Helianthemum cf. H. canum, Hexarthra mira, Humulus and Cannabis and Urtica, Juniperus, LakeSedNLfB, Lamiaceae, Monospilus dispar, Myrica, Myriophyllum spicatum, Nymphaea, Nymphaeaceae: trichome, Ostracoda mandible, PC_SM, Pediastrum bireticulatum, Pediastrum boryanum, Pediastrum boryanum rugulatum, Pediastrum boryanum ssp. boryanum, Pediastrum duplex, Pediastrum integrum, Pediastrum kawraiskyi, Picea, Pinus, Pinus: stomata, Piston corer Streif/Merkt, Plantago lanceolata, Plantago major, Pleuroxus trigonellus, Polygonum amphibium, Polypodiaceae, Polypodium vulgare, Populus, Potamogeton, Potentilla-type, Procladius sp., Pteridium, Quercus, Ranunculaceae, Ranunculus subgen. Batrachium-type, Rosaceae, other, Rotatoria, other, Rotatoria, resting eggs, Rubiaceae cf. galium, Rumex, Salix, Sampling/drilling in lake, Scenedesmus quadricauda, Secale cereale, Selaginella selaginoides, Sida crystallina, Sparganium-type, Sphagnum, Sphagnum sp., leaves, Staurastrum cf. gracilis, Tanytarsini, Taxus, Thalictrum, Thelypteris palustris, Tilia, Triticum/Hordeum, Tubuliflorae other, Turbellaria Rhabdocoela eggs, Ulmus, Utricularia, Vaccinium, Varia, Viscum</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2001-08-11</date></data>