<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.856894</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Annotated record of the detailed examination of Mn deposits from various ship expeditions in the Atlantic Ocean from 1876 until 1911</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>The greater part of this Monograph is devoted to detailed descriptions of 1426 samples of deposits from the floor of the Atlantic Ocean stored in the Challenger Office, Edinburgh, which had been collected during thirty-five cruising expeditions between 1857 and 1911. The remaining part discusses the results of the work. The work of examining and describing in detail this abundant mass of material was in progress when the late Sir JOHN MURRAY met his death in March 1914. By that time about three-fourths of the descriptive work had been completed under his supervision. Sir John's trustees arranged for the completion of the descriptive work by Mr Chumley, and this was done in the Challenger Office during the two succeeding years. Later, after he had removed to Glasgow, Mr Chumley prepared the notes discussing the results. The trustees have pleasure in recording, on the suggestion of Mr Chumley, the courtesy of Dr G. W. Lee of the Geological Survey of Scotland, for help in determining many of the rarer mineral particles contained in the deposits.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Atlantic Ocean, BRT-1163-182, BRT-1189-22, BRT-1210-44, BRT-1213-49, BRT-1214-51, BRT-1224-62, BRT-1367-232, BRT-1476-363, BRT-1479-366, BRT-1491-378, BRT-1494-383, BRT-1523-413, BRT-1540-435, BRT-1554-451, BRT-MUR-90, Comment, DAC-3593-204, DAC-3595-226, DAC-3598-265, Date/Time of event, Deposit type, DEPTH, sediment/rock, Description, DOL-MUR-18, DOL-MUR-22, Dredge, DRG, EGE-4311-5, Elevation of event, ENT-MUR-5557, ENT-MUR-5558, ENT-MUR-5559, ENT-MUR-5560, ENT-MUR-5561, ENT-MUR-5581, ENT-MUR-5583, ENT-MUR-5584, ENT-MUR-5585, ENT-MUR-5587, ENT-MUR-5588, ENT-MUR-5589, ENT-MUR-5590, ENT-MUR-5592, ENT-MUR-5593, ENT-MUR-5612, ENT-MUR-5616, ENT-MUR-5623, ENT-MUR-5641, ENT-MUR-5642, ENT-MUR-5643, ENT-MUR-5644, ENT-MUR-5645, ENT-MUR-5646, ENT-MUR-5656, ENT-MUR-5658, Event label, FARD-4521-60, FARD-4535-74, FARD-4543-85, GETY-MUR-a, GETY-MUR-b, GETY-MUR-c, GLDF-4621-164, GLDF-4622-165, GLDF-4627-175, GLDF-4628-176, GLDF-4629-177, GLDF-4649-200, GLDF-4653-204, Latitude of event, Longitude of event, NOAA and MMS Marine Minerals Geochemical Database, NOAA-MMS, Position, Quantity of deposit, RMBL-7331-15, RMBL-7337-22, RMBL-7338-23, RMBL-7340-26, RMBL-7346-31, RMBL-7347-32, RMBL-7348-33, RMBL-7384-5, RMBL-7387-10, RMBL-7391-29, Sample code/label, Sample ID, SCTI-7435-10, SCTI-7436-11, SCTI-7438-13, SCTI-7442-17, Sediment type, SENE-7583-22, SENE-7584-27, SENE-7587-32, SENE-7588-33, SENE-7590-35, SENE-7591-36, SENE-7592-37, SENE-7593-38, SENE-7596-41, SENE-7597-42, SENE-7598-43, SENE-7599-44, SENE-7600-45, SENE-7601-47, SENE-7605-53A, SENE-7606-54, Size, SLVT-7870-4, SSUK-9037-3, STPH-7900-12, Substrate type, TLMN-9148-136</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>1924-02-08</date></data>