<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.747711</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>(Table 1) Quantitative analysis of mollusk taxa from surface sediment samples in the Golfe d'Arguin</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Ecological and taxonomic study of the mollusk-rich fauna of the Golfe d'Arguin, North Mauritania, investigates the various environmental influences affecting this tropical shelf. The upwelling of nutrient-rich waters leads to a highly productive environment under tropical conditions. The resulting mixed carbonate-siliciclastic sediment contains a large portion of calcareous components produced by heterotrophic organisms--e.g., mollusks, foraminifers, worms, barnacles--that are reworked on the open shelf. On the basis of mollusk assemblages, six taphocoenoses are defined, all being characterized by a mixed fauna of tropical (e.g., Tellina densestriata), subtropical (e.g., Macoma cumana) and temperate (e.g., Spisula subtruncata) species. Differences between the assemblages are related to the medium--grain size ranging from mud to gravel--that results from local hydrodynamic conditions and water depth. Among carbonate grains, Donax burnupi shells are very abundant in the swell-exposed, northern part of the Golfe d'Arguin and reflect the tropical to subtropical, high-energy, and high-nutrient waters. Mollusk assemblages are demonstrated to be a sensitive tool for deciphering complex environmental conditions in sedimentary archives.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Abra alba, Abra lecointrei, Abra sp., Acteocina knockeri, Aequipecten flabellum, Aequipecten opercularis, Aequipecten sp., Alvania cf. internodula, Alvania fariai, Alvania marioi, Alvania parvula, Alvania sp., Anadara polii, Anadara sp., Anodontia senegalensis, Anodontia sp., Anomia ephippium, Anomia sp., Anomiidae, Arcidae, Asthenotoma lamothei, Atrina sp., Barleeia sp., Basisulcata lepida, Bela sp., Benthonella sp., BG, Bivalvia, Boomerang-Grab, Bornia sp., Brachycythara atlantidea, Buccinidae, Bufonaria marginata, Callista floridella, Calyptrea africana, Cardiidae, Cardiocardita ajar, Cardiocardita cf. lacunosa, Carditamera contigua, Cardita sp., Carditidae, Center for Marine Environmental Sciences, Chama crenulata, Chama sp., Chamidae, Chauvetia joani, Chauvetia sp., Chrysallida sigmoidea, Chrysallida sp., Circomphalus foliaceolamellosa, Cirsotrema cochlea, Clavatula mystica, Coracuta sp., Corbula gibba, Corbula laticostata, Corbula sp., Counting &gt;1000 &#181;m fraction, Crassatina marchadi, Crassatina sp., Crepidula porcellana, Cuna gambiensis, Cylichna cylindracea, Cystiscidae, Dentimargo bojadorensis, DEPTH, sediment/rock, Digitaria digitaria, Diplodonta dautzenbergii, Diplodonta rotundata, Diplodonta sp., Donacidae, Donax burnupi, Donax oweni, Dosinia adami, Dosinia exoleta, Dosinia lupinus afra, Dosinia sp., Dredge, DRG, Elevation of event, Ensis goreensis, Epitoniidae, Epitonium sp., Ervilia castanea, Eulimidae, Euspira grossularia, Event label, Fissurellidae, Fusinus sp., Fustiaria maltzani, Fustiariidae, Gari depressa, Gari fervensis, Gari jousseaumeana, Gari pseudoweinkauffi, Gari sp., Gastropoda, GeoB11509-1, GeoB11511B, GeoB11511E, GeoB11511F, GeoB11522-1, GeoB11525-1, GeoB11527-1, GeoB11534-1, GeoB11535-1, GeoB11540-1, GeoB11547-1, GeoB11549-1, GeoB11591A, GeoB11595-1, GeoB11601-1, GeoB11607-1, GeoB11613-1, GeoB11614-1, Giant box corer, Gibberula chudeaui, Gibberula sp., Gibbula joubini, Gibbula sp., GKG, Glans aculeata, Glycymeris sp., Gouldia minima, Gouldia sp., Granulina sp., Heteranomia squamula, Hiatella arctica, Kurtiella bidentata, Laevicardium crassum, Lamellolucina reyrei, Latitude of event, Limaria cf. gwyni, Limopsis sp., Linga adansoni, Longitude of event, Lucinidae, Macoma cumana, Macoma melo, Mactra glabrata, Mactra inconstans, Mactra sp., Mactridae, Manupecten pesfelis, Marginella cleryi, Marginella poppei, Marginella sp., Marginellidae, MARUM, Mesalia flammifera, Mesalia freytagi, Mesalia opalina, Mesalia sp., Modiolus nicklesi, Modiolus sp., Montacutidae, Myrtea sp., Myrtea spinifera, Mytilidae, Nassariidae, Nassarius argenteus, Nassarius atlantideus, Nassarius denticulatus, Nassarius desmouloides, Nassarius elatus, Nassarius goreensis, Nassarius miga, Nassarius sp., Natica adansoni, Natica fulminea, Natica sp., Natica turtoni, Naticidae, Nucula crassicostata, Nuculana bicuspidata, Nuculana commutata, Nuculana gruveli, Nuculana sp., Nucula nicklesi, Nucula nitidosa, Odostomia sp., off Mauritania, Ostreidae, Ostreola stentina, Pagodula fraseri, Pandora cf. oblonga, Pectinidae, Persicual cornea, Persicula cingulata, Persicula sp., Phaxas tenellus, Pitar belcheri, Pitar sp., Plagiocardium papillosum, Plagiocardium sp., POS346, POS-346, POS346_09-1, POS346_100-1, POS346_105-1, POS346_111-1, POS346_112-1, POS346_11B, POS346_11E, POS346_11F, POS346_22-1, POS346_25-1, POS346_27-1, POS346_34-1, POS346_35-1, POS346_40-1, POS346_47-1, POS346_49-1, POS346_91A, POS346_95-1, Poseidon, Pyramidellidae, Pyrunculus hoernesii, Raphitoma sp., Ringicula conformis, Ringicula sp., Rissoidae, Sample code/label, Scacchia sp., Scaphopoda, Similipecten similis, Sinistrella sinistralis, Skeneidae, Spisula sp., Spisula subtruncata, Tellina boucheti, Tellina compressa, Tellina densestriata, Tellina donacina, Tellina hanleyi, Tellina posteli, Tellina pseudopusilla, Tellina rubicincta, Tellina sp., Terebridae, Thracia phaseolina, Thyasira flexuosa, Thyasira sp., Timoclea ovata, Total counts, Tricolia pullus, Triphoridae, Trochidae, Trophon gruveli, Turbonilla cf. lactea, Turbonilla lactea, Turbonilla sp., Turridae, Turritella bicingulata, Turritella sp., Turritellidae, van Veen Grab, Veneridae, Venerupis dura, Venus crebrisulca, Venus erronea, Venus punctigera, Venus sp., VGRAB, Volvarina ambigua, Volvarina sp., Volvulella acuminata, Yoldiella philippiana, Zebina sp.</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2010-10-26</date></data>