<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.757877</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Seismic velocities and elastic properties of gabbroic rocks from ODP Hole 118-735B</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>The nearly continuous recovery of 0.5 km of generally fresh, layer 3 gabbroic rocks at Hole 735B, especially near the bottom of the section, presents scientists an unusual opportunity to study the detailed elastic properties of the lower oceanic crust. Extending compressional-wave and density shipboard measurements at room pressure, Vp and Vs were measured at pressures from 20 to 200 MPa using the pulse transmission method. All of the rocks exhibit significant increases in velocity with increasing pressure up to about 150 MPa, a feature attributed to the closing of microcrack porosity. Measured velocities reflect the mineralogical makeup and microstructures acquired during the tectonic history of Hole 735B. Most of the undeformed and unaltered gabbros are approximately 65:35 plagioclase/clinopyroxene rocks plus olivine or oxide minerals, and the observed densities and velocities are fully consistent with the Voigt-Reuss-Hill (VRH) averages of the component minerals and their proportions. Depending on their olivine content, the predominant olivine gabbros at 200 MPa have average Vp = 7.1 &#177; 0.2 km/s, Vs = 3.9 &#177; 0.1 km/s, and grain densities of 2.95 &#177; 0.5 g/cm3. The less abundant iron-titanium (Fe-Ti) oxide gabbros average Vp = 6.75 &#177; 0.15 km/s, Vs = 3.70 &#177; 0.1 km/s, and grain densities of 3.22 &#177; 0.05 g/cm3, reflecting the higher densities and lower velocities of oxide minerals compared to olivine. About 30% of the core is plastically deformed, and the densities and directionally averaged velocities of these shear-zone tectonites are generally consistent with those of the gabbros, their protoliths. Three sets of observations indicate that the shear-zone metagabbros are elastically anisotropic: (1) directional variations in Vp, both vertical and horizontal and with respect to foliation and lineation, (2) discrepancies among Vp values for the horizontal cores and the VRH averages of the component minerals and their mineral proportions, suggesting preferred crystallographic orientations of anisotropic minerals, and (3) variations of Vs of up to 7%, with polarization directions parallel and perpendicular to foliation. Optical inspection of thin sections of the same samples indicates that plagioclase feldspar, clinopyroxene, and amphibole typically display crystallographic-preferred orientations, and this, plus the elastic anisotropy of these minerals, suggests that preferred orientations are responsible for much of the observed anisotropy, particularly at high pressure. Alteration tends to be localized to brittle faults and brecciated zones, and typical alteration minerals are amphibole and secondary plagioclase, which do not significantly change the velocity-density relationships.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>118-735B, DRILL, Drilling/drill rig, Joides Resolution, Leg118, Ocean Drilling Program, ODP, South Indian Ridge, South Indian Ocean</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>1991-03-01</date></data>