<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.739965</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Pollen profile WOLB, Wolbrom, Poland</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description /><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Abies alba, Agrimonia, Alisma plantago-aquatica-type, Alnus, Anemone-type, Apiaceae undifferentiated, Arctostaphylos, Artemisia, Asteroideae, Betula, Betula nana-type, Boraginaceae, Botrychium, Bupleurum, Calluna vulgaris, Caltha-type, Campanula, Caryophyllaceae undifferentiated, Ceratophyllum hair, Chamaenerion angustifolium, Chenopodiaceae, Cichorioideae, Cirsium-type, Cladium mariscus, Corylus avellana, Cruciferae, Cynoglossum, Cyperaceae undifferentiated, Delphinium-type, DEPTH, sediment/rock, Dryas octopetala, Dryopteris-type, Empetrum, Ephedra distachya-type, Equisetum, Ericaceae undifferentiated, Fabaceae undifferentiated, Fagus sylvatica, Filipendula, Fraxinus excelsior, Galium-type, Gentiana, Gentiana nivalis-type, Gramineae undifferentiated, Helianthemum undifferentiated, Hippophae rhamnoides, Hottonia palustris, Humulus/Cannabis, Indeterminable: unknown, Juniperus communis, Labiatae, Larix, Lycopodium annotinum, Lycopodium undifferentiated, Melampyrum, Mentha-type, Menyanthes trifoliata, Myriophyllum spicatum/verticillatum, Oxyria digyna, Papaver, Pediastrum, Pedicularis, Picea abies, Pimpinella major-type, Pinus, Plantago major, Plantago major/media, Plantago maritima, Plantago maritima-type, Pleurospermum austriacum, Polemonium caeruleum, Polypodium vulgare, Populus, Potamogeton sect. Coleogeton, Potamogeton sect. Eupotamogeton, Potentilla-type, ProfileWOL-3, Pteridium aquilinum, Quercus, Ranunculaceae undifferentiated, Ranunculus acris-type, Ribes, Rosaceae undifferentiated, Rubus, Rumex acetosa/R. acetosella, Sagina, Salix polaris-type, Salix undifferentiated, Sambucus nigra-type, Sanguisorba minor, Saxifraga, Saxifraga cf. S. nivalis, Saxifraga oppositifolia-type, Scleranthus perennis, Scrophulariaceae, Selaginella selaginoides, Silene dioica-type, Sorbus aucuparia, Sparganium-type, Spergularia-type, Sphagnum, Stachys sylvatica-type, Stellaria, Thalictrum, Tilia, Typha latifolia, Ulmus, Urtica, Utricularia, WOLB, Wolbrom, Poland</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2010-06-08</date></data>