<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.711716</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>(Table 1) Average aluminium accumulation rate at 40 DSDP Sites for the time interval 0-10 Ma and relative rates for other time intervals</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>A six-fold increase in the rate of accumulation of Al in north and central Atlantic and Pacific Ocean sediments indicates vastly increased denudation of the continents during the past 15 Ma. The increase is more apparent in hemipelagic than pelagic sites, demonstrating widely distributed local controls. Similarities in the rate of increase in the Atlantic and Pacific show that tectonic elevation is not responsible for the difference in sedimentation rate. Also, similarities in the difference at sites of low and high latitude suggest that glaciation is not the most significant source. A lack of correspondence between sedimentation rates and Vail's sea-level curve similarly rule out that effect. The conclusion drawn here is that worldwide climatic deterioration during the late Tertiary is the explanation for the striking increase in detrital sedimentation in the World ocean.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>10-94, 11-106, 12-116, 12-118, 12-119, 14-142, 15-149, 16-158, 18-173, 18-178, 19-183, 19-192, 21-206, 21-210, 22-213, 22-214, 22-218, 24-231, 24-236, 24-238, 25-241, 26-250, 28-266, 29-278, 30-289, 31-292, 31-296, 31-297, 32-310, 34-321, 38-338, 38-341, 39-354, 40-362, 41-366, 4-29, 4-30, 43-382, 5-34, 7-62, Accumulation rate, aluminium, Antarctic Ocean/BASIN, Antarctic Ocean/RIDGE, Caribbean Sea/BASIN, Caribbean Sea/RIDGE, Deep Sea Drilling Project, DRILL, Drilling/drill rig, DSDP, Event label, Glomar Challenger, Gulf of Mexico/SCARP, Indian Ocean//BASIN, Indian Ocean//FAN, Indian Ocean//FRACTURE ZONE, Indian Ocean//RIDGE, Indian Ocean/Gulf of Aden/BASIN, Latitude of event, Leg10, Leg11, Leg12, Leg14, Leg15, Leg16, Leg18, Leg19, Leg21, Leg22, Leg24, Leg25, Leg26, Leg28, Leg29, Leg30, Leg31, Leg32, Leg34, Leg38, Leg39, Leg4, Leg40, Leg41, Leg43, Leg5, Leg7, Longitude of event, North Atlantic/BASIN, North Atlantic/CONT RISE, North Atlantic/Norwegian Sea, North Atlantic/Norwegian Sea/PLATEAU, North Atlantic/PLAIN, North Atlantic/SEAMOUNT, North Pacific/CONT RISE, North Pacific/GUYOT, North Pacific/Philippine Sea/BASIN, North Pacific/Philippine Sea/CONT RISE, North Pacific/Philippine Sea/RIDGE, North Pacific/PLAIN, North Pacific/RIDGE, North Pacific/SLOPE, Number of observations, Ratio, South Atlantic/RIDGE, South Pacific/BASIN, South Pacific/Coral Sea/BASIN, South Pacific/PLATEAU, South Pacific/Tasman Sea/BASIN</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>1982-01-22</date></data>