<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.769757</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Sedimentology on surface sediments from Lake Ohrid</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Lake Ohrid is likely of Pliocene age and thus commonly referred to as the oldest existing lake in Europe. In this study spatial variability of recent sediment composition is assessed using &gt;50 basin wide distributed surface sediment samples. Analysis of biogeochemical bulk parameters, selected metals, pigment concentrations as well as grain size distributions revealed a significant spatial heterogeneity in surface sediment composition. It implies that sedimentation in Lake Ohrid is controlled by an interaction of multiple natural and anthropogenic factors and processes. Major factors controlling surface sediment composition are related to differences in geological catchment characteristics, anthropogenic land use, and a counterclockwise rotating surface water current. In some instances processes controlling sediment composition also seem to impact distribution patterns of biodiversity, which suggests a common interaction of processes responsible for both patterns.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Aluminium, Calcium, Carbon, inorganic, total, Carbon, organic, total, Carbon/Nitrogen ratio, Chlorophyll a per unit sediment mass, Chromium, Cobalt, Copper, DEPTH, sediment/rock, Feldspar (Area, 3.18&#197;), GC, Gravity corer, Iron, Lake Ohrid, Macedonian/Albanian border, LATITUDE, Lithium, LONGITUDE, Magnesium, Manganese, Nickel, Nitrogen, total, OHRID, Potassium, Silt, very coarse, Silt, very fine, Size fraction &lt; 0.002 mm, &gt; 9 phi, clay, Size fraction 0.0063-0.002 mm, fine silt, Size fraction 0.020-0.0063 mm, medium silt, Size fraction 0.063-0.020 mm, coarse silt, Size fraction 0.125-0.063 mm, 3.0-4.0 phi, very fine sand, Size fraction 0.250-0.125 mm, 2.0-3.0 phi, fine sand, Size fraction 0.500-0.250 mm, 1.0-2.0 phi, medium sand, UTM Easting, Universal Transverse Mercator, UTM Northing, Universal Transverse Mercator, UTM Zone, Universal Transverse Mercator</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2011-09-12</date></data>