<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.77387</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Relative abundance of dead benthic foraminifera of sediment core M5/2_107MC</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description /><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Abditodendrix rhomboidalis, Adercotryma sp., Alliatinella panayensis, Allogromiida sp., Ammobaculites sp., Ammodiscus catinus, Ammodiscus flavians, Ammonia beccarii, Ammonia sp., Ammoscalaria cf. pseudospiralis, Ammoscalaria sp., Amphistegina sp., Angulogerina angulosa, Assilina sp., Astrononion sp., Bolivina dilatata, Bolivina limbata, Bolivina persiensis, Bolivina variabilis, Bolivinellina cf. pescicula, Brizalina subspathulata, Bulimina elongata, Bulimina marginata, Buliminella elegantissima, Cancris auriculus, Caribeanella elatensis, Cassidelina sp., Cassidelina spinescens, Cassidulina minuta, Cibicides aravaensis, Cibicides mahabeti, Cibicides mayori, Cibicides pseudolobatulus, Cibicides sp., Cibicides tenuimargo, Cibicidoides pseudoungerianus, Cibicidoides sp., Cornuspira planorbis, Counting &gt;125 &#181;m fraction, Cribrostomoides sp., Cushmanina sp., Cycloforina collumnosa, Cycloforina sp., Cymbaloporella tabellaeformis, Cymbaloporetta sp., Dentalina sp., Depth, bottom/max, DEPTH, sediment/rock, Depth, top/min, Diocibicides biserialis, Discorbinella bertheloti, Eggerella sp., Elphidium sp., Epistominella sp., Evolutononion sp., Evolvocassidulina belfordi, Favulina melosquamosa, Fursenkoina hybrida, Fursenkoina sp., Gavelinopsis praegeri, GeoT&#252;, Glandulina laevigata, Glandulina sp., Globocassidulina cf. n., Globocassidulina orientalis, Globotextularia sp., Glomospira charoides, Gyroidina soldanii, Haddonia sp., Hanzawaia sp., Haplophragmoides bradyi, Hormosina guttifera, Hyalinonetrion gracilis, Labrospira sp., Lagena cf. simistriata, Lagenammina cf. atlant., Lagenammina difflugiformis, Lagenammina sp., Lagena sp., Lagena strumosa, Lamarckina ventricosa, Lenticulina sp., Loxostomina amygdalaeformis, Loxostomina cf. africanus, Loxostomina cf. sinistralis, Loxostomina limbata, M5/2, M5/2_107MC, Meteor (1986), Miliolinella cf. hybrida, Miliolinella sp., Miliolinella subrotunda, Millettiana millettii, Morulaeplecta sp., MUC, MultiCorer, Neoeponides bradyi, Neorotalia sp., Neouvigerina ampullacea, Neouvigerina interrupta, Neouvigerina porrecta, Nodellum sp., Nonionoides grateloupi, Paleoceanography at T&#252;bingen University, Palliolatella bradii minima, Paracassidulina neocarinata, Paratrochammina mad., Paratrochammina sp., Patellinella sp., Paumotua terebra, Peneroplis planatus, Pentagonia sp., Plotnikovina cf. aequa, Pseudogaudryina sp., Pseudomassilina australis, Pulsiphonina sp., Pygmaeoseistron sp., Pyrgo rotalaria, Pyrgo sp., Quinqueloculina eburnea, Quinqueloculina patagonica, Quinqueloculina sp., Reophax sp., Reussella neopolitana, Robertinoides bradyi, Rosalina orientalis, Rosalina suezensis, Saccammina sp., Sagrinella lobata, Sahulia kerimbaensis, Sigmoiliuita sp., Sigmoilopsis minuta, Siphonaperta horrida, Siphonaperta hybrida, Siphonaperta pittensis, Siphonina tubulosa, Siphotextularia heterostoma, Siphouvigerina fimbriata, Sorites variabilis, Spirillina vivipara, Spiroloculina aff. communis, Spiroloculina antillarum, Spiroloculina cf. pellucida, Spiroloculina hybrida, Spiroloculina sp., Spirophthalmidium cf. elegans, Spirotextularia floridana, Svratkina sp., Textularia cushmani, Tretomphalus bulloides, Triloculina affinis, Triloculina tricarinata, Trochammina globigeriniformis, Trochammina sp., Tubular agglutinants, Valvulineria laevigata, Vasicostella inflatiperforata, Wiesnerella sp.</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2001-09-04</date></data>