<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.763348</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Seawater carbonate chemistry and community calcification near Lizar Island, 2011</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>It is predicted that surface ocean pH will reach 7.9, possibly 7.8 by the end of this century due to increased carbon dioxide (CO2) in the atmosphere and in the surface ocean. While aragonite-rich sediments don't begin to dissolve until a threshold pH of ~ 7.8 is reached, dissolution from high-Mg calcites is evident with any drop in pH. Indeed, it is high-Mg calcite that dominates the reaction of carbonate sediments with increased CO2, which undergoes a rapid neomorphism process to a more stable, low-Mg calcite. This has major implications for the future of the high-Mg calcite producing organisms within coral reef ecosystems. In order to understand any potential buffering system offered by the dissolution of carbonate sediments under a lower oceanic pH, this process of high-Mg calcite dissolution in the reef environment must be further elucidated.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Alkalinity, total, Alkalinity anomaly technique (Smith and Key, 1975), Aragonite saturation state, Benthos, Bicarbonate ion, Bottles or small containers/Aquaria ( 20 L), Calcification/Dissolution, Calcification rate of calcium carbonate, Calcite saturation state, Calcium, Calculated using CO2SYS, Calculated using seacarb after Nisumaa et al. (2010), Carbon, inorganic, dissolved, Carbonate ion, Carbonate system computation flag, Carbon dioxide, Coast and continental shelf, Entire community, EPOCA, EUR-OCEANS, European network of excellence for Ocean Ecosystems Analysis, European Project on Ocean Acidification, Fugacity of carbon dioxide (water) at sea surface temperature (wet air), Identification, Incubation duration, Laboratory experiment, Magnesium, Measured, Metrohm Titrando titrator, OA-ICC, Ocean Acidification International Coordination Centre, Partial pressure of carbon dioxide (water) at sea surface temperature (wet air), pH, Rocky-shore community, Salinity, Sample ID, Site, South Pacific, Temperature, water, Time of day, Tropical, Varian Vista Pro Inductively Coupled Plasma Atomic Emission Spectrometer, &#916; alkalinity, total</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2011-07-21</date></data>