<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.739124</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Pollen profile CLEAT, Loch Cleat, United Kingdom</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description /><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Achillea-type, Alnus glutinosa, Angelica-type, Arenaria-type, Artemisia, Athyrium filix-femina, Betula, Betula/Corylus/Myrica, Blechnum spicant, Botrychium lunaria, Botryococcus, Calluna vulgaris, Caltha-type, Caryophyllaceae undifferentiated, Centaurea nigra-type, Cerastium alpinum-type, Cerastium undifferentiated, Cerealia-type, Chenopodiaceae, Cichorioideae, Cirsium/Carduus, CLEAT, Compositae, Conopodium-type, Corylus/Myrica, Cruciferae, Cyperaceae, DEPTH, sediment/rock, Dryopteris carthusiana-type, Dryopteris filix-mas-type, Empetrum nigrum, Epilobium-type, Equisetum, Ericales undifferentiated, Fagus sylvatica, Filipendula, Filipendula vulgaris, Fraxinus excelsior, Fungal Hyphae, Geum, Gramineae, Hedera helix, Heracleum sphondylium, Humulus lupulus, Hydrocotyle vulgaris, Hypericum pulchrum-type, Indeterminable: broken, Indeterminable: concealed, Indeterminable: corroded, Indeterminable: crumpled, Indeterminable: degraded, Isoetes lacustris, Juniperus communis, Leguminosae undifferentiated, Littorella uniflora, Livingstone piston corer, Loch Cleat, United Kingdom, Lonicera periclymenum, Lotus, LPC, Lycopodium annotinum, Melampyrum, Mentha-type, Menyanthes trifoliata, Mercurialis perennis, Myriophyllum alterniflorum, Myriophyllum spicatum/verticillatum, Narthecium ossifragum, Nymphaea, Ononis-type, Osmunda regalis, Pediastrum, Phragmites-type, Picea, Pinus sylvestris, Plantago lanceolata, Plantago major/media, Plantago maritima, Polypodium, Populus tremula, Potamogeton subgen. Coleogeton, Potamogeton-type, Potentilla-type, Prunella-type, Prunus cf. P. padus, Pteridium aquilinum, Quercus, Ranunculus acris-type, Ranunculus trichophyllus-type, Ranunculus undifferentiated, Rhinanthus-type, Rhizopoda, Rosaceae undifferentiated, Rubiaceae, Rubus saxatilis, Rumex acetosa-type, Rumex acetosella-type, Rumex crispus-type, Rumex subgen. Acetosa/R. subgen. Acetosella, Salix, Salix pentandra-type, Sambucus nigra, Saussurea alpina, Saxifraga aizoides, Saxifraga granulata-type, Saxifraga oppositifolia, Selaginella selaginoides, Silene dioica-type, Solidago-type, Sorbus aucuparia, Sparganium-type, Spergula/Spergularia, Sphagnum, Stachys-type, Stellaria undifferentiated, Succisa pratensis, Teucrium, Thalictrum, Thelypteris phegopteris, Thelypteris-type, Tilia cordata, Trifolium, Trifolium pratense-type, Typha latifolia, Ulex-type, Ulmus, Unknown pollen and spores, Urtica, Valeriana officinalis, Varia, Viburnum opulus, Vicia/Lathyrus, Viola palustris</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2010-06-08</date></data>