<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.837858</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>(Table 2) Ba/Ca ratios of Cibicides wuellerstorfi and Orbulina universa from Bahaman sediment cores</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>This geochemical investigation utilizes Ba/Ca in the benthic foraminifer Cibicides wuellerstorfi from cores taken from the Bahama Banks and the Caribbean Sea to reconstruct changes in basal thermocline ventilation (800&#8211;1000 m) and middepth thermohaline circulation (1000&#8211;2000 m) in the western North Atlantic during the last glacial period, focusing on the deglacial transition. Previous studies show that an increase in ventilation of the North Atlantic subtropical gyre during the Last Glacial Maximum (LGM) caused a 30&#8211;60% decrease in labile nutrients within the thermocline layer. Using foraminiferal Ba/Ca as a proxy of refractory nutrients, increased ventilation during the LGM produced a depletion of less than 20% compared to Holocene values. Following glaciation, the production of Glacial North Atlantic Intermediate Water (GNAIW) shut down owing to the presence of meltwater in the surface ocean, which resulted in a decrease in ventilation, as seen by an enrichment of barium in the basal thermocline. GNAIW was subsequently replaced by barium-rich southern component water in the middepth western North Atlantic. Foraminiferal Ba/Ca data suggest a 38% contribution from southern component water to a depth as shallow as 1475 m and a 14% contribution at 1123 m during deglaciation.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>0097JPC, 0100GGC, Bahamas, Cibicides wuellerstorfi, Barium/Calcium ratio, DEPTH, sediment/rock, Elevation of event, Event label, GC, Gravity corer, JPC, Jumbo Piston Core, Latitude of event, Longitude of event, OC205-02, OC205-02_0007JPC, OC205-02_0097JPC, OC205-02_0100GGC, OC205-02_0117JPC, Oceanus, Oceanus205-02, Orbulina universa, Barium/Calcium ratio, PC, Piston corer, Providence Channel</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2004-11-03</date></data>