<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.311139</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Range table from diatoms in ODP Hole 145-884B</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description /><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>145-884B, Abundance estimate, Actinocyclus ingens, Actinocyclus ingens var. nodus, Actinocyclus octonarius, Actinocyclus sp., Actinocyclus tsugaruensis, Actinoptychus senarius, Asteromphalus aff. oligocenicus, Asteromphalus aff. robustus-symmetricus, Asteromphalus cf. darwinii, Azpeitia aff. praenodulifera, Azpeitia biradiata, Azpeitia oligocenica, Azpeitia praenodulifera, Azpeitia salisburyana, Azpeitia tabularis, Cavitatus exiguus, Cavitatus jouseanus, Cavitatus lanceolatus, Cavitatus linearis, Cavitatus miocenicus, Cavitatus rectus, Cestodiscus kugleri, Cestodiscus trochus, Chaetoceros, resting spores, Comment, Coscinodiscus lewisianus, Coscinodiscus lewisianus var. levis, Coscinodiscus marginatus, Coscinodiscus rhombicus, Crucidenticula ikebei, Crucidenticula kanayae, Crucidenticula sawamurae, Cymatosira aff. lorenziana, Denticulopsis hyalina, Denticulopsis lauta, Denticulopsis praelauta, Depth, composite, DEPTH, sediment/rock, Diatom abundance, Diatom preservation, Diatoms, benthic, DRILL, Drilling/drill rig, Goniothecium decoratum, Goniothecium odontella, Hemiaulus cf. incisus, Hemiaulus sp., Ikebea tenuis, Joides Resolution, Kisseleviella carina, Kisseleviella ezoensis, Kisselviella magnaareolata, Kozloviella minor, Leg145, Lisitzinia ornata, Lisitzinia ornata forma pentagona, Mediaria splendida, Melosira architecturalis, Nitzschia aff. challengeri, Nitzschia challengeri, Nitzschia maleinterpretaria, North Pacific Ocean, Ocean Drilling Program, ODP, ODP sample designation, Paralia sulcata, Pseudodimerogramma elegans, Pseudotriceratium radiosoreticulatum, Pyxilla spp., Raphidodiscus marylandicus, Rhizosolenia hotaense, Rhizosolenia norwegica, Rocella gelida, Rocella gelida var. schraderi, Rocella praenitida, Rocella semigelida, Rocella vigilans, Rouxia cf. granda, Rouxia isopolica, Rouxia naviculoides, Rouxia obesa, Sample code/label, Sceptroneis tenue, Simonseniella interposita, Simonseniella praebarboi, Spores, Stellarima spp., Thalassionema nitzschioides, Thalassionema nitzschioides var. parva, Thalassiosira dubiosa, Thalassiosira fraga, Thalassiosira irregulata, Thalassiosira lusca, Thalassiosira mediaconvexa, Thalassiosira praefraga, Thalassiothrix longissima, Yoshidaia divergens</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2005-07-07</date></data>