<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.682249</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>(Table 3) Relative abundance of benthic foraminifera in late Cenozoic sediments of DSDP Hole 68-502A from the Caribbean Sea</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description /><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>68-502A, Alabamina polita, Allomorphina pacifica, Amphicoryna bradii, Anomalinoides cf. alazaensis, Anomalinoides globulosus, Astrononion guadalupae, Bathysiphon spp., Bolivina decussata, Bolivina scabrata, Bolivina semiperforata, Bolivina striatula, Bolivina tongi filacostata, Bulimina aculeata, Bulimina cf. acanthia, Bulimina mexicana, Bulimina rostrata, Caribbean Sea/RIDGE, Cassidulina depressa, Cassidulina laevigata, Cassidulina laevigata carinata, Cassidulina minuta, Cassidulina oblonga, Cassidulinoides tenuis, Ceratobulimina sp., Chilostomella oolina, Chrysalogonium elongatum, Chrysalogonium lanceolum, Chrysalogonium longicostatum, Cibicides deprimus, Cibicides hemingwayae, Cibicides io, Cibicides lobatulus, Cibicides mckannai, Cibicides spiralis, Cibicides umbonatus, Cibicidoides bradyi, Cibicidoides cf. grimsdalei, Cibicidoides cf. robertsonianus, Cibicidoides kullenbergi, Cibicidoides robertsonianus, Cibicidoides spp., Cibicidoides wuellerstorfi, Cyclammina cancellata, Cyclogyra sp., Deep Sea Drilling Project, Dentalina advena, Dentalina communis, Dentalina consobrina, Dentalina intorta, Dentalina pauperata, Dentalina soluta, Dentalina spp., DEPTH, sediment/rock, DRILL, Drilling/drill rig, DSDP, Eggerella bradyi, Ehrenbergina bradyi, Ellipsoglandulina principiens, Ellipsoidina abbreviata, Elphidium spp., Epistominella bradyana, Epistominella exigua, Epistominella sp., Epistominella umbonifera, Eponides regularis, Fissurina aff. F. orbignyana, Fissurina alveolata, Fissurina auricolata, Fissurina bodjonegoroensis, Fissurina carteri, Fissurina cf. cucullata, Fissurina cf. trigonomarginata, Fissurina cf. wiesneri, Fissurina clathrata, Fissurina cucullata, Fissurina dominicana, Fissurina exsculpta, Fissurina fimbriata, Fissurina marginata, Fissurina orbignyana, Fissurina semimarginata, Fissurina semisculpta, Fissurina solida, Fissurina spinosa, Fissurina spp., Fissurina staphylleraria, Fissurina subformosa, Fissurina wiesneri, Foraminifera, benthic, Francesita advena, Fursenkoina bramletti, Fursenkoina rotundata, Fursenkoina seminuda, Globocassidulina ornata, Globocassidulina subglobosa, Glomar Challenger, Glomospira charoides, Guttulina caudata, Guttulina sp., Guttulina spp., Gyroidina altiformis, Gyroidina broeckhiana, Gyroidina cf. G. soldanii, Gyroidina condoni, Gyroidina io, Gyroidina lamarckiana, Gyroidina nitidula, Gyroidina planulata, Gyroidina soldanii, Gyroidina spp., Gyroidina umbonata, Hanzawaia sp., Hoeglundina elegans, Karreriella baccata, Karreriella bradyi, Karreriella brevis, Lagena advena, Lagena advena cf. L. striata, Lagena aff. L. laevis, Lagena aspera, Lagena cf. L. laevis, Lagena costata, Lagena crenulata capistriata, Lagena feildeniana, Lagena flatulenta, Lagena gracilis, Lagena gracillima, Lagena hexagona, Lagena hispida, Lagena plumigera, Lagena setigera, Lagena spp., Laticarinina pauperata, Leg68, Lenticulina crassa, Lenticulina cushmanii, Lenticulina spp., Marginulina asperuliformis, Marginulina exima, Marginulina planata, Marginulina subbullata, Marginulina sublituus, Marginulina subrecta, Martinottiella pallida, Martinottiella patens, Melonis affinis, Melonis pompilioides, Melonis soldanii, Melonis sp., Miliolinella irregularis, Nodogenerina challengeriana, Nodogenerina laevigata, Nodosarella robusta, Nodosarella salmojraghii, Nodosaria cf. N. vertebralis, Nodosaria fistuca, Nodosaria flintii, Nodosaria hispida, Nodosaria lamellata, Nodosaria longiscata, Nodosaria pyrula, Nodosaria vertebralis, Nonionella sp., Nonionella stella, Nonion havanense, Number of species, ODP sample designation, Oolina caudigera, Oolina desmophora, Oolina globulosa, Oolina ovum, Oolina sp., Ophthalmidium inconstans, Oridorsalis cf. umbonatus, Oridorsalis multiseptus, Oridorsalis umbonatus, Orthomorphina rohri, Osangularia culter, Parafissurina cf. Lagena fistulifera, Parafissurina lateralis carinata, Parafissurina pseudomarginata, Parafissurina sp., Parafissurina spp., Parafissurina tectulostoma, Planulina sp., Plectina apicularis, Plectofrondicularia advena, Plectofrondicularia vaughani, Pleurostomella acuminata, Pleurostomella acuta, Pleurostomella alternans, Pleurostomella bierigi, Pleurostomella brevis, Pleurostomella cf. P. alternans, Pleurostomella praegerontica, Pleurostomella spp., Pleurostomella subglobosa, Praeglobobulimina affinis, Praeglobobulimina auriculata, Praeglobobulimina pupoides, Pseudoglandulina sp., Pullenia alazaensis, Pullenia angusta, Pullenia bulloides, Pullenia cf. alazaensis, Pullenia quadriloba, Pullenia quinqueloba, Pullenia salisburyi, Pullenia spp., Pyrgo aff. P. rotalaria, Pyrgo anomala, Pyrgo cf. P. lucernula, Pyrgo cf. P. murrhina, Pyrgo cf. P. rotalaria, Pyrgo depressa, Pyrgo lucernula, Pyrgo murrhina, Pyrgo rotalaria, Pyrgo serrata, Pyrgo spp., Pyrgo williamsoni, Pyrulina albatrossi, Pyrulina cylindroides, Pyrulina cylindroides curvatura, Quinqueloculina auberiana, Quinqueloculina cf. seminuda, Quinqueloculina lamarckiana, Quinqueloculina seminula, Quinqueloculina spp., Quinqueloculina venusta, Robertinoides sp., Rosalina columbiensis, Sample code/label, Saracenaria acutauricularis, Sigmoilina schlumbergeri, Sigmoilina sp., Sigmoilina tenuis, Siphonodosaria abyssorum, Siphonodosaria paucistriata, Siphonodosaria verneuili, Siphotextularia catenata, Sphaeroidina bulloides, Spiroloculina robusta, Stilostomella advena, Stilostomella lepidula, Stilostomella sp., Stilostomella subspinosa, Textularia agglutinans, Triloculina trihedra, Uvigerina cf. hispidicostata, Uvigerina hispida, Uvigerina hispidocostata, Uvigerina peregrina, Uvigerina rustica, Uvigerina senticosa, Uvigerina striata, Valvulineria araucana, Valvulineria glabra, Valvulineria mexicana, Valvulineria minuta, Valvulineria sp., Vulvulina spinosa</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>1996-02-13</date></data>