<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.833716</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Acid-base regulation in the Dungeness crab (Metacarcinus magister)</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Homeostatic regulation allows organisms to secure basic physiological processes in a varying environment. To counteract fluctuations in ambient carbonate system speciation due to elevated seawater pCO2 (hypercapnia), many aquatic crustaceans excrete/accumulate acid-base equivalents through their gills, however, not much is known about the role of ammonia in this response. The present study investigated the effects of hypercapnia on acid-base and ammonia regulation in the Dungeness crab, Metacarcinus magister on the whole animal and isolated gill levels. Hemolymph pCO2 and [HCO3]- increased in M. magister acclimated to elevated pCO2 (330 Pa), while pH remained stable. Additionally, hemolymph [Na+], [Ca2+], and [SO4]2- were significantly increased. When challenged with varying pH during gill perfusion, the pH of the artificial hemolymph remained relatively unchanged. Overall, ammonia production and excretion, as well as oxygen consumption, were reduced in crabs acclimated to elevated pCO2, demonstrating that either (amino acid) oxidation is reduced in response to this particular stress, or nitrogenous wastes are excreted in an alternative form.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Acid-base regulation, Alkalinity, total, Alkalinity, total, standard error, Ammonia+Ammonium, Ammonia excretion, Animalia, Aragonite saturation state, Arthropoda, Benthic animals, Benthos, Bicarbonate ion, Bicarbonate ion, standard error, Bicarbonate ion increase rate, Calcite saturation state, Calcium ion, Calculated using CO2SYS, Calculated using seacarb after Nisumaa et al. (2010), Carbon, inorganic, dissolved, Carbon, inorganic, dissolved, standard error, Carbonate ion, Carbonate system computation flag, Carbon dioxide, Chloride ion, Coast and continental shelf, Containers and aquaria (20- 1000 L or &lt; 1 m**2), Coulometric titration, Figure, Fugacity of carbon dioxide (water) at sea surface temperature (wet air), Haemolymph, bicarbonate ion, Haemolymph, partial pressure of carbon dioxide, Haemolymph, pH, Hemocyanin, Identification, Laboratory experiment, Magnesium ion, Metacarcinus magister, Not applicable, OA-ICC, Ocean Acidification International Coordination Centre, Osmolality, Other metabolic rates, Partial pressure of carbon dioxide (water) at sea surface temperature (wet air), Partial pressure of carbon dioxide (water) at sea surface temperature (wet air), standard error, pH, pH, standard error, Potassium ion, Potentiometric, Replicates, Respiration, Respiration rate, oxygen, Salinity, Sample code/label, Single species, Sodium ion, Species, Sulfate ion, Table, Temperate, Temperature, water, Time point, descriptive, Treatment</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2014-07-01</date></data>