<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.875890</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Seawater carbonate chemistry and larval length, respiration and survival of sea urchin Loxechinus albus across</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Phenotypic plasticity is expected to play a major adaptive role in the response of species to ocean acidification (OA), by providing broader tolerances to changes in pCO2 conditions. However, tolerances and sensitivities to future OA may differ among populations within a species because of their particular environmental context and genetic backgrounds. Here, using the climatic variability hypothesis (CVH), we explored this conceptual framework in populations of the sea urchin Loxechinus albus across natural fluctuating pCO2/pH environments. Although elevated pCO2 affected the morphology, physiology, development and survival of sea urchin larvae, the magnitude of these effects differed among populations. These differences were consistent with the predictions of the CVH showing greater tolerance to OA in populations experiencing greater local variation in seawater pCO2/pH. Considering geographical differences in plasticity, tolerances and sensitivities to increased pCO2 will provide more accurate predictions for species responses to future OA.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Alkalinity, total, Alkalinity, total, standard error, Animalia, Aragonite saturation state, Aragonite saturation state, standard error, Bicarbonate ion, Bottles or small containers/Aquaria ( 20 L), Calcite saturation state, Calcite saturation state, standard error, Calculated using CO2calc, Calculated using seacarb after Nisumaa et al. (2010), Carbon, inorganic, dissolved, Carbonate ion, Carbonate system computation flag, Carbon dioxide, Coast and continental shelf, Development, Echinodermata, Experiment duration, Fugacity of carbon dioxide (water) at sea surface temperature (wet air), Growth/Morphology, Identification, Laboratory experiment, Larvae lam, length, Length, Location, Loxechinus albus, Mortality/Survival, OA-ICC, Ocean Acidification International Coordination Centre, Partial pressure of carbon dioxide (water) at sea surface temperature (wet air), Partial pressure of carbon dioxide (water) at sea surface temperature (wet air), standard error, Pelagos, Percentage, pH, pH, standard error, Potentiometric, Potentiometric titration, Registration number of species, Respiration, Respiration rate, oxygen, per individual, Salinity, Salinity, standard error, Single species, Site, South Pacific, Species, Survival, Temperate, Temperature, water, Temperature, water, standard error, Treatment, Tropical, Type, Uniform resource locator/link to reference, Zooplankton</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2017-06-05</date></data>