<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.880379</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Seawater carbonate chemistry and survival, larval development, shell growth and normal shell development of great scallop (Pecten maximus Lamarck)</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>The increasing amount of dissolved anthropogenic CO2 has caused a drop in pH values in the open ocean known as ocean acidification. This change in seawater carbonate chemistry has been shown to have a negative effect on a number of marine organisms. Early life stages are the most vulnerable, and especially the organisms that produce calcified structures in the phylum Mollusca. Few studies have looked at effects on scallops, and this is the first study presented including fed larvae of the great scallop (Pecten maximus) followed until day 14 post-fertilization. Fertilized eggs from unexposed parents were exposed to three levels of pCO2 using four replicate units: 465 (ambient), 768 and 1294 &#181;atm, corresponding to pHNIST of 7.94, 7.75 (-0.19 units) and 7.54 (-0.40 units), respectively. All of the observed parameters were negatively affected by elevated pCO2: survival, larval development, shell growth and normal shell development. The latter was observed to be affected only 2 days after fertilization. Negative effects on the fed larvae at day 7 were similar to what was shown earlier for unfed P. maximus larvae. Growth rate in the group at 768?&#181;atm seemed to decline after day 7, indicating that the ability to overcome the environmental change at moderately elevated pCO2 was lost over time. The present study shows that food availability does not decrease the sensitivity to elevated pCO2 in P. maximus larvae. Unless genetic adaptation and acclimatization counteract the negative effects of long term elevated pCO2, recruitment in populations of P. maximus will most likely be negatively affected by the projected drop of 0.06-0.32 units in pH within year 2100.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Alkalinity, total, Animalia, Aragonite saturation state, Benthic animals, Benthos, Bicarbonate ion, Calcite saturation state, Calculated using CO2SYS, Calculated using seacarb after Nisumaa et al. (2010), Carbon, inorganic, dissolved, Carbonate ion, Carbonate system computation flag, Carbon dioxide, Coast and continental shelf, Containers and aquaria (20- 1000 L or &lt; 1 m**2), Development, Experiment duration, Fugacity of carbon dioxide (water) at sea surface temperature (wet air), Growth/Morphology, Identification, Laboratory experiment, Larvae, Mollusca, Mortality/Survival, North Atlantic, OA-ICC, Ocean Acidification International Coordination Centre, Partial pressure of carbon dioxide (water) at sea surface temperature (wet air), Pecten maximus, pH, Potentiometric, Potentiometric titration, Registration number of species, Replicates, Salinity, Shell length, Shell length, standard deviation, Single species, Species, Survival, Temperate, Temperature, water, Time in days, Type, Uniform resource locator/link to reference</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2017-09-07</date></data>