<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.54324</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Pollen analysis of sediment profile HAE16 from H&#228;melsee</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description /><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Acer, Acroperus harpae, Alnus, Alona affinis, Alona sp., Alonella nana, Apiaceae apioide-type, Artemisia, Betula, Bosmina longirostris-group, Bosmina sp., Botrychium, Botryococcus, Brachionus cf. urceolaris, Calluna, Camptocercus rectirostris, Caryophyllaceae, Ceratophyllum: spines, Changes in the Geo-Biosphere during the last 15000 years, Chaoborus flavicans, Characeae egg fragment, Chenopodiaceae, Circaea, Cladocera, nonplanktic, Cladocera, planktic, Conochilus hippocrepis, Conochilus natans, Conochilus unicornis, Corylus, Cosmarium sp., Counting, palynology, Cyanophyceae, Cyperaceae, Daphnidae mandibles and claws, DEPTH, sediment/rock, Desmidiales, Dryopteris, Empetrum, Epilobium, Equisetum, Ericales, Euastrum sp., Eurycercus lamellatus, Fagus, Filinia longiseta passa/Filinia hofmanni, Filipendula, Frangula alnus, Fraxinus, GeoBio15k, Gramineae, Graptoleberis testudinaria, HAE16, H&#228;melsee, Hedera, Helianthemum cf. H. canum, Hexarthra mira, Isoetes, Jasione, Juniperus, Keratella quadrata, LakeSedNLfB, Lamiaceae, Liguliflorae, Monospilus dispar, Myriophyllum spicatum, Nymphaea, Nymphaeaceae: trichome, Ostracoda mandible, PC_SM, Pediastrum boryanum, Pediastrum boryanum rugulatum, Pediastrum duplex, Pediastrum integrum, Pediastrum kawraiskyi, Picea, Pinus, Pinus: stomata, Piston corer Streif/Merkt, Plantago major/media, Pleuroxus sp., Polygonum amphibium, Polypodiaceae, Populus, Potamogeton, Potentilla-type, Pteridium, Quercus, Ranunculus subgen. Batrachium-type, Rosaceae, other, Rotatoria, other, Rotatoria, resting eggs, Rubiaceae cf. galium, Rubus chamaemorus, Rumex, Salix, Sampling/drilling in lake, Sanguisorba officinalis, Saxifragaceae, Scenedesmus quadricauda, Sida crystallina, Sparganium-type, Sphagnum, Sphagnum sp., leaves, Staurastrum cf. gracilis, Staurophrya elegans, Thalictrum, Thelypteris palustris, Tilia, Tubuliflorae other, Turbellaria Rhabdocoela eggs, Typha latifolia, Ulmus, Urtica, Vaccinium, Varia, Viscum, Zygnemales</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2001-08-11</date></data>