<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.704588</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Phytoplankton abundance and species composition in the Gulf of Naples in June 1999 at station MCSSII-phyto129-136</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description /><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Acanthoica quattrospina, Alexandrium minutum, Alexandrium spp., Algirosphaera robusta, Bacteriastrum parallelum, Bottle, Niskin, Calciopappus caudatus, Calciosolenia brasiliensis, Calculated, Cerataulina pelagica, Ceratium fusus, Ceratoneis closterium, Chaetoceros cf. muelleri, Chaetoceros curvisetus, Chaetoceros decipiens, Chaetoceros minimus, Chaetoceros muelleri, Chaetoceros simplex, Chaetoceros socialis, Chaetoceros spp., Chaetoceros tenuissimus, Chaetoceros throndsenii, Chrysochromulina spp., Chrysophyceae, Coccoids, Coccolithophoridae indeterminata, Cochlodinium spp., Coronosphaera mediterranea, Cryptophyceae indeterminata, Cyclotella atomus, Cyclotella cf. striata, Dactyliosolen blavyanus, Dactyliosolen fragilissimus, Depth, bottom/max, Depth, top/min, DEPTH, water, Diatoms, centrales, Diatoms, pennales, Dictyocha fibula, Dinobryon faculiferum, Dinoflagellates, Dinoflagellates, naked, Dinoflagellates, thecate, Diplostauron cf. elegans, Emiliania huxleyi, Euglenophycea indeterminata, Flagellates, heterotrophic, Flagellates indeterminata, Gulf of Naples, Gymnodinium spp., Gyrodinium cf. pingue, Gyrodinium spp., Helicosphaera carteri, Heterocapsa niei, Integrated long-term monitoring of the planktonic system in the coastal area, Inverted microscopy, Leptocylindrus danicus, Leptocylindrus mediterraneus, Lessardia elongata, Leucocryptos marina, Lithodesmium cf. variabile, MARECHIARA, Marechiara394-MCSSII, MCSSII-phyto129-136, Meringosphaera mediterranea, Meringosphaera setifera, Minidiscus comicus, NIS, Ollicola vangoorii, Ophiaster spp., Oxytoxum caudatum, Oxytoxum cf. longum, Oxytoxum crassum, Oxytoxum spp., Oxytoxum variabile, Pachysphaera cf. pelagica, Pachysphaera spp., Papposphaera lepida, Paulinella ovalis, Pentapharsodinium tyrrhenicum, Peridinioid, Phytoflagellate indeterminata, Phytoplankton, Pronoctiluca spp., Prorocentrum minimum, Prorocentrum spp., Prorocentrum triestinum, Protoperidinium bipes, Protoperidinium spp., Pseudo-nitzschia delicatissima, Pseudo-nitzschia galaxiae, Pseudo-nitzschia pseudodelicatissima, Pseudo-nitzschia spp., Pseudoscourfieldia marina, Pyramimonas spp., Pyrocystis lunula, Pyrophacus spp., Rhabdosphaera clavigera, Rhizomonas setigera, Sample volume, Scrippsiella ramonii, Skeletonema menzelii, Skeletonema pseudocostatum, Sphaerocalyptra quadridentata, Syracosphaera molischii, Syracosphaera pulchra, Telonema subtile, Tetraselmis spp., Tetraselmis wettsteinii, Thalassionema bacillare, Thalassionema nitzschioides, Thalassiosira spp., Torodinium robustum, Umbellosphaera spp., Vettoria</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2008-09-19</date></data>