<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.776241</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Composition of recent carbonate bottom sediments from the Guiana shelf an off the West Africa</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>This work was based on a study of the upper layer of recent carbonate bottom sediments of the Atlantic Ocean. Biogenic carbonate of recent sediments is represented by metastable and stable minerals. In the ocean metastable phases can exist indefinitely long, but the structure of polymorphism determines inevitability of transformation of metastable phases into stable ones. This transformation occurs in the solid phase. In the absence of a critical point between the two phases of the transition process is not available for study by microscopic methods. It is estimated indirectly by studying the nature and extent of changes in mineral and chemical compositions. With aging of sediments their mineral composition alters in direction of increasing contents of resistant minerals. Fine grained sediments and fractions are subject to more intensive effects of early diagenesis processes, rather than coarse ones, this is reflected in their mineral composition. Regularities of distribution of carbonate minerals in size fractions consistent with the direction of polymorphic transformations in calcium carbonate. Such transformations can occur in a particular dimension of grains. Concrete grain size depends on environmental conditions. This situation explains presence of metastable biogenic carbonates at different depths of the ocean and suggests presence of diagenetic calcite in sediments occurring below expected for each case depth of the transition.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>AK3-144, AK3-210, AK3-99, Akademik Kurchatov, AKU3, AN9086-8, AN9086-8-469, Archive of Ocean Data, ARCOD, AtlantNIRO-SRTR-9086, Bel2, Bel2-1, Bel2-12, Bel2-13, Bel2-18, Bel2-19, Bel2-2, Bel2-36, Bel2-4, Bel2-49, Bel2-52, Bel2-54, Bel2-69, Bel2-75, Bel2-8, Belogorsk, Grab, GRAB</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>1975-02-20</date></data>