<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.894110</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Pollen profile of sediment core OTTRAT, R&#229;t&#229;sj&#248;en, Norway</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description /><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Acer, Aconitum septentrionale, AGE, Alchemilla, Alnus, Angelica-type, Arenaria-type, Artemisia, Artemisia cf. A. norvegica, Astragalus cf. A. alpinus, Athyrium distentifolium-type, Athyrium filix-femina, Betula, Betula/Corylus/Myrica, Blechnum spicant, Botryococcus, Capsella-type, Carduus/Cirsium, Carex-type, Caryophyllaceae undifferentiated, cf. Oxytropis, cf. Sorbus aucuparia, Charcoal, Chenopodiaceae, Cichorioideae, Corylus avellana, Counting, palynology, Cryptogramma crispa, Cyperaceae undifferentiated, DEPTH, sediment/rock, Diphasiastrum, Dryas octopetala, Dryopteris carthusiana-type, Dryopteris filix-mas-type, Dryopteris-type, Empetrum nigrum, EPD, Epilobium, Equisetum, Ericaceae-type, Eriophorum-type, Eucalyptus, Eucalyptus grains per tablet, Eucalyptus tablets, Filipendula, Fraxinus excelsior, Geranium sylvaticum-type, Gramineae undifferentiated, Gymnocarpium dryopteris, Hippophae rhamnoides, Huperzia selago, Indeterminable: broken, Indeterminable: concealed, Indeterminable: corroded, Indeterminable: crumpled, Indeterminable: degraded, Indeterminable: unknown, Juncaceae, Juniperus communis, Livingstone piston corer, Lotus cf. L. corniculatus, LPC, Lycopodium annotinum, Melampyrum, Norway, OTTRAT, Oxyria digyna, Parnassia palustris, Pediastrum, Picea abies, Pimpinella saxifraga, Pinus: stomata, Pinus sylvestris, Plantago lanceolata, Polygonum bistorta/P. viviparum, Populus tremula, Potamogeton sect. Eupotamogeton, Potentilla-type, Pteridium aquilinum, Quercus, Ranunculus acris-type, R&#229;t&#229;sj&#248;en, Rhinanthus-type, Rosaceae undifferentiated, Rubiaceae, Rumex acetosa, Rumex acetosa/R. acetosella-type, Rumex acetosella-type, Sagina, Salix herbacea-type, Salix undifferentiated, Sample volume, Saussurea alpina, Saxifraga cernua-type, Saxifraga cespitosa-type, Saxifraga oppositifolia-type, Saxifraga stellaris-type, Sedum, Selaginella selaginoides, Silene vulgaris-type, Sinapis-type, Solidago-type, Sparganium emersum-type, Sphagnum, Stachys-type, Thalictrum, Tilia cordata, Ulmus, Umbelliferae undifferentiated, Urtica, Vaccinium-type, Valeriana sambucifolia-type, Veronica-type, Viburnum opulus</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2018-09-14</date></data>