<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.878022</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>(Table S2) Concentration of the individual and summed BHPs of the suspended particulate matter</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description /><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Adenosylhopane per unit mass particulate organic carbon, Aminopentol per unit mass particulate organic carbon, Aminotetrol per unit mass particulate organic carbon, Aminotriol per unit mass particulate organic carbon, Anhydro-bacteriohopanetetrol per unit mass particulate organic carbon, Bacteriohopanehexol cyclitol ether per unit mass particulate organic carbon, Bacteriohopanehexol per unit mass particulate organic carbon, Bacteriohopanepentol cyclitol ether per unit mass particulate organic carbon, Bacteriohopanepolyols per unit mass particulate organic carbon, Bacteriohopanetetrol cyclitol ether unit mass particulate organic carbon, Bacteriohopanetetrol per unit mass particulate organic carbon, BHT-pseudopentose per unit mass particulate organic carbon, DEPTH, water, Event label, Kara Sea, Khalmyer Bay, Siberia, Russia, Meth. Adenosylhopane per unit mass particulate organic carbon, Meth. Bacteriohopanetetrol, Meth. BHT-pseudopentose per unit mass particulate organic carbon, Meth. Soil Group 2 BHP per unit mass particulate organic carbon, Meth. Soil Group 3 BHP per unit mass particulate organic carbon, Mountain River, Siberia, Russia, MULT, Multiple investigations, NIOZ_UU, NIOZ Royal Netherlands Institute for Sea Research, and Utrecht University, Ob outflow, Siberia, Russia, Ratio, Siberia_KB1, Siberia_KB2, Siberia_KB3, Siberia_KB4, Siberia_KG1, Siberia_KG2, Siberia_KS1, Siberia_KS2, Siberia_KS3, Siberia_KS4, Siberia_MR1, Siberia_MR2, Siberia_OO1, Siberia_OO2, Siberia_SR1, Siberia_YG1, Siberia_YG2a, Siberia_YG2b, Siberia_YG3, Siberia_YG4, Siberia_YG5, Siberia_YG6, Siberia_YG7, Siberia_YG8, Siberia_YG9, Siberia_YM1, Siberia_YM2, Siberia_YM3, Siberia_YM4, Siberia_YM5, Siberia_YO1, Siberia_YR1, Siberia_YR2, Siberia_YR3, Siberia_YR4, Siberia_YR5, Siberia_YR6, Siberia_YR7, Siberia_YR8, Siberia_YR9, Soil Group 2 BHP per unit mass particulate organic carbon, Soil Group 3 BHP per unit mass particulate organic carbon, Unsat. Aminotriol per unit mass particulate organic carbon, Unsat. BHT-pseudopentose per unit mass particulate organic carbon, Unsaturated Bacteriohopanetetrol per unit mass particulate organic carbon, Yenisei, Siberia, Russia, Yenisei Gulf, Siberia, Russia, Yenisei Outflow, Siberia, Russia, Yenisei River Mouth, Siberia, Russia</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2016-07-20</date></data>