<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.870538</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Recent surface sediment samples of ostracoda and foraminifera (&gt;200&#181;m), South Africa</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description /><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Aglaiella railbridgensis, Aglaiella westfordensis, Aglaiocypris sp., Ambostracon flabellicostata, Ammobaculites sp., Ammodiscus sp., Ammonia japonica, Ammonia parkinsoniana, Ammonia tepida, Ammotium salsum, Astacolus sp., Aurila dayii, Aurila kliei, Australoecia sp., Australoloxoconcha favornamentata, Austroaurila rugosa, Bairdiinae, Bairdoppilata sp., Basslerites (Loculiconcha), Bolangvlei, Bolivina striatula, Bollard Bey Beach, Leisure Isle, Bonnyannella sp., Bulimina elongata, Bulimina gibba, Bulimina sp., Bythocythere sp., Cancris auriculus, Candona sp., Caudites tankardi, Chrissia hodgsoni, Cibicides praecinctus, Cibicides refulgens, Coney Glenn Beach, Connemarella rudis, Cornuspira planorbis, Counting, Cribroelphidium articulatum, Cribroelphidium reticulosum, Cymbaloporella sp., Cyprideis remanei, Cytherella namibensis, Cytherelloidea compuncta, Cytheridae, Cytheromorpha milleri, Cytherura cf. siesseri, DEPTH, sediment/rock, Discorbinella sp., Eilandvlei, Elevation of event, Elphidium crispum, Elphidium macellum, Elphidium spp., Entzia macrescens, Eponides repandus, Eucythere sp., Event label, Exsculptina discrepans, Falklandia, Falsagglutinella sp., Favulina cf. hexagona, Favulina melosquamosa, Gavelinopsis sp., Globigerina cf. bulloides, Globigerina sp., Globigerininae, Globigerinoides ruber, Glomospira gordialis, Gomphocythere capensis, Goukamma, Grinioneis sp., Groenvlei, Guttulina communis, Haplophragmoides canariensis, Haplophragmoides cf. wilberti, Haplophragmoides sp., Haynesina cf. depressula, Helenina anderseni, Hemicythere sp., Hemicytherura petheri, Kaaimansgat, Kaimaansgat mouth, Kangarina sola, Knysna, Knysna, King Fisher Creek, Knysna, Leisure Island, Knysna Heads, Krithe sp., Lagena cf. semilineata, Lagena sp., Lagena sulcata, Latitude of event, Leisure &amp; Thesen Island, Leisure Island, Lenticulina sp., Leptocythere hartmanni, Limnocythere stationis, Lobatula lobatula, Longitude of event, Loxoconcha megapora, Loxoconcha parameridionalis, Mediocytherideis (Sylvestra) ochracea, Melonis affinis, Meridionalicythere petricola, Microcytherura sp., Miliammina earlandi, Miliammina fusca, Mutilus bensonmaddocksorum, Myodocopa, Neocaudites osseus, Neocytherideis boomeri, Neonesidea villosa, Neorotalia calcar, Number of individuals, Oolina ampulladistoma, Ostracoda, Palmoconcha peterseni, Palmoconcha sp., Paracypris sp., Paradoxostoma griseum, Paradoxostoma luederitzense, Paradoxostoma wuenschei, Paranesidea verlorevleiensis, Pararotalia nipponica, Perissocytheridea estuaria, Physocypria capensis, Pileolina sp., Pileolina zealandica, Planoglabratella australensis, Planoglabratella sp., Planorbulina mediterranensis, Pontocypris sp., Pontocythere sp., Propontocypris sp., Propontocypris subreniformis, Pullenia bikiniensis, Pyrgo sarsi, Quadracythere sp., Quinqueloculina spp., RAiN, Regional Archives for Integrated iNvestigations, Rondevlei, Rosalina bradyi, Rotaliida, Ruigtevlei, Sample volume, Sarscypridopsis aculeata, Sarscypridopsis sp., Sclerochilus incurvatus, Semicytherura cf. mucronata, Serpentine Bridge, Siphonaperta subagglutinata, Spirillina denticulata, Spiroloculina cf. antillarum, Spiroloculina henbesti, Spiroloculina spp., Split, Strobilocythere (Keniacythere) knysnaensis, Strobilocythere (Keniacythere) malzi, Sulcostocythere knysnaensis, Swartvlei, Swartvlei estuary, Taxa analyzed, Textularia pseudogramen, Textularia sp., Thesen Island, Touwsriver Eden adventure Kanoe, Touwsriver estuary, Touwsriver Railway Bridge, Triloculina cf. tricarinata, Triloculina oblonga, Triloculina spp., Trochammina inflata, Trochamminita irregularis, Urocythereis sp., Valvulineria sp., Xestoleberis aff. crenulata, Xestoleberis baja, Xestoleberis capensis, Xestoleberis cf. ferax, Xestoleberis cf. ventricosa, Xestoleberis humilis, Xestoleberis maculata, Xestoleberis sp., ZA_13/01, ZA_13/02, ZA_13/03, ZA_13/04, ZA_13/05, ZA_13/06, ZA_13/07, ZA_13/08, ZA_13/09, ZA_13/10, ZA_13/11, ZA_13/12, ZA_13/13, ZA_13/14, ZA_13/15, ZA_13/16, ZA_13/17, ZA_13/18, ZA_13/19, ZA_13/20, ZA_13/21, ZA_13/22, ZA_13/23, ZA_13/24, ZA_13/25, ZA_13/26, ZA_13/27, ZA_13/28, ZA_13/29, ZA_13/30, ZA_13/31, ZA_13/32, ZA_13/33, ZA_13/34, ZA_13/35, ZA_13/36, ZA_13/37, ZA_13/38, ZA_13/39, ZA_13/40, ZA_13/41, ZA_13/42, ZA_13/43, ZA_13/44, ZA_13/45, ZA_13/46, ZA_13/47, ZA_13/48, ZA_13/49, ZA_13/50, ZA_13/51, ZA_13/52, ZA_13/53, ZA_13/54, ZA_13/55, ZA_13/56, ZA_13/57, ZA_13/58, ZA_13/59, ZA_13/60, ZA_13/61, ZA_13/62, ZA_13/63, ZA_13/64, ZA_13/65, ZA_13/66, ZA_13/67, ZA_13/68, ZA_13/69, ZA_13/70, ZA_14/01, ZA_14/02, ZA_14/03, ZA_14/04, ZA_14/05, ZA_14/06, ZA_14/07, ZA_14/08, ZA_14/09, ZA_14/10, ZA_14/11, ZA_14/12, ZA_14/13, ZA_14/14, ZA_14/15, ZA_14/16, ZA_14/17, ZA_14/18, Zonocypris cordata</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2017-01-09</date></data>