<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.816451</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Biomass and stable isotope composition of plankton in five size fractions along a zonal transect (24&#176;N) from the Canary Islands to Florida in January-March 2011</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>The spatial variability of biomass and stable isotopes in plankton size fractions in the upper 200 m was studied in a high spatial resolution transect along 24&#176;N from Canary Islands to Florida (January - March  2011) during Leg 8 of the Malaspina-2010 expedition (http://www.expedicionmalaspina.es) to determine nitrogen and carbon sources. Plankton samples were collected by vertical tows of a microplankton net (40 mm mesh size) and a mesoplankton net (200 mm mesh size) through the upper 200 m of the  water column. Sampling was between 10:00 and 16:00 h GMT.  Plankton was separated into  five size fractions  (40 - 200,  200 - 500,  500 - 1000,  1000 - 2000 and &gt; 2000 mm) by gentle filtration of the samples by a graded series of nylon sieves (2000, 1000, 500, 200 and 40 mm).  Large gelatinous organisms  were  removed before filtration. Aliquots for each size fraction were collected on pre-weighed glass-fibre filters, dried (60&#176;C, 48 h) and stored in a desiccator before determination of biomass (dry weight), carbon and nitrogen content and natural abundance of stable carbon and nitrogen isotopes ashore. Vertical advection of waters predominated in lateral zones while the central Atlantic (30-70&#176;W) was characterized by a strong stratification and oligotrophic surface waters. Plankton biomass was low in the central zone and high in both eastern and western sides, with most of the variability due to either large (&gt;2000 &#181;m) and small plankton (&lt;500 &#181;m). Carbon isotopes reflected mainly the advection the deep water in lateral zones. Stable nitrogen isotopes showed a nearly symmetrical spatial distribution in all fractions, with the lowest values (delta15N &lt;1per mill) in the central zone, and were inversely correlated to carbon stable isotopes (delta13C) and to the abundance of the nitrogen-fixer Trichodesmium. Diazotrophy was estimated to account for &gt;50% of organic nitrogen in the central zone, and even &gt;30% in eastern and western zones. The impact of diazotrophy increased with the size of the organisms, supporting the wide participation of all trophic levels in the processing of recently fixed nitrogen. These results indicate that atmospheric sources of carbon and nitrogen prevail over deep water sources in the subtropical North Atlantic and that the zone influenced by diazotrophy is much larger than reported in previous studies.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Basin Scale Analysis, Synthesis and Integration, Date/Time of event, Depth, bottom/max, Depth, top/min, DEPTH, water, Element analyser CHNS-O, Carlo Erba EA1108, EURO-BASIN, Event label, Latitude of event, Longitude of event, MALASPINA-2010, MALASPINA-2010 Leg 8, Malaspina circumnavigation expedition, Mass spectrometer Finnigan Delta Plus, MS-2010-8_012, MS-2010-8_016, MS-2010-8_020, MS-2010-8_024, MS-2010-8_027, MS-2010-8_030, MS-2010-8_033, MS-2010-8_037, MS-2010-8_039, MS-2010-8_040, MS-2010-8_043, MS-2010-8_045, MS-2010-8_048, MS-2010-8_052, MS-2010-8_055, MS-2010-8_059, MS-2010-8_061-1, MS-2010-8_064, MS-2010-8_068, MS-2010-8_071-1, MS-2010-8_075, MS-2010-8_078-1, MS-2010-8_082, MS-2010-8_085, MS-2010-8_088, MS-2010-8_091, MS-2010-8_094, MS-2010-8_097, MS-2010-8_100, MS-2010-8_104, MS-2010-8_107, MS-2010-8_110, MS-2010-8_113, MS-2010-8_116, MS-2010-8_120, MS-2010-8_125, MS-2010-8_128, MS-2010-8_133, MS-2010-8_137, MS-2010-8_143, MS-2010-8_149, MS-2010-8_157, MS-2010-8_161-1, PLA, Plankton, biomass as carbon, Plankton, biomass as dry weight, Plankton, biomass as nitrogen, Plankton net, Sarmiento de Gamboa, station: 012, station: 016, station: 020, station: 024, station: 027, station: 030, station: 033, station: 037, station: 039, station: 040, station: 043, station: 045, station: 048, station: 052, station: 055, station: 059, station: 061-1, station: 064, station: 068, station: 071-1, station: 075, station: 078-1, station: 082, station: 085, station: 088, station: 091, station: 094, station: 097, station: 100, station: 104, station: 107, station: 110, station: 113, station: 116, station: 120, station: 125, station: 128, station: 133, station: 137, station: 143, station: 149, station: 157, station: 161-1, Subtropical North Atlantic, Weighted, &#948;13C, plankton, &#948;15N, plankton</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2013-07-09</date></data>