<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.885392</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Soil texture from the Jena Experiment (Main Experiment, year 2002)</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>This data set contains measurements of soil texture, i. e. proportion of sand, silt and clay. Data presented here is from the Main Experiment plots of a large grassland biodiversity experiment (the Jena Experiment, see further details below). In the main experiment, 82 grassland plots of 20 x 20 m were established from a pool of 60 species belonging to four functional groups (grasses, legumes, tall and small herbs). In May 2002, varying numbers of plant species from this species pool were sown into the plots to create a gradient of plant species richness (1, 2, 4, 8, 16 and 60 species) and functional richness (1, 2, 3, 4 functional groups). Plots were maintained in general by bi-annual weeding and mowing. Since 2010, plot size was reduced to 5 x 6 m and plots were weeded three times per year.Soil texture was determined from undisturbed soil cores at 27 locations distributed throughout the experimental site before plot establishment. Two of the locations are now reference plots and thus not included in this data set. Soil cores were taken to 100 cm depth and separated in increments with a resolution of ten cm from ground level to 40 cm depth and 20 cm from 40 cm to 100 cm depth. The bulk material was passed through a sieve with 2 mm mesh size and only fine soil was used for the investigation of soil texture. Grain size fractions according to DIN 19683-2 for every sample were then determined at the laboratory for geoecology of Jena University by a combined sieve and hydrometer analysis.Values for each plot were interpolated by ordinary kriging. This data set contains both, the actually measured in may as well as the interpolated values (Date/time start:01/01/2002,Date/time end:31/12/2002).</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Date/time end, Date/time start, DEPTH, soil, Depth, soil, maximum, Depth, soil, minimum, EXP, Experiment, Experimental plot, Jena Experiment 2002, JenExp, JenExp_2002, Particle size fractions by K&#214;HN, combined sieve and hydrometer (DIN 19683-2), Size fraction &lt; 0.002 mm, &gt; 9 phi, clay, Size fraction &gt; 0.006 mm, silt, Size fraction &gt; 0.063 mm, sand, The Jena Experiment, Thuringia, Germany, Treatment: aboveground: pesticide, Treatment: below pesticide, Treatment: drought, Treatment: eartworm exclosure, Treatment: fertilizing, Treatment: molluscide, Treatment: mowing, Treatment: nematicide, Treatment: phytometers, Treatment: seed addition, Treatment: special, Treatment: weeding, Treatment: weeding history</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2018-01-22</date></data>