<data><id>oai:pangaea.de:doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.854406</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Hydrochemistry (DIC, TA and N2O) measured on water bottle samples during Maria S. Merian cruise MSM18/3</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description /><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Alkalinity, total, Bottle number, Carbon, inorganic, dissolved, CTD/Rosette, CTD1, CTD10, CTD11, CTD12, CTD13, CTD14, CTD15, CTD16, CTD17, CTD18, CTD19, CTD2, CTD20, CTD21, CTD22, CTD23, CTD24, CTD25, CTD26, CTD27, CTD28, CTD29, CTD3, CTD30, CTD31, CTD32, CTD33, CTD34, CTD35, CTD36, CTD37, CTD38, CTD39, CTD4, CTD40, CTD41, CTD42, CTD43, CTD44, CTD45, CTD46, CTD47, CTD48, CTD49, CTD5, CTD50, CTD51, CTD52, CTD53, CTD54, CTD55, CTD56, CTD57, CTD58, CTD59, CTD6, CTD60, CTD61, CTD62, CTD63, CTD64, CTD65, CTD66, CTD67, CTD68, CTD69, CTD7, CTD70, CTD71, CTD72, CTD73, CTD74, CTD75, CTD76, CTD77, CTD78, CTD79, CTD8, CTD80, CTD81, CTD82, CTD83, CTD84, CTD85, CTD86, CTD87, CTD88, CTD89, CTD9, CTD90, CTD91, CTD92, CTD93, CTD-RO, DATE/TIME, DEPTH, water, Event label, Latitude of event, Longitude of event, Maria S. Merian, MSM18/3, MSM18/3_721-1, MSM18/3_722-1, MSM18/3_723-1, MSM18/3_724-1, MSM18/3_725-1, MSM18/3_726-1, MSM18/3_727-1, MSM18/3_728-1, MSM18/3_728-3, MSM18/3_728-4, MSM18/3_729-1, MSM18/3_730-1, MSM18/3_731-1, MSM18/3_732-1, MSM18/3_733-1, MSM18/3_734-2, MSM18/3_735-10, MSM18/3_735-12, MSM18/3_735-14, MSM18/3_735-2, MSM18/3_735-4, MSM18/3_735-6, MSM18/3_735-8, MSM18/3_736-1, MSM18/3_737-1, MSM18/3_738-1, MSM18/3_739-1, MSM18/3_740-1, MSM18/3_741-1, MSM18/3_742-1, MSM18/3_743-1, MSM18/3_743-3, MSM18/3_743-4, MSM18/3_745-1, MSM18/3_746-1, MSM18/3_747-1, MSM18/3_747-3, MSM18/3_747-4, MSM18/3_748-11, MSM18/3_748-2, MSM18/3_748-5, MSM18/3_748-7, MSM18/3_748-9, MSM18/3_750-1, MSM18/3_751-1, MSM18/3_752-1, MSM18/3_753-1, MSM18/3_754-2, MSM18/3_755-2, MSM18/3_756-1, MSM18/3_756-3, MSM18/3_756-4, MSM18/3_758-10, MSM18/3_758-12, MSM18/3_758-14, MSM18/3_758-2, MSM18/3_758-4, MSM18/3_758-6, MSM18/3_758-8, MSM18/3_759-1, MSM18/3_760-1, MSM18/3_764-1, MSM18/3_765-4, MSM18/3_766-2, MSM18/3_767-1, MSM18/3_768-1, MSM18/3_768-2, MSM18/3_768-4, MSM18/3_768-5, MSM18/3_769-10, MSM18/3_769-12, MSM18/3_769-14, MSM18/3_769-2, MSM18/3_769-4, MSM18/3_769-6, MSM18/3_769-8, MSM18/3_770-1, MSM18/3_771-1, MSM18/3_772-1, MSM18/3_773-1, MSM18/3_773-2, MSM18/3_773-4, MSM18/3_774-1, MSM18/3_775-10, MSM18/3_775-12, MSM18/3_775-14, MSM18/3_775-2, MSM18/3_775-4, MSM18/3_775-6, MSM18/3_775-8, MSM18/3_776-1, MSM18/3_778-1, MSM18/3_779-1, Nitrous oxide, Nitrous oxide, standard deviation, Pressure, water, Quality flag, Salinity, Sample code/label, SOPRAN, Surface Ocean Processes in the Anthropocene, Temperature, water</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date>2015-10-27</date></data>