<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.153633</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Data from: Multimodal in situ datalogging quantifies inter-individual variation in thermal experience and persistent origin effects on gaping behavior among intertidal mussels (Mytilus californianus)</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>In complex habitats, environmental variation over small spatial scales can equal or exceed larger-scale gradients. This small-scale variation may allow motile organisms to mitigate stressful conditions by choosing benign microhabitats, whereas sessile organisms may rely on other behaviors to cope with environmental stresses in these variable environments. We developed a monitoring system to track body temperature, valve gaping behavior, and posture of individual mussels (Mytilus californianus) in field conditions in the rocky intertidal zone. Neighboring mussels' body temperatures varied by up to 14&#176;C during low tides. Valve gaping during low tide and postural adjustments, which could theoretically lower body temperature, were not commonly observed. Rather, gaping behavior followed a tidal rhythm at a warm, high intertidal site, this rhythm shifted to a circadian period at a low intertidal site and for mussels continuously submerged in a tidepool. However, individuals within a site varied considerably in time spent gaping when submerged. This behavioral variation could be attributed in part to persistent effects of mussels' developmental environment. Mussels originating from a wave-protected, warm site gaped more widely, and they remained open for longer periods during high tide than mussels from a wave-exposed, cool site. Variation in behavior was modulated further by recent wave heights and body temperatures during the preceding low tide. These large ranges in body temperatures and durations of valve closure events - which coincide with anaerobic metabolism - support the conclusion that individuals experience "homogeneous" aggregations such as mussel beds in dramatically different fashion, ultimately contributing to physiological variation among neighbors.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>biologging|bivalve|body temperature|inter-individual variation|tidal rhythm|valve gaping</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2017-08-24T15:59:50Z</date
></data>