<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.216582</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Data from: Real-world study of efficacy, risk management and reasons for discontinuation of natalizumab for treatment of multiple sclerosis in Russia</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Background. NTZ is approved in Russia for the treatment of highly active relapsing remitting multiple sclerosis and is reimbursed via federal budget program. However, no data about NTZ treatment in Russia and the effect of federal reimbursement have been performed so far. Objective. To characterize the population of patients receiving natalizumab and assess the efficacy and risk-management plan (RMP) implementation of NTZ therapy in routine clinical practice in Russia. Methods. We analyzed data for 334 patients, who received at least one infusion of NTZ. Relapse rate, MRI activity, NEDA-3 status after 2 years were assessed. Anti-JC virus antibodies status and RMP implementation were evaluated. Drop-out rate and reasons for therapy discontinuation were analyzed.  Results. Patients switched to natalizumab in Russia are mainly female (63%), with median EDSS score of 3.5 and high disease activity: 93% had at least 1 relapse and 58% had both T1Gd+ and new T2 lesion an year before therapy initiation. Introduction of federal reimbursement allowed to start therapy with natalizumab for patients with less relapses. The only predictor of 6-month progression was EDSS score at the baseline of therapy (HR=2.1375, 95%CI 1.0026 &#8211; 4.5570, p=0.0492). 82% patients reached NEDA-3 at 24 month of therapy. 25% of patients discontinued NTZ for reasons: tolerability (14.5%), JCV antibody status (61%), and patient&#8217;s decision (17%). RMP was implemented in only 36% patients.Conclusion. Natalizumab appeared to have high efficacy in Russian clinical practice. Federal reimbursement allowed less active patients to start natalizumab. More efforts should be done to improve RMP implementation.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject /><date
>2019-05-29T11:59:02Z</date
></data>