<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.162271</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Species-level database of density, body mass, speed and home range size.</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>This is a dataset compiled from bibliographic references (see Materials &amp; Methods). Essentially, it includes information of density, body mass, speed and home range size for 44 species. Name variables (in columns) are defined as follows:  &#8220;Species&#8221; (TEXT): scientific name of each species, &#8220;BM(g)&#8221; (NUMERIC): body mass in grams, &#8220;HR(Km2)&#8221; (NUMERIC): Home range size in square kilometres, &#8220;Refs(for_BM_and_HR)&#8221; (TEXT): data source for body mass and home range size data  (see Appendix S3 in Supplementary Materials for full citations), &#8220;DENSITY(ind/Km2)&#8221; (NUMERIC): animal density in number of individuals per square kilometre, &#8220;Density_survey_method&#8221; (TEXT): details of the survey method used to estimate density (if available), &#8220;Surveyed_area&#8221; (NUMERIC+TEXT): details of the surveyed area when estimating density (if available), &#8220;Study_area&#8221; (TEXT): details of the area of study when estimating density (if available), &#8220;Refs(for_Density)&#8221; (TEXT): data source for density and density-related data  (see Appendix S3 in Supplementary Materials for full citations), &#8220;SPEED(ms-1)&#8221; (NUMERIC): speed in meters per second, &#8220;Speed_survey_method&#8221; (TEXT): details of the survey method used to estimate speed (if available), &#8220;Time_step&#8221; (NUMERIC+TEXT): time step used to estimate speed (if available), &#8220;Sampling_time&#8221; (NUMERIC+TEXT): total tracking time used to estimate speed (if available), &#8220;Refs(for_Speed)&#8221; (TEXT): data source for speed and speed-related data  (see Appendix S3 in Supplementary Materials for full citations).</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>abundance|biased random walk (BRW)|counts|movement|space occupancy|speed|terrestrial and aquatic wildlife surveys|video recording</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2017-12-15T20:25:51Z</date
></data>