<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.153231</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Data from: Systematics and diversification of Anindobothrium Marques, Brooks &amp; Lasso, 2001 (Eucestoda: Rhinebothriidea)</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Tapeworms of the genus Anindobothrium Marques, Brooks &amp; Lasso, 2001 are found in both marine and Neotropical freshwater stingrays of the family Potamotrygonidae. The patterns of host association within the genus support the most recent hypothesis about the history of diversification of potamotrygonids, which suggests that the ancestor of freshwater lineages of the Potamotrygonidae colonized South American river systems through marine incursion events. Despite the relevance of the genus Anindobothrium to understand the history of colonization and diversification of potamotrygonids, no additional efforts were done to better investigate the phylogenetic relationship of this taxon with other lineages of cestodes since its erection. This study is a result of recent collecting efforts to sample members of the genus in marine and freshwater potamotrygonids that enabled the most extensive documentation of the fauna of Anindobothrium parasitizing species of Styracura de Carvalho, Loboda &amp; da Silva, Potamotrygon schroederi Fern&#225;ndez-Y&#233;pez, P. orbignyi (Castelnau) and P. yepezi Castex &amp; Castello from six different countries, representing the eastern Pacific Ocean, Caribbean Sea, and river basins in South America (Rio Negro, Orinoco, and Maracaibo). The newly collected material provided additional specimens for morphological studies and molecular samples for subsequent phylogenetic analyses that allowed us to address the phylogenetic position of Anindobothrium and provide molecular and morphological evidence to recognize two additional species for the genus. The taxonomic actions that followed our analyses included the proposition of a new family, Anindobothriidae fam. n., to accommodate the genus Anindobothrium in the order Rhinebothriidea Healy, Caira, Jensen, Webster &amp; Littlewood, 2009 and the description of two new species &#8212; one from the eastern Pacific Ocean, A. carrioni sp. n., and the other from the Caribbean Sea, A. inexpectatum sp. n. In addition, we also present a redescription of the type species of the genus, A. anacolum (Brooks, 1977) Marques, Brooks &amp; Lasso, 2001, and of A. lisae Marques, Brooks &amp; Lasso, 2001. We also discuss the paleogeographical events mostly linked with the diversification of the genus and the protocols adopted to uncover cryptic diversity in Anindobothrium.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Netropical|Cestoda|Biogeography|Molecular systematics|cryptic species</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2017-09-28T15:18:07Z</date
></data>