<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.220134</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Data from: Recent global changes have decoupled species richness from specialization patterns in North American birds</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Aim: Theory suggests that increasing productivity and climate stability towards the tropics favours specialization, thus contributing to the latitudinal richness gradient. A positive relationship between species richness and specialization should therefore emerge as a fundamental biogeographical pattern. However, land&#8208;use and climate changes disproportionally increase the local extirpation risk for specialists, potentially weakening the relationship between richness and specialization. Here, we quantify empirically the richness&#8211;specialization prediction and test how 50 years of climate and land&#8208;use change has affected the richness&#8211;specialization relationship. Location: USA. Time period: 1966&#8211;2015. Major taxa studied: Birds. Methods: We used the North American Breeding Bird Survey to quantify bird community richness and specialization to habitat and climate. We (a) quantify temporal change in the slope of the richness&#8211;specialization relationship, using a generalized mixed model, (b) assess how this change translates spatially, using generalized additive models, and (c) attribute spatio&#8208;temporal change in the richness&#8211;specialization relationship to land use, climate and topographic drivers. Results: We found evidence for a positive but weak richness&#8211;specialization relationship in bird communities that greatly weakened over time. Given that specialization was not the main driver of richness, this relationship did not translate spatially into a linear spatial covariation between richness and specialization. Instead, the spatial covariation in richness and specialization followed a unimodal pattern, the peak of which shifted towards less specialized communities over time. These temporal changes were associated with precipitation change, decreasing temperature stability and land use. Main conclusions: Recent climate and land&#8208;use changes have induced two contrasting types of community responses. In human&#8208;dominated areas, the decoupling of richness and specialization drove a general trend for biotic homogenization. In areas of low human impact experiencing increasing climate harshness, specialization increased, whereas richness decreased. Our results offer new support for specialization as a key driver of macroecological diversity patterns and show that global changes are weakening this fundamental macroecological pattern.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Birds|Biotic homogenization|Community metrics|Land use and climate changes|Latitudinal richness gradient|Latitudinal specialization gradient|Niche partitioning|Niche-breadth</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2019-08-11T18:33:59Z</date
></data>