<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.189362</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Data from: Consequences of multiple flower-insect interactions for subsequent plant-insect interactions and plant reproduction</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Premise of the study. Plants often interact simultaneously with multiple antagonists and mutualists that can alter plant traits at the phenotypic or genetic level, subsequent plant-insect interactions, and reproduction.  Although many studies have examined the effects of single floral antagonisms on subsequent pollination and plant reproduction, we know very little about the combined, potentially non-additive effects of multiple flower-insect interactions.Methods. We simulated increased florivory, nectar robbing, and pollination on field-grown Impatiens capensis.  This allowed us to determine interactive effects on five subsequent plant-insect interactions and 16 plant traits, including traits related to plant growth, floral attractiveness, floral defenses, and plant reproduction.Key results. All three manipulative treatments had significant non-additive effects on the behavior of subsequent floral visitors, indicating that the effect of floral visitors generally depended on the presence or behavior of others.  Pollination increased visitation by both pollinators and nectar larcenists (robbers and thieves), while florivory reduced pollinator and larcenist visits.  Surprisingly, supplemental pollination also increased leaf herbivory.  Florivores often responded to manipulations in opposite ways than did nectar larcenists and pollinators, suggesting different mechanisms influencing visitors that consume nectar compared to floral tissue. While our treatments did not affect any floral trait measured, they non-additively impacted plant reproduction, with florivory having a larger overall impact than either nectar robbing or pollination.Conclusions. These results emphasize the importance of understanding the context in which flower-insect interactions occur, because the composition of the interacting community can have large and non-additive impacts on subsequent insect behavior and plant reproduction.If you would like your personal information to be removed from the database, please contact the publication office.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>anthocyanins|condensed tannins|factorial design|florivory|interactions|floral larceny|mutualism|nectar robbing|non-additive effects|pollination</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2018-10-31T16:12:58Z</date
></data>