<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.189795</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Global parasitic helminths &#8211; mammalian hosts association records</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>This data file contains association records of focal parasitic worm species (helminths) in different mammalian host species compiled from the publicly available Host-Parasite Database (http://www.nhm.ac.uk/research-curation/scientific-resources/taxonomy-systematics/host-parasites/) of the Natural History Museum (NHM), London (Gibson et al., 2005). Data extraction and revision is described in Wells et al. (2018). Location names were standardised to country names of the current world geopolitical map and assigned to one of 11 zoogeographical regions according to Holt et al. (2013). Unique host-parasite-country records are given for nine focal parasite species: Calodium hepaticum (Nematoda), Echinococcus granulosus (Cestoda), Echinococcus multilocularis (Cestoda), Hydatigera taeniaeformis (Cestoda), Hymenolepis diminuta (Cestoda), Mesocestoides lineatus (Cestoda), Taenia hydatigena (Cestoda), Trichinella spiralis (Nematoda) and Versteria mustelae (Cestoda). For records of non-focal parasitic helminth species in different host species and locations, binomial species names have been replaced with &#8220;0&#8221; to represent the full range mammal species with records of any parasitic helminth species (i.e. potential host species pools).  Column titles refer to the following content for serial records of host-parasite associations:Host.Species &#8211; Binomial name of mammalian host species for which an association has been recorded.Host.Order &#8211; Taxonomic order of host species.Parasite.Species - Binomial name of parasitic helminth species (nine focal species) for which an association has been recorded. Records of non-focal parasitic helminth species are indicated with &#8220;0&#8221;, including all records of mammalian host species in the original database in which the focal parasites were not recorded.  Parasite.Taxa &#8211; Taxonomic classification of parasitic helminth species.Location.Name &#8211; Name of the location of association record according to original database.Country &#8211; Country name matching the location name of association record according to contemporary world geopolitical map.Zoogeogr.Region &#8211; Zoogeographical region matching the location name of association record according to Holt et al. (2013).References:Gibson, D. I. et al.(Compilers) (2005). Host-Parasite Database of the Natural History Museum, London. http://www.nhm.ac.uk/research-curation/scientific-resources/taxonomy-systematics/host-parasites/index.html,Holt, B. G. et al. 2013. An update of Wallace&#8217;s zoogeographic regions of the world. &#8212; Science 339: 74-78. doi:10.1126/science.1228282,Wells, K. et al. (2018). Global spread of helminth parasites at the human &#8211; domestic animal &#8211; wildlife interface. &#8212; Global Change Biology 24: 3254-3265. doi:10.1111/gcb.14064,</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>host-parasite interactions|parasite global spread|environmental niche conservatism|host specificity|ecological fitting|helminths</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2018-08-15T10:50:14Z</date
></data>