<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.189495</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Data from: Social-ecological landscape patterns predict woody encroachment from native tree plantings in a temperate grassland</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Afforestation is often viewed as the purposeful planting of trees in historically non-forested grasslands, but an unintended consequence is woody encroachment, which should be considered part of the afforestation process. In North America&#8217;s temperate grassland biome, Eastern redcedar (Juniperus virginiana L.) is a native species used in tree plantings that aggressively invades in the absence of controlling processes. Cedar is a well-studied woody encroacher, but little is known about the degree to which cedar windbreaks, which are advocated for in agroforestry programs, are contributing to woody encroachment, what factors are associated with cedar spread from windbreaks, nor where encroachment from windbreaks is occurring in contemporary social&#8211;ecological landscapes. We used remotely sensed imagery to identify the presence and pattern of woody encroachment from windbreaks in the Nebraska Sandhills. We used multimodel inference to compare three classes of models representingthree hypotheses about factors that could influence cedar spread: (a) windbreak models based on windbreak structure and design elements, (b) abiotic models focused on local environmental conditions, and (c) landscape models characterizing coupled human-natural features within the broader matrix. Woody encroachment was evident for 22% of sampled windbreaks in the Nebraska Sandhills. Of our candidate models, our inclusive landscape model carried 92% of the model weight. This model indicated that encroachment from windbreaks was more likely near roadways and less likely near farmsteads, other cedar plantings, and waterbodies, highlighting strong social ties to the distribution of woody encroachment from tree plantingsacross contemporary landscapes. Cedar control efforts are insufficient for nearly one-quarter of windbreaks in the Nebraska Sandhills. Our model findings indicate where additional investments into cedar control can be prioritized to prevent cedar spread from windbreaks. This approach can serve as a model in other temperate regions to identify where woody encroachment resulting from temperate agroforestry programs is emerging.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>afforestation|agroforestry|tree planting|windbreak|woody encroachment</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2018-09-11T12:09:21Z</date
></data>