<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.171794</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Data from: Double-digest RAD sequencing outperforms microsatellite loci at assigning paternity and estimating relatedness: a proof of concept in a highly promiscuous bird</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Information on genetic relationships among individuals is essential to many studies of the behavior and ecology of wild organisms. Parentage and relatedness assays based on large numbers of SNP loci hold substantial advantages over the microsatellite markers traditionally used for these purposes. We present a double-digest restriction site-associated DNA sequencing (ddRAD-seq) analysis pipeline that, as such, simultaneously achieves the SNP discovery and genotyping steps and which is optimized to return a statistically powerful set of SNP markers (typically 150-600 after stringent filtering) from large numbers of individuals (up to 240 per run). We explore the tradeoffs inherent in this approach through a set of experiments in a species with a complex social system, the variegated fairy-wren (Malurus lamberti), and further validate it in a phylogenetically broad set of other bird species. Through direct comparisons with a parallel dataset from a robust panel of highly variable microsatellite markers, we show that this ddRAD-seq approach results in substantially improved power to discriminate among potential relatives and considerably more precise estimates of relatedness coefficients. The pipeline is designed to be universally applicable to all bird species (and with minor modifications to many other taxa), to be cost- and time-efficient, and to be replicable across independent runs such that genotype data from different study periods can be combined and analyzed as field samples are accumulated.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>double-digest restriction site-associated DNA sequencing (ddRAD-seq)|microsatellite|single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP)|relatedness|parentage|cooperative breeding</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2018-02-13T19:55:10Z</date
></data>