<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.201231</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Data from: Phylogeographic diversification and postglacial range dynamics shed light on the conservation of the kelp Saccharina japonica</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Studies of postglacial range shifts could enhance our understanding of seaweed species&#8217; responses to climate change, and hence facilitate the conservation of natural resources. However, the distribution dynamics and phylogeographic diversification of the commercially and ecologically important kelp Saccharina japonica in the Northwest Pacific (NWP) are still poorly surveyed. In this study, we analyzed the evolutionary history of S. japonica using two mitochondrial markers and 24 nuclear microsatellites. A STRUCTURE analysis revealed two partially isolated lineages: lineage H, which is scattered along the coast of Japan, and lineage P, which occurs along the west coast of the Japan Sea. Ecological niche modeling projections to the Last Glacial Maximum (LGM) revealed that the southern coasts of the Japan Sea and the Pacific side of the Oshima and Honshu Peninsulas provided the most suitable habitats for S. japonica, implying that these regions served as ancient refugia during the LGM. Ancient isolation in different refugia may explain the observed divergence between lineages P and H. An approximate Bayesian computation analysis indicated that the two lineages experienced post&#8208;LGM range expansion, and that postglacial secondary contact occurred in Sakhalin. Model projections into the year 2100 predicted that S. japonica will shift northwards and lose its genetic diversity center on the Oshima Peninsula in Hokkaido and Shimokita Peninsula in Honshu. The range shifts and evolutionary history of S. japonica improve our understanding of how climate change impacted the distribution range and diversity of this species and provide useful information for the conservation of natural resources under ongoing environmental change in the NWP.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject /><date
>2018-12-18T16:21:59Z</date
></data>