<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.162819</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Data from: Effect of Hf-doping on electrochemical performance of anatase TiO2 as an anode material for lithium storage</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>Hafnium-doped titania (Hf/Ti = 0.01, 0.03, 0.05) had been facilely synthesized via a template sol-gel method on carbon fiber. Physicochemical properties of the as-synthesized materials were characterized by X-ray diffraction, Raman spectroscopy, scanning electron microscopy, energy-dispersive X-ray analysis, scanning transmission electron microscopy, X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy, thermogravimetry analysis, and Brunauer&#8722;Emmett&#8722;Teller measurements. It was confirmed that Hf4+ substitute in the Ti4+ sites, forming Ti1&#8211;xHfxO2 (x = 0.01, 0.03, 0.05) solid solutions with an anatase crystal structure. The Ti1&#8211;xHfxO2 materials are hollow microtubes (length of 10&#8211;100 &#956;m, outer diameter of 1&#8211;5 &#956;m) composed of nanoparticles (average size of 15&#8211;20 nm) with surface area of 80&#8211;90 m2 g&#8211;1 and pore volume of 0.294&#8211;0.372 cm3 g&#8211;1. The effect of hafnium ions incorporation on electrochemical behavior of anatase TiO2 as Li-ion battery anode was investigated by galvanostatic charge/discharge and electrochemical impedance spectroscopy. It was established that Ti0.95Hf0.05O2 shows significantly higher reversibility (154.2 mAh g&#8211;1) after 35-fold cycling at C/10 rate in comparison with undoped titania (55.9 mAh g&#8211;1). The better performance offered by Hf4+ substitution of the Ti4+ into anatase TiO2 mainly results from more open crystal structure, which has been achieved via the difference in ionic radius values of Ti4+ (0.604 &#197;) and Hf4+ (0.71 &#197;). The obtained results are in a strong accordance with ones for anatase TiO2 doped via Zr4+ (0.72 &#197;) published earlier. Furthermore, improved electrical conductivity of Hf-doped anatase TiO2 materials due to charge redistribution in the lattice and enhanced interfacial lithium storage due to increased surface area directly depending on Hf/Ti atomic ratio have beneficial effect on electrochemical properties.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Li-ion battery|anatase TiO2|doping|anode|nanostructured material|sol-gel process</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2018-05-07T07:42:29Z</date
></data>