<data><id>oai:v1.datadryad.org:10255/dryad.189777</id><oai_dc:dc/dc:title>Data from: Tau imaging detects distinctive distribution of tau pathology in ALS/PDC on the Kii Peninsula</oai_dc:dc/dc:title><oai_dc:dc/dc:description>OBJECTIVE: To characterize the distribution of tau pathology in patients with amyotrophic lateral sclerosis/parkinsonism-dementia complex on the Kii Peninsula (Kii ALS/PDC) by tau PET using [11C]PBB3 as ligand.METHODS: This is a cross-sectional study of five patients with ALS/PDC and one asymptomatic participant with a dense family history of ALS/PDC from the Kii Peninsula who took part in this study. All were men, and their age was 76 &#177; 8 (mean &#177; SD) years. Thirteen healthy men (69 &#177; 6 years) participated as healthy controls (HCs). Dynamic PET scans were performed following injection of [11C]PBB3, and parametric PET images were generated by voxel-by-voxel calculation of binding potential (BPND) using a multilinear reference tissue model. [11C]PiB PET, MRI, and cognitive tests were also performed.RESULTS: A voxel-based comparison of [11C]PBB3 BPND illustrated PET-detectable tau deposition in the cerebral cortex and white matter, and pontine basis including the corticospinal tract in Kii ALS/PDC patients compared with HCs (uncorrected p &lt; 0.05). Group-wise VOI analysis of [11C]PBB3 BPND images showed increased BPND in the hippocampus and in frontal and parietal white matters of Kii ALS/PDC patients relative to HCs (p &lt; 0.05, Holm-Sidak multiple comparisons test). BPND in frontal, temporal, and parietal gray matters correlated with Mini-Mental State Examination scores in Kii ALS/PDC subjects (p &lt; 0.05). All Kii ALS/PDC patients were negative for [11C]PiB (amyloid &#946;) except one with marginal positivity.CONCLUSION: [11C]PBB3 PET visualized the characteristic topography of tau pathology in Kii ALS/PDC, corresponding to clinical phenotypes of this disease.</oai_dc:dc/dc:description><oai_dc:dc/dc:subject>Cognitive Disorders/Dementia|Alzheimer's disease|PET|Parkinson's disease/Parkinsonism|Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis</oai_dc:dc/dc:subject><date
>2018-12-18T19:54:58Z</date
></data>